- Remember George Washington,
you know how he died?
Well-meaning physicians bled him to death.
And this was the most important
patient in the country,
maybe in the history of the country.
And we bled him to death
trying to help him.
So when you're actually
inflating the money supply at 7%,
but you're calling it 2%
because you want to help the economy,
you're literally bleeding
the free market to death.
But the sad fact is George
Washington went along with it
'cause he thought that they
were gonna do him good.
And the majority of the
society, most companies,
most conventional thinkers,
the working class,
they go along with this because they think
that someone has their
best interest in mind.
And the people that are
bleeding them to death believe,
they believe that prescription
because their mental models
are just so defective.
- The following is a
conversation with Michael Saylor,
one of the most prominent and brilliant
Bitcoin proponents in the world.
He is the CEO of MicroStrategy,
founder of Saylor Academy,
graduate of MIT.
And Michael is one of the most fascinating
and rigorous thinkers
I've ever gotten a chance
to explore ideas with.
He can effortlessly zoom
out to the big perspectives
of human civilization and human history,
and zoom back in to the
technical details of blockchains,
markets, governments,
and financial systems.
This is the, "Lex Fridman Podcast."
To support it, please check out
our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends,
here's Michael Saylor.
Let's start with a big
question of truth and wisdom.
When advanced humans,
or aliens or AI systems,
let's say five to 10 centuries from now,
look back at Earth on
this early 21st century,
how much do you think they
would say we understood about
money and economics, or
even about engineering,
science, life, death,
meaning, intelligence,
consciousness, all the
big interesting questions?
- I think they would probably
give us a B- on engineering,
on all the engineering things.
The hard sciences.
- [Lex] A passing grade.
- Like we're doing okay.
We're working our way
through rockets and jets
and electric cars and
electricity, transport systems
and nuclear power and
space flight and the like.
And if you look at the walls
that grace the great court at MIT,
it's full of all the great thinkers
and they're all pretty admirable.
If you could be with Newton
or Gauss or Madam Curie
or Einstein, you would respect them.
I would say they'd give
us like a D- on economics.
Like an F+ or a D-.
- You see even an optimistic vision.
First of all, optimistic
vision of engineering
because everybody you've
listed, not everybody,
but most people you've listed
is just over the past couple of centuries
and maybe stretches a little farther back.
But mostly all the cool stuff
we've done in engineering,
is the past couple of centuries.
- I mean, Archimedes had his virtues.
(Lex chuckles)
I studied the history of science at MIT
and I also studied aerospace engineering,
and so I clearly have a
bias in favor of science.
And if I look at the past 10,000 years,
and I consider all of the
philosophy and the politics
and their impact on the human
condition, I think it's awash
for every politician that
came up with a good idea.
Another politician came
up with a bad idea,
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And it's not clear to me
that most of the political
and philosophical
contributions to the human race
and the human conditions
have advanced so much.
I mean, we're still taking guidance
and admiring Aristotle and
Plato and Seneca and the like.
And on the other hand if you think about
what has made the human condition better.
Fire, water, harnessing of wind energy.
Like try to row across an ocean, right?
Not easy.
- And for people who are
just listening or watching,
there's a beautiful, sexy
ship from 16th, 17th century.
- This is a 19th century handmade model
of a 17th century sailing
ship, which is of the type
that the Dutch East India Company
used to sail the world and trade.
So that was made, you
know, the original was made
sometime in the 1600s.
And then this model is made
in the 19th century by individuals.
- Both the model and the ship itself
is engineering at its best.
And just imagine just like
rock is flying out the space,
how much hope this filled people with,
exploring the unknown,
going into the mystery,
both the entrepreneurs
and the business people
and the engineers and just humans.
What's out there?
What's out there to be discovered?
- Yeah, the metaphor of human beings
leaving shore sailing across the horizon,
risking their lives in
pursuit of a better life
is a incredibly powerful one.
In 1900, I suppose the
average life expectancy is 50.
During the Revolutionary War,
while our founding fathers
were fighting to establish life, liberty,
pursuit of happiness, the constitution,
average life expectancy of it's like 32,
somewhere between 32 and 36.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So all the sound and the fury
doesn't make you live past
32, but what does, right?
Antibiotics.
Conquest of infectious diseases.
If we understand the science
of infectious disease.
Sterilizing a knife and
harnessing antibiotics
gets you from 50 to 70.
And that happened fast, right?
That happens from 1900 to
1950 or something like that.
And I think if you look
at the human condition,
you ever get on one of
those rowing machines
where they actually keep
track of your watts output
when you're on the-
- [Lex] Yeah.
- It's like 200 is a lot, okay?
200 is a lot.
So a kilowatt hour is like
all the energy that a human,
a trained athlete can deliver in a day.
And probably not 1% of
the people in the world
could deliver a kilowatt hour in a day.
And the commercial value
of a kilowatt hour,
the retail value is 11 cents today.
And the wholesale value is 2 cents.
And so you have to look
at the contribution
of politicians and
philosophers and economists
to the human condition.
And it's like at best of
wash one way or the other.
And then if you look at the contribution
of John D. Rockefeller
when he delivered you
a barrel of oil.
Yeah, and the energy
in oil, liquid energy,
or the contribution of Tesla,
as we deliver electricity.
And what's the impact
of the human condition
if I have electric power,
if I have chemical power,
if I have wind energy, if I can
actually set up a reservoir,
create a dam, spin a turbine,
and generate energy
from a hydraulic source,
that's extraordinary, right?
And so our ability to cross the ocean,
our ability to grow food,
our ability to live,
it's technology that gets the human race
from a brutal life where
life expectancy is 30
to a world where life expectancy is 80.
- You gave a D- to the economists,
so are they too like
the politicians, awash
in terms of there's good
ideas and bad ideas?
And that tiny delta between good and bad
is how you squeak past the
F+ onto the D- territory.
- I think most economic
ideas are bad ideas.
- [Lex] Most?
- Like take us back to
MIT and you wanna solve
a fluid dynamics problem.
Like design the shape of
the hull of that ship,
or you wanna design an air foil, a wing.
Or if you want to an engine
or a nozzle in a rocket ship,
you wouldn't do it with simple arithmetic,
you wouldn't do it with a scaler.
There's not a single number, right?
It's vector math,
computational fluid dynamics.
There's end dimensional,
higher level math,
complicated stuff.
So when an economist says
the inflation rate is 2%,
that's a scaler.
And when an economist
says it's not a problem
to print more money because
the velocity of the money
is very low, monetary velocity is low.
That's another scaler, okay?
So the truth of the matter
is inflation is not a scaler.
Inflation is an indimensional vector.
Money velocity is not a scaler.
Saying, what's the velocity of money?
Oh, it's slow or it's fast.
It ignores the question of
what medium is the money
moving through in the same way
that what's the speed of sound?
Okay, well, what is sound, right?
Sound is a compression wave.
It's energy moving through a medium,
but the speed is different.
So for example, the speed of
sound through air is different
than the speed of sound through water.
And sound moves faster through water,
it moves faster through a solid,
and it moves faster
through a stiffer solid.
So there isn't one.
- What is the fundamental
problem with the way
economists reduce the
world down to a model?
Is it too simple or is it
just even the first principles
of constructing the model is wrong?
- I think that the fundamental problem
is if you see the world as a scaler,
you simply pick the one number
which supports whatever you wanna do,
and you ignore the universe
of other consequences
from your behavior.
- In general, I don't know
if you've heard of like Eric Watson
has been talking about
this with gauge theory.
So different kinds of approaches
from the physics world,
from the mathematical world
to extend past this
scaler view of economics.
So gauge theory is one way
that comes from physics.
Do you find that way of
exploring economics interesting?
So outside of cryptocurrency,
outside of the extra
technologies and so on,
just analysis of how economics works,
do you find that interesting?
- Yeah, I think that if we're gonna
wanna really make any scientific
progress in economics,
we have to apply much more
computationally intensive
and richer forms of mathematics.
- So, simulation perhaps?
- Yeah, when I was at MIT,
I studied system dynamics,
they taught it at the Sloan School.
It was developed by Jay Forrester,
who was an extraordinary
computer scientist.
And when we created models
of economic behavior,
they were all multidimensional
non-linear models.
So if you wanna describe
how anything works
in the real world, you have to start
with the concept of feedback.
If I double the price of
something, demand will fall
and attempts to create
supply will increase,
and there will be a delay
before the capacity increases.
There'll be an instant demand change,
and there'll be rippling effects
throughout every other
segment of the economy
downstream and upstream of such thing.
So it's kind of common
sense, but most economics,
most classical economics,
it's always taught
with linear models, fairly
simplistic linear models.
And oftentimes even I'm
really shocked today
that the entire mainstream
dialogue of economics
has been captured by scale or arithmetic.
For example, if you read any
article in New York Times
or the Wall Street Journal, right?
They just refer to there's
an inflation number
or the CPI or the inflation rate is X.
And if you look at all
the historic studies
of the impact of inflation,
generally they're all based
upon the idea that inflation equals CPI
and then they try to
extrapolate from that,
and you just get nowhere with it.
- So at the very least, we
should be considering inflation
and other economics concept
is a non-linear dynamical system.
So non-linearity, and also just embracing
the full complexity of just
how the variables interact,
maybe through simulation, maybe have some
interesting models around that.
- Wouldn't it be refreshing
if somebody for once
published a table of the change
in price of every product,
every service, and every asset
and every place over time?
- You said table.
Some of that also is the
task of visualization.
How to extract from this
complex set of numbers,
patterns that somehow indicate
something fundamental
about what's happening.
Summarization of data is still important.
Perhaps summarization not down
to a single scale of value,
but looking at that whole sea of numbers,
you have to find patterns
like what is inflation
in a particular sector, what
is maybe change over time,
maybe different geographical
regions, things of that nature.
I think that's kinda, I don't
know even what that task is.
That's what you could
look at machine learning,
you can look at AI with that
perspective, which is like,
how do you represent what's
happening efficiently
as efficiently as possible?
That's never going to be a single number,
but it might be a compressed model
that captures something,
something beautiful,
something fundamental
about what's happening.
- It's an opportunity for sure, right?
You know, if we take, for
example, during the pandemic,
the response of the political apparatus
was to lower interest rates to zero
and to start buying assets,
in essence printing money.
And the defense was there's no inflation.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But of course you had
one part of the economy
where it was locked down, so
it was illegal to buy anything,
but you couldn't, you
know, it was either illegal
or it was impractical,
so it would be impossible
for demand to manifest, so of
course there is no inflation.
On the other hand, there was instantaneous
immediate inflation in
another part of the economy.
For example, you lower the
interest rates to zero.
At one point we saw the
swap rate on a 30 year note
go to 72 basis points, okay?
That means that the value
of a long dated bond immediately inflates.
So the bond market had hyperinflation
within minutes of these
financial decisions.
The asset market had hyperinflation.
We had what you call a K shape recovery,
what we affectionately
call a K shape recovery.
Main Street shut down,
Wall Street recovered
all within six weeks.
The inflation was in the
assets, like in the stocks,
in the bonds.
If you look today, you
see that typical house
according to the Case-Shiller index today
is up 19.2% year over year.
So if you're a first time home buyer,
the inflation rate is 19%.
The formal CPI announced as 7.9%.
You can pretty much create
any inflation rate you want
by constructing a market basket,
a weighted basket of products
or services or assets
that yield you the answer.
I think that the fundamental
failing of economists
is first of all, they
don't really have a term
for asset inflation, right?
- What's an asset?
What's asset hyperinflation?
You mentioned bond market
swap rate and asset
is where the majority of
the hyperinflation happen.
What's inflation?
What's hyperinflation?
What's an asset?
What's an asset market?
And I'm gonna ask so many dumb questions.
- In the conventional economic world,
you would treat inflation as
the rate of increase in price
of a market basket of consumer products
defined by a government agency, okay?
- So they have a, like traditional things
that a regular consumer would be buying.
The government selects
like toilet paper, food,
toaster, refrigerator, electronics,
all that kind of stuff.
And it's like a
representative basket of goods
that lead to a content
existence on this earth
for a regular consumer.
- They define a synthetic metric, right?
I mean, I'm gonna say you should have
a thousand square foot apartment
and you should have a used car
and you should eat
three hamburgers a week.
Now, 10 years go by and
the apartment costs more.
I could adjust the market
basket by a, you know,
they call 'em hedonic adjustments.
I could decide that it used to be a 1970
needed a thousand square feet,
but in the year 2020, you
only need 700 square feet
because we've miniaturized televisions
and we've got more efficient
electric appliances
and because things have
collapsed into the iPhone,
you just don't need as much space.
So now it may be that the
apartment costs 50% more,
but after the hedonic
adjustment, there is no inflation
because I just downgraded the expectation
of what a normal person should have.
- So the synthetic nature of the metric
allows for manipulation
by people in power.
- (chuckles) Pretty much.
I guess my criticism of economist
is rather than embracing inflation
based upon its fundamental
idea, which is the rate
at which the price of things go up, right?
They've been captured by
mainstream conventional thinking
to immediately equate inflation
to the government issued CPI
or government issued PCE or
government issued PPI measure,
which was never the rate
at which things go up,
it's simply the rate at which
a synthetic basket of products
and services the government
wishes to track go up.
Now the problem with
that is two big things.
One thing is the government
gets to create the market basket,
and so they keep changing
what's in the basket over time.
So I mean, if I said three years ago,
you should go see 10 concerts a year,
and the concert tickets
now cost $200 each.
Now it's $2,000 a year to go see concerts.
Now I'm in charge of
calculating inflation,
so I redefine your
entertainment quota for the year
to be eight Netflix streaming concerts.
And now they don't cost $2,000,
they cost nothing and
there is no inflation,
but you don't get your concerts, right?
So the problem starts
with continually changing
the definition of the market basket,
but in my opinion, that's
not the biggest problem.
The more egregious problem
is the fundamental idea
that assets aren't products or services.
A assets can't be inflated.
- [Lex] What's an asset?
- A house, a share of Apple stock, a bond.
A Bitcoin is an asset
or a Picasso painting.
- Not a consumable good?
- [Michael] Yeah.
- Not a apple that you can eat.
- Right, if I throw away an
asset, then I'm not on the hook
to track the inflation rate for it.
So what happens if I change
the policy such that,
let's take the classic example.
A million dollar bond
at a 5% interest rate
gives you $50,000 a year
in risk-free income,
you might retire on $50,000 a year
in a low cost jurisdiction.
So the cost of social
security or early retirement
is $1 million when the
interest rate is 5%.
During the crisis of March of 2020,
the interest rate on a 10-year bond
went to 50 basis points, okay?
So now the cost of that
bond is $10 million, okay?
The cost of social security
went from a million
dollars to $10 million.
So if you wanted to work
your entire life, save money,
and then retire risk free
and live happily ever after
on a $50,000 salary living
on a beach in Mexico,
wherever you wanted to go,
you had hyperinflation,
the cost of your aspiration
increased by a factor of 10
over the course of some amount of time.
In fact, in that case, that was like
over the course of about 12 years, right?
As the inflation rate ground
down, the asset traded up.
But the conventional view
is, oh, that's not a problem
because it's good that assets,
it's good that the bond is highly priced
because we own the bond.
Or what's the problem
with the inflation rate
in housing being 19%?
It's an awful problem for a 22-year-old
that's starting their first job
that's saving money to buy a house.
But it would be characterized
as a benefit to society
by a conventional economist who would say,
"Well, housing asset values are higher
because of interest rate fluctuation
and now the economy's got more wealth."
And so, that's viewed as a benefit.
- What's being missed here?
Like the suffering of the
average person or the struggle,
the suffering, the pain
of the average person,
like metrics that captured
that within the economic system
When you're talking about-
- What I'm going to say,
it is a conventional
view of inflation as CPI
understates the human
misery that's inflicted
upon the working class and
on mainstream companies
by the political class.
And so it's a massive shift to wealth
from the working class
to the property class.
It's a massive shift to
power from the free market
to the centrally governed
or the controlled market.
It's a massive shift to power
from the people to the government.
And maybe one more
illustrative point here, Lex,
is what do you think the inflation rate's
been for the past a hundred years?
- Oh, we talking about the scaler again?
- If you took a survey of
everybody on the street
and you asked them what do
they think inflation was,
what is it?
You remember when Jerome Powell said,
our target's 2%, but we're not there.
If you go around the corner,
I have posted the deed
to this house sold in 1930, okay?
And the number on that
deed is $100,000, 1930.
And if you go on Zillow
and you get the Zestimate,
- Is it higher than that?
No?
- [Michael] $30,500,000.
- Yeah.
- So that's 92 years.
1930 or 2022.
(Lex chuckles)
And in 92 years we've had 305X increase
in price of the house.
Now if you actually back calculate,
you come to a conclusion
that the inflation rate
was approximately 6.5% a year
every year for 92 years, okay?
And there's nobody, nobody in government,
no conventional economists
who would ever admit
to an inflation rate of 7% a year
in the US dollar over the last century.
Now, if you dig deeper, I mean one guy
that's done a great job working
on this is Saidedean Ammous,
who wrote the book,
"The Bitcoin Standard."
And he notes that on average
it looks like the inflation
rate and the money supply
is about 7% a year all the
way up to the year 2020.
If you look at the S&P index,
which is a market basket
of scarce desirable stocks,
it returned about 10%.
If you talk to 10% a
year for a hundred years.
The money supply is expanding
at 7% a hundred years.
If you actually talk to economists
or you look at the economy
and you ask the question,
how fast does the economy grow
in its entirety year over year?
Generally about two to 3%.
Like the sum total impact
of all this technology
and human ingenuity might
get you a two and a half,
3% improvement a year
- As measured by GDP.
Are you okay with that measure?
- I'm not sure I go that far
yet, but I would just say
that if you had the
human race doing stuff.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And if you ask the question,
how much more efficiently
will we do the stuff
next year than this year,
or what's the value of
all of our innovations
and inventions and investments
in the past 12 months?
You'd be hard pressed to
say, we get 2% better.
Typical investor thinks
they're 10% better every year.
So if you look at what's going on,
really when you're holding
a million dollars of stocks
and you're getting a 10% gain a year,
you're really get a 7%
expansion of the money supply.
You're getting a two or 3%
gain under best circumstances.
And another way to say
that is if the money supply
stopped expanding at 7% a year,
the S&P yield might be 3% and not 10%.
It probably should be.
Now, that gets you to start to ask a bunch
of other fundamental questions
like if I borrow a billion
dollars and pay 3% interest
and the money supply expands
at seven to 10% a year,
and I ended up making a 10% return
on a billion dollar
investment, paying 3% interest.
Is that fair?
And who suffered?
So that I could do that
because in an environment
where you're just
inflating the money supply
and you're holding the assets constant,
it stands the reason that
the price of all the assets
is going to appreciate
somewhat proportional
to the money supply.
And the difference in asset appreciations
is gonna be a function of the scarce,
desirable quality of the assets,
and to what extent can
I make more of them,
and to what extent are they
truly limited in supply?
- Yeah, so we'll get to a lot
of the words you said there.
The scarcity and so connected
to how limited they are
and the value of those assets.
But you also said, so the
expansion of the money supply,
which is put another
way is printing money.
And so is that always bad?
The expansion of the money supply is this,
just to put some terms on the
table so we understand them.
You nonchalantly say it's always the,
on average expanding every year,
the money supply is
expanding every year by 7%.
That's a bad thing.
That's a universally a bad thing.
- It's awful.
I guess to be precise,
it's the currency that,
I mean, money, I would say money
is monetary energy or economic energy.
And the economic energy has
to find its way into a medium.
So if you wanna move it rapidly
as a medium of exchange,
it has to find its way into currency,
but the money can also flow into property
like a house or gold.
If the money flows into property,
it'll probably hold its value much better
if the money flows into currency, right?
If you had put a hundred
thousand dollars in this house,
you would have 305X return over 92 years.
But if you had put the money,
a hundred thousand dollars
into safe deposit box
and buried it in the basement,
you would've lost 99.7% of your wealth
over the same time period.
So, the expansion of the currency
creates a massive
inefficiency in the society,
what I'll call an adiabatic lapse.
It's what we're doing is we're bleeding
the civilization to death, right?
- What's the, adiabatic, what's that word?
- [Michael] Adiabatic lapse.
- Adiabatic.
- Right, and aerospace engineering,
you wanna solve any problem,
they start with the phrase,
assume an adiabatic system.
And what that means is a closed system,
- [Lex] Okay, I've got it.
- So, I've got a container,
and in that container no air leaves
and no air enters, no
energy exits or enters,
so it's a closed system.
- So you got the closed system lapse?
- [Michael] Okay.
(Lex laughs)
Okay, I'm gonna use a.
- There's a leak in the ship.
- [Michael] I'm gonna use
a physical metaphor for you
'cause you're the jujutsu, right?
- Yeah.
- Like you got 10 pints
of blood in your body.
And so before your next workout,
I'm gonna take one pint from you.
Now you're gonna go exercise,
but you've lost 10% of your blood, okay?
You're not gonna perform as well.
It takes about one month for your body
to replace the red blood platelets.
So what if I tell you every month
you gotta show up and I'm gonna bleed you?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Okay, so if I'm draining the energy,
I'm draining the blood from your body.
You can't perform.
Adiabatic lapse is when
you go up an altitude.
Every thousand feet,
you lose three degrees.
You go at 50,000 feet,
you're 150 degrees colder than sea level.
That's why you look at your instruments
and instead of 80 degrees,
you're minus 70 degrees.
Why is the temperature falling?
Temperature's falling because
it's not a closed system,
it's an open system.
As the air expands, the
density falls, right?
The energy per cubic, whatever, falls,
and therefore the
temperature falls, right?
The heat's falling outta the solution.
So when you're inflating,
let's say you're inflating
the currency supply by 6%,
you're sucking 6% of the
energy out of the fluid
that the economy is using to function.
- So the currency, this
kind of ocean of currency,
that's a nice way for
the economy to function.
It's the most kind of,
it's being inefficient
when you expand the money supply,
but it's the liquid, I'm trying to find
the right kind of adjective here.
It's how you do transactions
at a scale of billions.
- Currency is the asset we use
to move monetary energy around.
And you could use the dollar
or you could use the peso
or you could use the bolivar.
- Selling houses and buying
houses is much more inefficient.
Or like you can't transact between
billions of people with houses.
- Yeah, properties don't make
such good mediums of exchange.
They make better stores of value
and they have utility value
if it's a ship or a house or a plane
or a bushel of corn, right?
- Can I zoom out just for-
- [Michael] Yeah.
- Can we zoom out, keep zooming out
until we reach the origin
of human civilization.
But on the way ask, you
gave economists a D-,
I'm not even gonna ask you
what you give to governments.
Do you think their failure,
economists' and government failure
is malevolence or incompetence?
- I think policy makers
are well intentioned,
but generally all government
policy is inflationary
and all government, it's
inflammatory and inflationary.
So what I mean by that
is when you have a policy
pursuing supply chain independence,
if you have an energy policy,
if you have a labor policy,
if you have a trade policy,
if you have any kind
of foreign policy, a domestic policy,
a manufacturing policy, a medical policy,
every one of these policies
interferes with the free market
and generally prevents some rational actor
from doing it in a cheaper,
more efficient way.
So when you layer them
on top of each other,
they all have to be paid for.
If you want to shut down the
entire economy for a year,
you have to pay for it, right?
If you wanna fight a war, you
have to pay for it, right?
If you don't want to
use oil or natural gas,
you have to pay for it.
If you don't wanna manufacture
semiconductors in China
and you want to
manufacture them in the US,
you gotta pay for it.
If I rebuild the entire
supply chain in Pennsylvania
and I hire a bunch of employees
and then I unionize the employees,
then not only am I idle the
factory in the far east,
it goes to 50% capacity,
so whatever it sells, it
has to raise the price on.
And then I drive up the cost of labor
for every other manufacturer in the US
because I competing against them, right?
I'm changing their condition.
So everything gets less efficient,
everything gets more expensive.
And of course the government couldn't pay
for its policies and its wars with taxes.
We didn't pay for World War I with tax,
we didn't pay for World War II with tax,
we didn't pay for Vietnam with tax.
In fact, when you trace this,
what you realize is the government
never pays for all of
its policies with tax.
It pays for-
- Because it's too painful
to ask to raise the taxes
to truly transparently pay
for the things you're doing
with taxes with taxpayer money,
'cause they feel the pain.
- Either that's one interpretation
or it's just too transparent.
If people understood the true cost-
- Of war.
They wouldn't want to go to war.
- If you were told that you
would lose 95% of your assets,
and 90% of everything you will be ever
will be taken from you, you
might reprioritize your thought
about a given policy
and you might not vote
for that politician.
- But you're still saying
incompetence not malevolence.
So fundamentally, government
creates a bureaucracy
of incompetence is kind
of how you look at it.
- I think a lack of humility, right?
Like, if people had more
humility than they would realize-
- Humility about how little they know,
how little they understand about
the function of complex systems.
- It's a phrase from Clint
Eastwood's movie, "Unforgiven,"
where he says, "A man's
gotta know his limitations."
(Lex chuckles)
I think that a lot of people overestimate
what they can accomplish
and experience in life
causes you to reevaluate that.
So, I mean I've done a
lot of things in my life
and generally my mistakes
were always my good ideas
that I enthusiastically
pursued to the detriment
of my great ideas that required 150%
of my attention to prosper.
So I think people pursue
too many good ideas
and they all sound good,
but there's just a limit
to what you can accomplish.
And everybody underestimates
the challenges
of implementing an idea, right?
And they always overestimate
the benefits of the pursuit of that.
And so I think it's an overconfidence
that causes an overexuberance
in pursuit of policies.
And as the ambition of
the government expands,
so must the currency supply.
Well, I could say the money supply,
but let's say the currency supply.
You can triple the number
of pesos in the economy,
but it doesn't triple the amount
of manufacturing capacity
in the said economy.
And it doesn't triple the
amount of assets in the economy.
It just triples the pesos.
So as you increase the currency supply,
then the price of all those
scarce desirable things
will tend to go up rapidly.
And the confidence of
all of the institutions,
the corporations and the individual actors
and trading partners will collapse.
- If we take a tangent on a
tangent, and we will return
soon to the big human
civilization question.
So if government naturally wants
to buy stuff it can't afford,
what's the best form of government?
Anarchism, libertarianism.
There's not even armies,
there's no borders.
That's anarchism.
- [Michael] The least. (chuckles)
- The smallest possible.
- The best government would be the least.
And the debate will be over that.
- When you think about this
stuff, do you think about,
okay, government is the way it is,
I as a person that can
generate great ideas,
how do I operate in this world?
Or do you also think
about the big picture?
If we start a new civilization
somewhere on Mars,
do you think about what's the
ultimate form of government?
What's at least a promising thing to try?
- I have laser eyes on my
profile on Twitter, Lex.
- [Lex] Yes, I noticed.
What does that mean?
- And the significance of laser eyes
is to focus on the thing
that can make a difference.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And if I look at the civilization,
I would say half the
problems in the civilization
are due to the fact that our understanding
of economics and money is defective.
Half, 50%.
I don't know, it's worth $500
trillion worth of problems.
Like money represents
all the economic energy
and the civilization
and it kind of equates
to all the products, all the
services and all the assets
that we have and wherever
we're gonna have.
So, that's half.
The other half of the
problems in the civilization
are medical and military and political
and philosophical and natural.
And I think that there are a lot
of different solutions
to all those problems.
And they are all honorable professions
and they all merit a
lifetime of consideration
for the specialist in all those areas.
I think that what I could
offer it's constructive is
inflation is completely misunderstood.
It's a much bigger problem
than we understand it to be.
We need to introduce engineering
and science techniques into economics
if we wanna further the human condition.
All government policy is inflationary.
And another pernicious myth is inflation
is always and everywhere
a monetary phenomena.
So, a famous quote by
Milton Friedman, I believe.
It's like, "It's a monetary phenomena."
That is inflation comes from
expanding the currency supply.
It's a nice phrase and
it's oftentimes quoted
by people that are anti inflation.
But again, it just signifies
a lack of appreciation
of what the issue is.
Inflation is.
If I had a currency which was
completely non-inflationary,
if I never printed another dollar
and if I eliminated
fractional reserve banking
from the face of the earth,
we'd still have inflation.
And we'd have inflation as
long as we have government
that is capable of pursuing
any kind of policies
that are in them self inflationary.
And generally they all are.
- So in general, inflationary
is the big characteristic
of human nature that
governments, collection of groups
that have power over others and allocate
other people's resources
will try to intentionally
or not hide the costs of those allocations
like in some tricky ways.
Whatever the options ever available.
- Hiding the cost is
like the tertiary thing.
Like the primary goal is the government
will attempt to do good, right?
- [Lex] And that's the primary problem.
- They will attempt to do good
and they will do good imperfectly
and they will create
oftentimes as much damage,
more damage than the good they do.
Most government policy will be iatrogenic,
it will create more harm than
good in the pursuit of it,
but it is what it is.
The secondary issue is they
will unintentionally pay for it
by expanding the currency
supply without realizing
that they're actually paying
for it in a suboptimal fashion.
They'll collapse their own currencies
while they attempt to do good.
The tertiary issue is they will mismeasure
how badly they're collapsing the currency.
So for example, if you go to
the Bureau of Labor Statistics,
and look at the numbers printed
by the Fed, they'll say,
"Oh, it looks like the dollars lost 95%
of its purchasing power
over a hundred years."
Okay, they sort of fess
up there's a problem,
but they make it 95% loss
over a hundred years.
What they don't do is realize
it's a 99.7% loss over 80 years,
so they will mismeasure
just the horrific extent
of the monetary policy in pursuit
of the foreign policy
and the domestic policy,
which they overestimate their budget
and their means to accomplish their ends
and they underestimate the cost
and they're oblivious
to the horrific damage
that they do to the civilization
because the mental models that they use
that are conventionally
taught are wrong, right?
The mental model that like, it's okay,
we can print all this money
because the velocity of
the money is low, right?
Because money velocity is a scaler
and inflation is the scaler
and we don't see 2% inflation yet,
and the money velocity is low,
and so it's okay if we
print trillions of dollars.
Well, the money velocity
was immediate, right?
The velocity of money
through the crypto economy
is 10,000 times faster
than the velocity of money
through the consumer economy, right?
I think Nick pointed out
when you spoke to him,
he said it takes two months
for a credit card
transaction to settle, right?
So you wanna spend a million dollars
in the consumer economy, you
can move it six times a year.
You put a million dollars into gold,
gold will sit in a vault for a decade.
Okay, so the velocity of
money through gold is 0.1.
You put the money in the stock market
and you can trade it once a week.
The settlement is t plus two.
Maybe you get to two to one leverage.
You might get to a money velocity
of a hundred a year in the stock market.
You put your money into the crypto economy
and these people are
settling every four hours.
And if you're offshore, they're
trading with 20X leverage.
So if you settle every day and
you trade with 20X leverage,
you just went to 7,000.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So the velocity of the money varies.
I think the politicians,
they don't really understand inflation
and they don't understand economic.
But you can't blame 'em
because the economists
don't understand economics
because if they did,
they would be creating
multi-variate computer simulations
where they actually put in the price
of every piece of housing
in every city in the world,
the full array of foods and
the full array of products
and the full array of assets.
And then on a monthly basis
they would publish all those results.
And that's a high bandwidth requirement.
And I think that people don't
really wanna embrace it.
And also there's the
most pernicious thing.
Like there's that phrase, you know,
"You can't tell people what to think,
but you can tell 'em what to think about."
The most pernicious thing is I get you
to misunderstand the phenomena,
so that even when it's happening to you,
you don't appreciate that it's a bad thing
and you think it's a good thing.
So if housing prices are
going up 20% year over year,
and I say this is great
for the American public
'cause most of 'em are homeowners,
then I have misrepresented a phenomena,
inflation is 20%, not 7%.
And then I have misrepresented it
as being a positive
rather than a negative.
And people will stare at it
and you could even show
them their house on fire
and they would perceive it as being great
because it's warming them up
and they're gonna save on their heat cost.
- It does seem that the
cruder of the model,
whether it's economics,
whether it's psychology,
the easier it is to weave
whatever the heck narrative you want.
And not in a malicious way,
but just like it's some kind
of like emergent phenomena,
this narrative thing that
would tell ourselves.
So you can tell any kind
of story about inflation.
Inflation is good, inflation is bad.
Like the crude of the model,
the easier just to tell
a narrative about it.
So like if you take an
engineering approach,
I feel like it's becomes
more and more difficult
to run away from sort of
a true deep understanding
of the dynamics of the system.
- I mean, honestly, if you went
to a hundred people on the street
and you asked them to define inflation,
how many would say it's a vector
tracking the change in price
of every product service
asset in the world over time?
- [Lex] No.
- Not many.
- [Lex] Not many.
- Now if you went to them and you said,
do you think 2% inflation
a year is good or bad?
The majority would probably say,
"Well, here it's good."
- Yeah.
- The majority of economists
would say 2% inflation a year is good.
And of course there's look
at the ship next to us.
What if I told you that
the ship leaked 2%, right,
of its volume every something, right?
The ship is rotting 2% a year.
That means the useful life
of the ship is 50 years.
Now, ironically, that's true.
Like a wooden ship had a 50
year to a hundred year life.
A hundred would be long,
50 years not unlikely.
So when we built ships outta wood,
they had a useful life of about 50 years
and then they sunk, they rotted.
There's nothing good about it, right?
You build a ship out of steel,
and it's zero as opposed
to 2% degradation.
And how much better is 0% versus 2%?
Well, 2% means you have a
useful life of, you know,
it's half life of 35 years.
2% is a half life of 35 years.
That's basically the half
life of money and gold.
If I store your life force in gold,
under perfect circumstances,
you have a useful life of 35 years.
0% is a useful life of forever.
So 0% is immortal,
2% is 35 years average life expectancy.
So, the idea that you would think
the life expectancy of the currency
and the civilization should be 35 years
instead of forever is
kind of a silly notion.
But the tragic notion is it
was seven into 70 or 10 years.
It's the money has had
a half life of 10 years
except for the fact that in
weak societies and in Argentina
or the like, the half life of the money
is three to four years,
in Venezuela one year.
So the United States dollar
and the United States economic system
was the most successful economic system
in the last a hundred years in the world.
We won every war, we were
the world superpower.
Our currency lost 99.7% of its value.
And that means horrifically
every other currency lost everything.
In essence, the other ones were 99.9,
except for most that were 100%
because they all completely failed.
And you've got a mainstream
economic community
that thinks that inflation is
a number and 2% is desirable.
It's kind of like, you know,
remember George Washington,
you know how he died?
- [Lex] No.
- Well-meaning physicians
bled him to death.
- [Lex] Hmm.
- Okay.
The last thing in the
world you would want to do
to a sick person is bleed them, right?
In the modern world, I think we understand
that oxygen is carried by the blood cells.
There's that phrase, right?
Triage phrase.
What's the first thing
you do in an injury?
Stop the bleeding.
Single first thing, right?
You show up after any
accident, I look at you,
stop the bleeding, because
you're gonna be dead
in a matter of minutes if you bleed out.
So, it strikes me as being ironic
that orthodox conventional wisdom
was bleed the patient to death.
And this was the most important
patient in the country,
maybe in the history of the country.
And we bled him to death
trying to help him.
So when you're actually
inflating the money supply at 7%,
but you're calling it 2%
because you want to help the economy,
you're literally bleeding
the free market to death.
But the sad fact is George
Washington went along with it
'cause he thought that they
were gonna do him good.
And the majority of the
society, most companies,
most conventional thinkers,
the working class,
they go along with this because they think
that someone has their
best interest in mind.
And the people that are
bleeding them to death believe,
they believe that prescription
because their mental models
are just so defective.
And then understanding
of energy and engineering
and the economics that are at play
is crippled by these mental models.
- But that's both the bug in the future
of human civilization
that ideas take hold.
They unite us, we believe in them,
and we make a lot of cool stuff happen.
By as an average sort of
just the fact of the matter,
a lot of people believe the same thing.
They get together and
they get some shit done
because they believe that thing.
And then some ideas can be really bad
and really destructive.
But on average, the ideas
seem to be progressing
in a direction of good.
Let me just step back.
What the hell are we doing here?
Us humans on this earth.
How do you think of humans?
How special are humans?
How did human civilization
originate on this earth?
And what is this human project
they we're all taking on?
You mentioned fire and water
and apparently bleeding you
to death is not a good idea.
I always thought you can get
the demons out in that way,
but that was a recent invention.
So, what's this thing we're doing here?
- I think what distinguishes human beings
from all the other creatures on the earth
is our ability to engineer.
We're engineers, right?
- To solve problems or just
build incredible cool things?
- Engineering, harnessing
energy and technique
to make the world a better
place than you found it.
Right, from the point
that we actually started
to play with fire, right?
That was a big leap forward.
Harnessing the power of
kinetic energy and missiles,
another step forward.
Every city built on water.
Why water?
Well, water's bringing energy, right?
If you actually put a turbine on a river
or you capture a change
in elevation of water,
you've literally harnessed
gravitational energy.
But water's also bringing you food.
It's also giving you a cheap form
of getting rid of your waste.
It's also giving you free transportation.
You wanna move one ton blocks around,
you want to move them in water.
So I think, I mean the human story
is really the story of
engineering a better world.
And the rise in the human condition
is determined by those groups of people,
those civilizations that were
best at harnessing energy.
Right, if you look, you
know, the Greek civilization,
they built it around ports and sea ports
and water and created a trading network.
The Romans were really good
at harnessing all sorts of engineering.
I mean, the aqueducts are a great example.
If you go to any big city,
you travel through cities in the Med,
you find that the carrying
capacity of the city
or the island is 5,000
people without running water.
And then if you can find
a way to bring water to it
increases by a factor of 10.
And so human flourishing
is really only possible
through that channeling of energy, right?
That eventually takes the
form of air power, right?
I mean that ship, I mean,
look at the intricacy
of those sails, right?
I mean, it's just the model is intricate.
Now think about all of the
experimentation that took place
to figure out how many
sails to put on that ship
and how to rig them and how to repair them
and how to operate them.
- There's thousands of lives spent
thinking through all
the tiny little details
all to increase the efficiency
of this, the effectiveness,
the efficiency of this
ship as it sails to water.
And we should also note
that there's a bunch
of cannons on the side.
So obviously-
- Another form of engineering, right?
Energy harnessing with explosives.
- To achieve what end.
That's another discussion, exactly.
- [Michael] Suppose we're trying
to get off the planet, right?
- Well, there's a selection
mechanism going on.
So natural selection, this whatever,
however evolution works, it seems that one
of the interesting inventions on earth
was the predator-prey dynamic,
that you want to be the bigger fish.
That violence seems to
serve a useful purpose
if you look at earth as a whole.
We as humans now like to think of violence
as really a bad thing.
It seems to be one of the
amazing things about humans
is we're ultimately tend
towards cooperation.
We want to, we like peace.
If you just look at
history, we want things
to be nice and calm
but just wars break out
every once in a while and
lead to immense suffering
and destruction and so on.
And they have a kind of like
resetting the palate effect.
It's one that's full of just
immeasurable human suffering.
But it's like a way to start over.
- We're clearly the apex
predator on the planet.
And I googled something the other day,
what's the most common form
of mammal life on the earth?
- By number of organisms?
- [Michael] Count.
- By count.
- And the answer that came
back was human beings.
I was shocked.
I couldn't believe it, right?
It says like apparently if
we're just looking at mammals,
the answer was human
beings are the most common.
Which was very interesting to me.
I almost didn't believe
it, but I was trying to,
you know, 8 billion or so human beings.
- Yeah, it's a lot.
- There's no other mammal
that's got more than 8 billion.
If you walk through downtown
Edinburgh and Scotland,
and you look up on this hill
and there's castle up on the hill,
and you talk to people and the story is,
"Oh yeah, well, that was
a British castle before.
It was a Scottish castle
before it was a pick castle,
before it was a Roman castle,
before it was some other
Celtic castle before it was a."
Then they found 13 prehistoric castles
buried one under the other.
And you get the conclusion
that a hundred thousand
years ago, somebody showed up
and grabbed the high point,
the apex of the city,
and they built a stronghold there
and they flourished and
their family flourished
and their tribe flourished
until someone came along
and knocked him off the hill.
And it's been a nonstop never ending fight
by the aggressive, most
powerful entity, family,
organization, municipality,
tribe, whatever.
- [Lex] Off the hill.
- For that one hill going
back since time in memorial.
And you scratch your head and you think,
"It seems like it's like just
this never ending wheel."
- But does not lead if you
just all kinds of metrics
that seems to improve the quality
of our cannons and ships as a result.
Like it seems that just
like your laser eyes
focuses the mind on the engineering tasks.
- It is that, and it does remind you
that the winner is
always the most powerful.
And we throw that phrase out,
but no one thinks about
what that phrase means.
Like who's the most powerful
or the most powerful side won,
but they don't think about it
and they think about power,
energy delivered in a period of time.
And then you think a guy with a spear
is more powerful than
someone with their fist
and someone with a bow
and arrow is more powerful
than the person with the spear.
And then you realize
that somebody with bronze
is more powerful than without,
and steel is more powerful than bronze.
And if you look at the Romans,
they persevered with artillery
and they could stand off from 800 meters
and blast you to smithereens, right?
You study the history of the
Balearic slingers, right?
And you think we invented bullets,
but they invented bullets to put in slings
thousands of years ago that
could have stood off 500 meters
and put a hole in your head, right?
And so there was never a time
when humanity wasn't vying
to come up with an asymmetric form
of projecting their own
power via technology.
- An absolute power is
when a leader is able
to control large amount of humans,
they're facing the same direction,
working in the same
direction to leverage energy.
- The most organized society wins.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- When the Romans were
dominating everybody,
they were the most organized
civilization in Europe.
And as long as they stayed
organized, they dominated.
And at some point they over expanded
and got disorganized and they collapsed.
And I guess you could say
that the struggle of human condition,
it catalyzes the development
of new technologies
one after the other.
It penalizes anybody that
rejects ocean power, right?
Gets penalized.
You reject artillery, you get penalized.
You reject atomic power,
you get penalized.
If you reject digital power,
cyber power, you get penalized.
And the underlying control of the property
keeps shifting hands from one institution
or one government to another based upon
how rationally they're
able to channel that energy
and how well organized
or coordinated they are.
- Well, that's really
interesting thing about
both the human mind and
governments that they,
once they get a few good and companies,
once they get a few good ideas,
they seem to stick with them.
They reject new ideas.
It's almost whether that's
emergent or however that evolved,
it seems to have a
really interesting effect
'cause when you're young,
you fight for the new ideas,
you push them through.
Then a few of us humans find success,
then we get complacent.
We take over the world
using that new idea.
And then the new young person
with a better new idea challenges you.
And you as opposed to pivoting,
you stick with the old,
and lose because of it.
And that's how empires collapse.
And it's just both at the
individual level that happens
with two academics fighting about ideas
or something like that.
And at the human civilization
level, governments,
they hold on to the ideas of old.
It's fascinating.
- Yeah, an ever persistent
theme in the history of science
is the paradigm shifts
and the paradigms shift
when the old guard dies and
a new generation arrives,
or the paradigm shifts when there's a war.
And everyone that disagrees
with the idea of aviation
finds bombs dropping on
their head or everyone
that disagrees with
whatever your technology is
has a rude awakening.
And if they totally disagree,
they're society collapses
and they're replaced by that new thing.
- A lot of the engineering
you talked about had to do
with ships and cannons
and leveraging water.
What about this whole digital
thing that's happening?
Been happening over the past century.
Is that still engineering in your mind?
You're starting to operate
in these bits of information?
- I think there's two big ideas.
The first wave of ideas
were digital information.
And that was the internet
wave been running
since 1990 or so for 30 years.
And the second wave is digital energy.
So if I look at digital information,
this idea that we wanna
digitally transform a book,
I'm gonna dematerialize every
book in this room into bits,
and then I'm going to deliver a copy
of the entire library to a billion people.
And I'm gonna do it for pretty
much de minimis electricity.
If I can dematerialize music, books,
education, entertainment, maps, right?
That is an incredibly like
exothermic transaction.
It's a crystallization when we collapse
into a lower energy
state as a civilization
and we give off massive amounts of energy.
Like if you look at what Carnegie did,
the richest man in the
world created libraries
everywhere at the time, and he
gave away his entire fortune.
And now we can give a better library
to every 6-year-old for nothing.
And so what's the value
of giving a million books
to a 8 billion people, right?
That's the explosion in prosperity
that comes from digital transformation.
And when we do it with maps.
I transform the map, I put it into a car.
You get in the car and the car drives you
where you want to go with the map, right?
And how much better is that
than a Rand McNally atlas right here?
It's like a million times better.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So the first wave of
digital transformation
was the dematerialization of all
of these informational things,
which are non-conservative.
That is I could take
Beethoven's, "Fifth Symphony,"
played for by the best
orchestra in Germany,
and I could give it to a billion people
and they could play it
a thousand times each
at less than the cost of
the one performance, right?
So I deliver culture and education
in their edition and
intelligence and insight
to the entire civilization
over digital rails.
And the consequences of the human race
are first order generally good, right?
The world is a better place.
It drives growth and you create
these trillion dollar
entities like Apple and Amazon
and Facebook and Google
and Microsoft, right?
That is the first wave.
The second wave-
- Do you mind, I'm sorry to interrupt.
- [Michael] Yeah.
- But that first wave, it feels like
the impact that's positive,
you said the first order impact
is generally positive.
It feels like it's positive in a way
that nothing else in
history has been positive.
And then we may not actually truly be able
to understand the orders
of magnitude of increase
in productivity in just
progress and human civilization
until we look back centuries from now.
Just looking at the impact of Wikipedia,
the giving access to basic
wisdom or basic knowledge
and then perhaps wisdom
to billions of people.
If you can just linger
on that for a second.
What's your sense of the impact of that?
- I would say if you're a
technologist philosopher,
the impact of a technology
is so much greater on the civilization
and the human condition
than a non-technology
that is almost not worth
your trouble to bother
trying to fix things a conventional way.
So, let's take example.
I have a foundation, the Saylor Academy
and the Saylor Academy
gives away free education,
free college education to
anybody on earth that wants it.
And we've had more than
a million students.
And if you go and you
take the physics class,
the lectures were by
the same physics lecture
that taught me physics at
MIT except when I was at MIT,
the cost of the first four weeks of MIT
would've drained my family's
collective life savings
for the first, last a hundred years.
- [Lex] Yep. (chuckles)
- Like a hundred years worth of my father,
my grandfather, my great-grandfather,
they saved every penny they
had after a hundred years,
they could have paid for one
week or two weeks of MIT.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- That's how fiendishly
expensive and inefficient it was.
So, I went on scholarship.
- [Lex] Yes.
- I was lucky to have a scholarship.
But on the other hand,
I sat in the back of the 801 lecture hall
and I was like right up in the rafters.
It's an awful experience on these
like uncomfortable wooden benches
and you can barely see the blackboard
and you gotta be there synchronously.
And the stuff we upload,
you can start it and stop it
and watch it on your iPad
or watch it on your computer
and rewind it multiple times
and sit in a comfortable chair
and you can do it from anywhere on earth.
And it's absolutely free.
So, I think about this and I think
you wanna improve the human condition.
You need people with
postgraduate level education.
You need PhDs, and I know
this sounds kind of elitist,
but you want to cure cancer
and you wanna go to the
stars, fusion drive.
We need new propulsion, right?
We need extraordinary breakthroughs
in every area of basic science.
Be it biology or propulsion
or material science
or computer science.
You're not doing that with
an undergraduate degree.
You're certainly not doing it
with a high school education.
But the cost of a PhD
is like a million bucks.
There's like 10 million PhDs in the world
if you check it out.
There's 8 billion people in the world.
How many people could get
a PhD or would want to?
Maybe not 8 billion, but
a billion, 500 million.
Let's just say 500 million to a billion.
How do you go from 10 million
to a billion highly educated people,
all of them specializing in,
and I don't have to tell you
how many different fields
of human endeavor there are.
I mean, your life is
interviewing these experts.
And there's so many, right?
You know, it's amazing.
So how do I give a
multimillion dollar education
to a billion people?
And there's two choices.
You can either endow a scholarship,
in which case you pay $75,000 a year.
Let's pay a million dollars
and a million dollars a person.
I can do it that way.
And you're never, even if
you had a trillion dollars.
If you had $10 trillion
to throw at the problem
and we've just thrown $10
trillion at certain problems.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- You don't solve the problem, right?
If I put $10 trillion
on the table and I said,
"Educate everybody, give 'em all a PhD,"
you still wouldn't solve the problem.
Harvard University can't
educate 18,000 people
simultaneously, or 87,000
or 800,000 or 8 million.
So you have to dematerialize the professor
and dematerialize the experience.
So you put it all as streaming on demand,
computer generated education,
and you create simulations where you need
to create simulations and you upload it.
It's like the human
condition is being held back
by 500,000 well-meaning
average algebra teachers.
(Lex chuckles)
I love 'em.
I mean, please don't take of offense
if you're an algebra teacher,
but instead of 500,000 algebra teachers
going through the same
motion over and over again,
what you need is like one or five
or 10 really good algebra teachers
and they need to do it
a billion times a day
or a billion times a year for free.
And if we do that, there's no reason
why you can't give infinite
education, certainly in science,
technology, engineering, and math, right?
Infinite education to
everybody with no constraint.
And I think the same is true, right?
With just about every other thing.
If you wanna bring joy to the
world, you need digital music.
If you wanna bring
enlightenment to the world,
you need digital education.
If you wanna bring anything
of consequence in the world,
you gotta digitally transform it
and then you gotta manufacture it
something like a hundred times
more efficiently as a start.
But a million times more efficiently
is probably, that's hopeful.
Maybe you have a chance.
And if you look at all
of these space endeavors
and everything, we're thinking
about getting to Mars,
getting off the planet,
getting to other worlds.
Number one thing you
gotta do is you gotta make
a fundamental breakthrough in an engine.
People dreamed about flying
for thousands of years,
but until the internal combustion engine,
you didn't have enough energy,
enough power in a light enough package
in order to solve the problem.
And the human race has all sorts
of those fundamental engines and materials
and techniques that we need to master.
And each one of them is a
lifetime of experimentation
of someone capable of making
a seminal contribution
to the body of human knowledge.
- There are certain
problems like education
that could be solved through this process
of dematerialization.
And by the way, to give props
to the 500K algebra teachers.
When I look at YouTube, for example,
one possible approach is each
one of those 500,000 teachers
probably had days and
moments of brilliance.
And if they had ability to contribute to,
in the natural selection
process like the market
of education where the best ones rise up.
That's a really interesting way,
which is like the best day of your life,
the best lesson you've ever taught
could be found and sort of
broadcast to billions of people.
So all of those kinds of ideas
can be made real in the digital world.
Now, traveling across
planets, you still can't solve
that problem with dematerialization.
Where you could solve potentially
is dematerializing the human brain
where you can transfer,
like you don't need
to have astronauts on the ship.
You can have a floppy disc
carrying a human brain.
- Touching on those points.
You'd love for the
500,000 algebra teachers
to become 500,000 math specialists
and maybe they comp into
50,000 specialties as teams
and they all pursue 50,000 new problems
and they put their algebra
teaching on autopilot.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- That's the same as
when I give you 11 cents
worth of electricity and
you don't have to row a boat
eight hours a day before
you can eat, right?
- [Lex] Yes.
- It would be a lot better,
that you would pay for your food
in the first eight seconds of your day
and then you could start thinking
about other things, right?
With regard to technology.
One thing that I learned
studying technology,
when you look at S-curves is
until you start the S-curve
you don't know whether
you're a hundred years
from viability, a thousand
years from viability
or a few months from viability.
- Isn't that fun?
That's so fun.
The early part of the S-curve is so fun,
(chuckles) because you don't know.
- In 1900 you could have got
any number of learned academics
to give you 10,000 reasons
why humans will never fly,
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And in 1903, the Wright brothers flew,
and by 1969 we're walking on the moon.
So the advance that we made in
that field was extraordinary.
But for the a hundred
years and 200 years before,
they were just back and
forth and nobody was close.
And that's the happy part.
The happy part is we went
from flying 20 miles an hour or whatever
to flying 25,000 miles
an hour in 66 years.
The unhappy part is I studied
aeronautical engineering
at MIT in the 80s.
And in the 80s we had Gulfstream aircraft,
we had Boeing 737s, we
had the space shuttle.
And you fast forward 40 years
and we pretty much had
the same exact aircraft.
The efficiency of the
engines was 20, 30% more,
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- We slammed into a brick
wall around '69 to '75.
Like in fact the Global
Express, the Gulfstream,
these were all engineered
in the 70s, some in the 60s.
The actual, the fuselage
silhouette of a Gulfstream,
of a G5 was the same shape as a G4,
is the same shape as a G3,
is the same shape as a G2.
And that's because they were afraid
to change the shape for 40 years
because they worked it
out in a wind tunnel.
They knew it worked.
And when they finally
decided to change the shape,
it was like a $10 billion exercise
with modern supercomputers and
computational fluid dynamics.
- Why was this so hard?
What is that wall made
of that you slammed into?
- The right question is, so
why does a guy that went to MIT
that got an aeronautical
engineering degree
spent his career in software?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Like why is it that I
never a day in my life,
with the exception of some
Air Force reserve work,
I never got paid to be
an aeronautical engineer
and I worked in software
engineering my entire career.
- Or maybe software engineering
is the new aeronautical
engineering in some way.
Maybe you hit fundamental walls uncertain
until you have to return to
it centuries later, or no.
- The National Gallery of Art
was endowed by a very
rich man, Andrew Mellon,
and you know how he made his money?
Aluminum, okay?
(Lex chuckles)
And you know what kind of airplanes
you can create without aluminum?
Nothing.
Nothing, right?
- [Lex] So, it's a material.
So, it's a materials problem?
- Okay, so 1900, we made massive advances
in metallurgy, right?
I mean, that was US Steel,
that was iron to steel,
aluminum, massive fortunes were created
because this was a
massive technical advance.
And then we also had the
internal combustion engine.
And the story of Ford and General Motors
and Daimler Chrysler and the
like is informed by that.
So you have no jet
engines, no rocket motors,
no internal combustion
engines, you have no aviation.
But even if you had those engines,
if you were trying to build
those things with steel,
no chance, you had to have aluminum.
So there's like two
pretty basic technologies.
And once you have those two technologies,
stuff happens very fast.
So tell me the last big
advance in like jet engines,
there hasn't been one.
The last big advance in rocket
engines hasn't been one.
The big advances in spaceship design
from what I can see are
in the control systems,
the gyros and the ability to land, right,
in a stable fashion,
that's pretty amazing.
Landing a rocket.
- Also in the, at least
according to the Elon and so on,
the manufacturer of the more efficient
and less expensive
manufacturer of rockets.
So like it's production,
whatever that you call
that discipline of at scale manufacture,
at scale production, so factory work.
But it's not 10X.
I mean maybe it's 10X over
a period of a few decades.
- When we figure out how
to operate a spaceship
on the water, in your
water bottle for a year,
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Now then you've got a breakthrough.
So the bottom line is propulsion,
propulsion technology,
propellants, and the materials technology,
they were critical to getting
on that aviation S-curve.
And then we slammed into a wall in the 70s
and the Boeing 747, the Global
Express, the Gulfstream,
these things were, the space shuttle.
They were all pretty
much reflective of that.
And then we kind of, then we
stopped, and at that point,
you have to switch to a new S-curve.
So the next equivalent to the
internal combustion engine
was the CPU and the next
aluminum equivalent was silicon.
So when we actually
started developing CPUs,
transistor gateway to CPUs,
and if you look at the power,
right, the bandwidth
that we had on computers
and Moore's law, right?
What if the efficiency of jet engines
had doubled every three years,
right, in the last 40 years.
Where would we be right now, right?
So, I think that if
you're a business person,
if you're looking for
commercially viable application
of your mind, then you
have to find that S-curve.
And ideally, you have to find it
in the first five, six, 10 years.
But people always miss this.
Let's take Google Glass, right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Google Glass was a idea
2013, the year is 2022.
And people were quite sure
this was gonna be a big thing.
- And it could have been at
the beginning of the S-curve.
- But fundamentally, we didn't really have
an effective mechanism.
I mean, people getting vertigo and there-
- But you didn't know that
at the beginning of the S-curve, right?
- [Michael] We didn't have that.
- I mean, maybe some people
had a deep intuition about
the fundamentals of augmented reality,
but you don't know that, you don't have.
Those, you're looking through
the fog, you don't know.
- So the point is, we're
at year zero in 2013,
and we're still year zero in
2022 on that augmented reality.
And when somebody puts
out a set of glasses
that you can wear comfortably
without getting vertigo, right,
without any disorientation that managed
to have the stability and
the bandwidth necessary
to sync with the real world,
you'll be in year one.
And from that point, you'll have a 70 year
or some interesting future
until you slam into a limit to growth
and then it'll slow down.
This is the story of a
lot of things, right?
I mean, John D. Rockefeller
got in the oil business
in the 1860s, and the oil
business as we understood it,
became fairly mature
by the 1920s, the 30s.
And then it actually stayed that way
until we got to fracking and like,
which was like seven years
later, and then it burst forward.
- The interesting story
about Moore's law though
is that you get this like constant burst
of S-curves on top of
S-curves on top of S-curve.
It's like the moment
you start slowing down,
or almost ahead of you slowing down,
you come up with another
innovation, another innovation.
So like Moore's law doesn't seem to happen
in every technological advancement.
It seems like you only
get a couple of S-curves
and then you're done for a bit.
So I wonder what the pressures there are
that resulted in such
success over several decades
and still going.
- Humility dictates that nobody knows
when the S-curve kicks off.
And you could be 20 years
early or a hundred years early.
Leonardo da Vinci, Michelangelo,
they were designing flying machines
hundreds and hundreds of years ago.
So humility says you're not quite sure
when you really hit that
commercial viability.
And it also dictates, you
don't know when it ends.
Like when will the party stop?
When will Moore's law stop
and we'll get to the point
where they're exponentially
diminishing returns
on silicon performance.
Just like we got exponentially
diminishing returns on jet engines,
and it just takes an exponential increase
in effort to make it 10% better.
But while you're in the middle of it,
then you know you can do things.
So the reason that the digital
revolution is so important
is because the underlying
platforms, the bandwidth of,
and the performance of the components,
and I say the components
are the radio protocols,
mobile protocols, the batteries,
the CPUs, and the displays, right?
Those four components are pretty critical.
They're all critical in
the creation of an iPhone.
I wrote about it in the
book, "The Mobile Wave,"
and they catalyzed this
entire mobile revolution
because they have advanced
and continue to advance,
they created the very fertile environment
for all these digital transformations.
And the digital transformations
themself, right?
They call for creativity
in their own, right?
Like, I think the interesting thing about
let's take digital maps, right?
When you conceptualize something
as a dematerialized map, right?
It becomes a map because
I can put it on a display
like an iPad, or I can put
it in a car like a Tesla.
But if you really wanna figure it out,
you can't think like an engineer.
You need to think like a fantasy writer.
Like this is where it's
useful if you studied,
if you read, played,
"Dungeons and Dragons,"
and you read, "Lord of the Rings,"
and you studied all the fantasy literature
because when I dematerialize the map,
first I put 10 million
pages of satellite imagery
into the map, right?
That's a simple physical transform.
But then I start to put
telemetry into the map
and I keep track of the
traffic rates on the roads,
and I tell you whether
you'll be in a traffic jam
if you drive that way, and I
tell you which way to drive,
and then I start to get
feedback on where you're going.
And I tell you the restaurant's closed
and people don't like it anyway.
And then I put an AI on top of it
and I have a drive your car for you.
And eventually the implication
of digital transformation of maps
is I get in a self-driving car and I say,
"Take me someplace cool where I can eat."
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And how did you get to
that last step, right?
It wasn't simple engineering.
There's a bit of fantasy
in there, a bit of magic.
- Design, art, whatever
the heck you call it.
It's whatever, yeah, yeah,
fantasy injects magic into
the engineering process.
Like imagination like
precedes great revolutions
in engineering.
It's like imagining a world,
like of what you can do with the display,
how will the interaction be?
That's where Google
Glass actually came in.
Augmented reality, virtual reality,
people were playing in the
space of sci-fi, imagination.
- They called it a moonshot.
They tried, it didn't
work, but to their credit,
they stopped trying, right?
And then there's new
people, they keep dreaming,
they're dreamers all around us.
I love those dreamers and most of 'em fail
and suffer because of it.
But some of them won win Nobel Prizes
or become billionaires.
- Well, what I would say
is if half the civilization
dropped what they were doing tomorrow
and eagerly started working on launching
a rocket to Alpha San Tori,
it might not be the best
use of our resources
because it's kind of
like if half of Athens
in the year 500 BC eagerly started
working on flying machines,
if you went back and you said,
what advice would you give 'em?
You would say, it's not gonna
work till you get to aluminum
and you're not gonna get to aluminum
till you work out the steel
and certain other things.
And you're not gonna get to that
until you work out the
calculus of variations
and some metallurgy.
And there's a dude Newton
that won't come along
for quite a while and he's gonna give you
the calculus to do it.
And until then it's hopeless.
So, you might be better
off to work on the aqueduct
or to focus upon sales or something.
So if I look at this today,
I say there's massive
profound environment civilization advances
to be made through digital
transformation of information.
And you can see them.
Like, this is the story of today.
This is not the story of today, right?
It's 10 years old what we've been seeing.
- We're living through
different manifestations
of that story today too though.
- [Michael] Yeah.
- Like social media, the effects of that
is very interesting because ideas spread,
even you talk about velocity of money,
the velocity of ideas keeps increasing.
- [Michael] Yeah.
- So like Wikipedia is a passive store,
it's a store of knowledge.
Twitter is like a, (chuckles)
it's like a water hose or something.
It's like spraying you with knowledge
whether you want it or not.
It's like social media is just
like this explosion of ideas
and then we pick 'em up
and then we try to understand ourselves
because the drama of it also
plays with our human psyche.
So sometimes there's more
ability for misinformation,
for propaganda to take hold.
So we get to learn about ourselves,
we get to learn about the technology
that can decelerate the propaganda,
for example, all that kind of stuff.
But like, the reality is we're living,
I feel like we're living
through a singularity
in the digital information space.
And we are not, we don't
have a great understanding
of exactly how it's
transforming our lives.
- This is where money is useful
as a metaphor for significance.
Because if money is the economic
energy of the civilization,
then something that's
extraordinarily lucrative
that's gonna generate a
monetary or a wealth increase
is a way to increase the net
energy in the civilization.
And ultimately, if we had 10
times as much of everything,
we'd have a lot more
free resources to pursue
all of our advanced
scientific and mathematical
and theoretical endeavors.
So let's take Twitter, right?
Twitter's something that could be 10 times
more valuable than it is, right?
Twitter could be made 10 times better.
- Oh, by the way, I should say that.
People should follow you on Twitter.
Your Twitter account is awesome.
- Thank you.
(Lex chuckles)
Thank you.
- It could be made 10 times better, yeah.
- Yeah, Twitter can be
made 10 times better.
If we take YouTube or take education,
we could generate a billion PhDs.
And the question is, do you
need any profound breakthrough
in materials or technology to do that?
And the answer is not really no.
So if you wanna, you could
make Apple, Amazon, Facebook,
Google, Twitter, all these things better.
The United States
government, if they took 1%
of the money they spend on
the Department of Education
and they simply poured
it into digital education
and they gave degrees to people
that actually met those requirements,
they could provide 100X as much education
for 1/100 of the cost,
and they could do it
with no new technology.
That's a marketing and
political challenge.
So I don't think every
objective is equally practical.
And I think the benefit
of being an engineer
or thinking about practical achievements
is when the government pursues
an impractical objective
or when anybody, an entrepreneur.
Not so bad with an entrepreneur
'cause they don't have
that much money to waste.
When a government pursues
an impractical objective,
they squander trillions
and trillions of dollars
and achieve nothing.
Whereas if they pursue
a practical objective
or if they simply get out
of the way and do nothing,
and they allow the free market
to pursue the practical objectives,
then I think you can have profound impact
on the human civilization.
And if I look at the world we're in today,
I think that there are multi-trillion 10,
20, $50 trillion worth of opportunities
in the digital information
realm yet to be obtained.
But there's hundreds
of trillions of dollars
of opportunities in the
digital energy realm
that not only are they not
obtained, the majority of people
don't even know what digital energy is.
Most of them would reject the concept.
They're not looking for it,
they're not expecting to find it.
It's inconceivable because
it is a paradigm shift.
But in fact, it's completely practical,
right under our nose.
It's staring at us.
And it could make the entire civilization
work dramatically better in every respect.
- So you mentioned in the digital world,
digital information is
one, digital energy is two,
and the possible impact on the world
and the set of opportunities available
in the digital energy
space is much greater.
So how do you think about digital energy?
What is it?
- So I'll start with Tesla.
He had a very famous quote.
He said, "If you wanna
understand the universe,
think in terms of energy,
vibration and frequency,"
and it gets you thinking
about what is the universe?
And of course the universe
is just all energy.
And then what does matter?
Matter is low frequency energy.
And what are we?
We're vibrating from...
Ashes to ashes, dust to dust.
I can turn a tree into light.
I can turn light back into a tree
if I consider the entire universe.
And then it's very important
because we don't really think this way.
Let's take the New York disco model.
If I walk into a nightclub
and there's loud music
blaring in New York City,
what's really going on there, right?
If you blast out 15, 14 billion years ago,
the universe is formed.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Okay, that's a low frequency thing.
The universe, four and a
half billion years ago,
the sun, maybe the earth are formed.
The continents are 400 million years old.
The shift that New York City is on
is some hundreds of millions of years.
But the Hudson River is only 20,000 years.
There's a building that's
probably 50 years old.
There's a company operating
that disco or that club,
which is five to 10 years old.
There's a person, a
customer walking in there
for an experience for a few hours.
There's music that's
oscillating at some kilohertz,
and then there's light.
- [Lex] Right.
- And you have all forms of energy,
all frequencies, right?
All layered, all moving
through different medium.
And how you perceive the
world is a question of
at what frequency do you
want to perceive the world?
And I think that once you
start to think that way,
you're catalyze to think about
what would digital energy look like,
and why would I want it?
And what is it?
So why don't we just start right there.
What is it?
The most famous manifestation
of digital energy is Bitcoin.
Bitcoin's a crypto asset.
It's a crypto asset
that has monetary value.
- Can we just linger on that?
Bitcoin is a, so it is digital asset
that has monetary value.
What is a digital asset?
What is monetary?
Why use those terms versus the
words of money and currency?
Is there something interesting
in that disambiguation of different terms?
- I'd call it a crypto asset network.
The goal is to create
a billion dollar block,
a pure energy in cyberspace.
One that I could then
move with no friction
at the speed of light, right?
It's the equivalent to putting
a million pounds in orbit.
How do I actually launch
something into orbit, right?
How do I launch something into cyberspace
that such that it moves friction free?
And the solution is a decentralized
proof of work network, right?
Satoshi's solution was,
I'm going to establish
protocol running on a
distributed set of computers
that will maintain a constant supply
of never more than 21 million Bitcoin
sub dividable by a
hundred million satoshis,
each transferable via
transferring private keys.
Now the innovation is to create that
in a ethical, durable fashion, right?
The ethical innovation is
I want it to be property
and not a security.
A bushel of corn, an acre of land,
a stack of lumber and a bar of gold
and a Bitcoin are all property.
And that means they're all commonly
occurring elements in the world.
You could call them commodities,
but commodities a little bit misleading.
And I'll tell you why in a second.
But they're all distinguished
by the fact that no one entity
or person or government controls them.
If you have a barrel of
oil and you're in Ukraine
versus Russia versus Saudi
Arabia versus the US,
you have a barrel of oil, right?
And it doesn't matter
what the premier in Japan
or the mayor of Miami Beach
thinks about your barrel.
They cannot wave their hand and make it
not a barrel of oil or
a cord of wood, right?
And so property is just a
naturally occurring element
in the universe, right?
- Why use the word, ethical?
And sorry to, I may
interrupt occasionally.
Why ethical assigned to property?
- Because if it's a security,
a security would be an example
of a share of a stock or a crypto token
controlled by a small team.
And in the event that
something is a security
because some small group
or some identifiable group
can control its nature, character supply,
then it really only becomes
ethical to promote it
or sell it pursuant to fair disclosures.
So, I'll give you maybe practical example.
I'm the mayor of Chicago, I give a speech.
In my speech, I'll say, I
think everybody in Chicago
should own their own
farm and have chicken,
a chicken in the backyard
and their own horse and an automobile.
That's ethical.
I give the same speech and I say,
I think everybody in Chicago
should buy Twitter stock,
sell their house, or sell their
cash and buy Twitter stock.
Well, is that ethical?
Not really.
But at that point, you've
entered into a conflict
of interest because what you're
doing is you're promoting
an asset which is substantially
controlled by a small group
of people, the board of directors
or the CEO of the company.
How would you feel
if the president of
the United States said,
I really think Americans
should all buy Apple stock.
Especially if you worked at Google.
But you worked anywhere, you'd be like,
"Why isn't he saying buy mine?"
Right?
A security is a proprietary asset
in some way, shape or form.
And the whole nature of securities law,
it starts from this ancient idea
thou shalt not lie, cheat, or steal, okay?
So if I'm going to sell you securities,
or I'm gonna promote
securities as a public figure
or as an influencer or
anybody else, right?
If I create my own yo-yo
coin or Mikey coin,
and then there's a million of them,
and I tell you that I think
that it's a really good thing,
and Mikey coin will go up forever, right?
And everybody buys Mikey coin,
and then I give 10 million to you
and don't tell the public, right?
I've cheated them.
Maybe if I have Mikey coin and I think
there's only 2 million Mikey coin,
and I swear to you there's only 2 million,
and then I get married
and I have three kids
and my third kid is in the
hospital and my kid's gonna die
and I have this ethical reason
to print 500,000 more Mikey coin
or else people are gonna die,
and everybody tells me it's fine.
I've still abused the investor, right?
It's a ethical challenge.
If you look at ethics laws
everywhere in the world,
they all boil down to having a clause
which says that if you're a public figure,
you can't endorse any, a security,
you can't endorse something
that would cause you
to have a conflict of interest.
So if you're a mayor,
a governor, a country,
a public figure, an influencer,
and you want to promote or promulgate
or support something
using any public influence
or funds or resources you may
have, it needs to be property.
It can't be security.
So it goes beyond that, right?
I mean, like what the Chinese want
to support an American company, right?
As soon as you look at
what's in the best interest
of the human race, the civilization,
you realize that if you want
an ethical path forward,
it needs to be based on common
property, which is fair.
And the way you get to a common property
is through an open
permissionless protocol.
If it's not open, right?
If it's proprietary and
I know what the code says
and you don't know what the code says,
that makes it a security.
If it's permissioned, if you're
not allowed on my network
or if you can be censored
or booted off my network,
that also makes it a security.
So, when I talk about property,
I mean the challenge here
is how do I create
something that's equivalent
to a barrel of oil in cyberspace?
And that means it has to be
a non sovereign bearer instrument,
open, permissionless,
not sensorable, right?
If I could do that,
then I could deliver you
10,000 dematerialized barrels of oil
and you would take settlement of them
and you would know that
you have possession
of that property regardless of
the opinion of any politician
or any company or anybody
else in the world.
That's a really critical characteristic.
And it actually is, it's probably one
of the fundamental things
that makes Bitcoin special.
Bitcoin isn't just a crypto asset network,
it's easy to create a
crypto asset network.
It's very hard to create an
ethical crypto asset network
because you have to create one
without any government or
corporation or investor
exercising into influence
to make it successful.
- So, open, permissionless,
non-sensorable.
So basically no way for you
without explicitly saying so
outsourcing control to somebody else.
So it's a kinda, you have full control.
Even with a barrel of
oil, what's the difference
between a barrel of oil
and a Bitcoin to you?
Because you kind of mentioned
that both are property is,
you mentioned Russia and China and so on.
Is it the ability of the
government to confiscate.
In the end, governments
can probably confiscate
no matter what the asset is,
but you want to lessen
the effort involved.
- A barrel oil is a bucket
of physical property,
liquid property.
- [Lex] That's very complicated.
- And Bitcoin is a digital property.
- But it's easier to
confiscate a barrel of oil.
- It's easier to confiscate
things in the real world
than things in cyberspace, much easier.
- So, that's not universally true.
Some things in the digital
space are actually easier
to confiscate because just the nature
of how things move easily
with information, right?
- I think in the Bitcoin
world, what we would say
is that Bitcoin is the
most difficult property
that the human race possesses
or has yet invented to confiscate.
And that's by virtue of the fact
that you could take possession
of it via your private key.
So, if you've got your 12
seed phrases in your head,
then that would be the highest
form of property, right?
Because I literally have
to crack your head open
and read your mind to take it.
It doesn't mean I couldn't
extract it from you under duress,
but it means that it's harder
than every other thing you might own.
In fact, it's exponentially harder.
If you consider every other
thing you might own, a car,
a house, a share of stock,
gold, diamonds, property rights,
intellectual property rights,
movie rights, music rights,
anything imaginable,
they would all be easier
by orders and orders
of magnitude to seize.
So digital property in the
form of a set of private keys
is by far the apex
property of the human race.
In terms of ethics, I
wanna make one more point.
It's like I might say to you, Lex,
I think Bitcoin is the best, most secure,
most durable crypto asset
network in the world,
is gonna go up forever,
and there's nothing better in the world.
I might be right, I might be wrong,
but the point is, because it's property,
it's ethical for me to say that.
If I were to turn around and say,
Lex, I think the same about
MicroStrategy stock, MSTR.
That's a security, okay?
If I'm wrong about that,
I have civil liability or other liability
because I could go to a
board meeting tomorrow
and I could actually propose we issue
a million more shares
of MicroStrategy stock.
Whereas the thing that
makes Bitcoin ethical for me
to even promote is the knowledge
that I can't change it.
If I knew that I could make it 42 million
instead of 21 million and
I had the button back here,
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Then I have a different degree
of ethical responsibility.
Now, I could tell you
your life will be better
if you buy Bitcoin, and it might not.
You might go buy Bitcoin,
you might lose the keys
and be bankrupt and your life ends
and your life is not better
because you bought Bitcoin, right?
But it wouldn't be my ethical liability
any more than if I were to say, Lex,
I think you ought to get a farm.
I think you should be a farmer.
I think a chicken in every
pot, you should get a horse.
I think you'd be better.
I mean, they're all opinions
expressed about property,
which may or may not be right
that you may or may not agree with.
But in a legal sense, if we read the law,
if we understand securities
law, and I would say,
you know, most people
in the crypto industry,
they didn't take companies public,
and so they're not really
focused on the securities law.
They don't even know the securities law.
If you focus on the
securities law, that would say
you just can't legally sell
this stuff to the general public
or promote it without a full
set of continuing disclosures
signed off on by a regulator.
So, there's a fairly bright line there
with regard to securities.
But when you get to the secondary issue,
it's how do you actually build a world
based on digital property
if public figures
can't embrace it or endorse it, you see?
So you're not gonna build a better world
based upon Twitter stock if
that's your idea of property,
because Twitter stock is a security,
and Twitter stock is never going to be
a non sovereign bearer
instrument in Russia, right?
Or in China, right?
It's not even legal in China, right?
So it's not a global,
permissionless, open thing.
It will never be trusted
by the rest of the world,
and legally it's impractical.
But would you really wanna
put a hundred trillion dollars
worth of economic value on Twitter stock
if there's a board of directors and a CEO
that could just get up and
like take half of it tomorrow?
The answer is no.
So if you wanna build a better world
based on digital energy, you need to start
with constructing a digital property.
And I'm using property here in the-
- Open, permissionless, non-sensorable.
- [Michael] In the legal sense.
- Okay.
- But I would also go to the next step
and say property is low frequency money.
So if I give you a million dollars
and you wanna hold it for a decade,
you might go buy a house with it, right?
And the house is low frequency money.
You converted the million
dollars of economic energy
into a structure called a house.
Maybe in after a decade
you might convert it back into energy,
you might sell the house for currency,
and it'll be worth more or less
depending upon the
monetary climate you sell.
- The frequency means what here?
How quickly it changes state?
- How quickly does something vibrate?
So if I transfer $10 from
me to you for a drink,
and then you turn around
and you buy another, right?
We're vibrating on a frequency
of every few hours, right?
The energy is changing hands.
But it's not likely that you sell
and buy houses every few hours, right?
The frequency of a
transaction in real estate
is every 10 years, every five,
it's a much lower frequency transaction.
And so when you think
about what's going on here,
you have extremely low frequency things
which we'll call property,
then you have mid frequency things,
I'm gonna call 'em money or currency.
And then you have high
frequency, and that's energy.
And that's why I use the illustration
of you got the building,
you got the light,
and you got the sound, and
they're all just energy
moving at different frequencies.
Now, Bitcoin is magical and
it is truly the innovation.
It's like a singularity
because it represents
the first time in the
history of the human race
that we managed to create
a digital property properly understood.
It's easy to create
something digital, right?
Every coupon and every scan
on, "Fortnite," and, "Roblox,"
and Apple TV credits and all these things,
they're all digital something,
but they're securities, right?
Shares of stock are securities.
Whenever anybody transfers,
when you transfer money
on PayPal or Apple Pay,
you're transferring in
essence a security or an IOU.
And so transferring a bearer instrument
with final settlement
in the internet domain
or in cyberspace, that's a critical thing.
And anybody in the
crypto world can do that.
All the cryptos can do that.
But what they can't do,
what 99% of them fail
to do is be property.
They're securities, right?
- Well, there's a line there
I'd like to explore a little further.
For example, what about
when you like Coinbase
or something like that,
when there's an exchange
that you buy, Bitcoin is
in, you start to move away
from this kind of, some of the aspects
that you said makes up a property,
which is this non-sensorable
and permissionless and open.
So in order to achieve the convenience,
the effectiveness of
the transfer of energy,
you have to leverage some of these,
of the places that remove
the aspects of property.
So, maybe you can comment on that.
- Let me give you a good model for that.
If you think about the
layer one of Bitcoin,
the layer one is the
property settlement layer
and we're gonna do 350,000
transactions or less a day.
A hundred million transactions a year
is the bandwidth on the layer one.
And it would be an ideal layer one
to move a billion dollars
from point A to point B
with the massive security.
The role of the layer one is two things.
One thing is I wanna
move a large sum of money
through space with security.
I can move any amount of
Bitcoin in a matter of minutes
for dollars on layer one.
The second important
feature of the layer one
is I need the money to
last forever, right?
I need the money indestructible, immortal.
So, the bigger trick is not to move
a billion dollars from here to Tokyo.
The big trick is to move a billion dollars
from here to the year 2140.
And that's what we wanna
solve with layer one.
And the best real
metaphor in New York City
would be the granite or the schist.
What you want is a city block of bedrock.
And how long has it been there?
Like millions of years it's been there.
And how fast you want it to move?
You don't.
In fact, the single thing
that's most important
is that it not deflect.
If it deflects a foot in a
hundred years, it's too much.
If it deflects an inch in a hundred years,
you might not want that.
So the layer one of
Bitcoin is a foundation
upon which you put weight.
How much weight can you put on it?
You put a trillion, 10 trillion,
a hundred trillion, a quadrillion.
How much weight's on the
bedrock in Manhattan, right?
Think about a hundred story buildings.
So the real key there is
the foundational asset
needs to be there at all.
So the fact that you can create
a hundred trillion dollars layer one
that would stand for a hundred years,
that is the revolutionary
breakthrough first time.
And the fact that it's ethical, right?
It's ethical and it's common property.
global, permissionless.
Extremely unlikely that would happen.
People tried 50 times
before and they all failed.
They tried 15,000 times
after, and they've all been,
they've all generally failed.
98% have failed and a couple
have like been less successful.
But for the most part, that's
an extraordinary thing.
- Just really quickly pause
just to find some terms people don't know.
Layer one is that Michael's referring to
is in general what people know of
as the Bitcoin technology
originally defined,
which is there's blockchain,
there's a consensus
mechanism of proof of work,
low number of transactions,
but you can move a very
large amount of money.
The reason he's using the term layer one
is now that there's a lot of
ideas of layer two technologies
that built on top of this
bedrock that allow you
to move a much larger
number of transactions.
So sort of higher frequency,
I don't know what
terminology I wanna to use,
but basically be able to use now something
that is based on Bitcoin
to then buy stuff,
be a consumer to transfer
money, to use it as currency.
Just to define some terms.
- Yeah, so the layer one is the foundation
for the entire cyber economy,
and we don't want it to move fast.
What we want is immortality,
incorrupt, immortal,
incorruptible and destructible, right?
That's what you want.
Integrity from the layer one.
Now there's layer two and layer three.
And layer two I would define
as an open, permissionless,
non-custodial protocol that uses
the underlying layer one
token as it's gas fee.
- So what's custodial mean
and how does the different markets,
like is Lightning Network?
- So Lightning Network would be an example
of a layer two, non-custodial.
So the Lightning Network
will sit on top of layer one,
it'll sit on top of
Bitcoin and it solves the,
what you wanna do is solve the problem
of it's well and fine,
I don't wanna move a
billion dollars every day.
What I wanna move is $5
a billion times a day.
So if I wanna move $5
a billion times a day,
I don't really need to put
the entire trillion dollars
of assets at risk every time I move $5.
All I really need to do
is put a hundred thousand
dollars in a channel
or a million dollars in a channel,
and then I do 10 million transactions
where I have a million dollars at risk.
And of course it's kind of simple.
If I lower my security requirement
by a factor of a million,
I can probably move the stuff
a million times faster, right?
And that's how Lightning works.
It's non-custodial because
there's no corporation
or custodian or counterparty
you're trusting, right?
There's the risk of moving
through the channel,
but Lightning is an example
of how I go from 350,000
transactions a day
to 350 million transactions a day.
So on that layer two, you
could move the Bitcoin
in seconds for fractions of pennies.
Now that's not the end all be all
because the truth is there
are a lot of open protocols.
Lightning probably won't be the only one.
There's a open market competition
of other permissionless
open source protocols
to do this work.
And in theory, any other crypto network
that was deemed to be property,
deemed to be non security,
you could also think of
as potentially a layer
two to Bitcoin, right?
There's a debate about are
there any and what are they?
And we could leave that for a later time.
- But why do you think
of them as layer two
as opposed to contending for layer one?
- Yeah, actually if they're
using their own token,
then they are a layer one.
If you create an open protocol
that uses the Bitcoin
token got as the fee-
- [Lex] I got you, I got you.
- Then it becomes a layer two,
right?
- [Lex] Okay.
- Bitcoin itself, right,
incentivizes its own transactions
with its own token.
And that's what makes it layer one.
- Okay, what's layer three then?
- Layer three is a custodial layer.
So if you wanna move Bitcoin
in milliseconds for free,
you move it through Binance
or Coinbase or Cash App.
So this is a very straightforward thing.
I mean it seems pretty obvious
when you think about it
that there are gonna be
hundreds of thousands
of layer threes, there may
be dozens of layer twos.
I mean Lightning is a one,
but it's not the only one.
Anybody can invent something, right?
And we can have this debate
about custodial, non-custodial.
- Don't you think there's a
monopolization possibilities
at layer three?
So, you mentioned Binance, Coinbase,
what if they start to dominate
and basically everybody's using
them practically speaking,
and then it becomes too costly
to memorize the private key in your brain.
I mean, or like cold storage
of layer one technology.
- Well, the idealist fear the layer threes
because they think, and
especially they detest,
they would detest a bit...
There's almost like a layer
four by the way, if you want to.
A layer four would be, I've
got Bitcoin on an application,
but I can't withdraw it.
So, I've got an application
that's backed by Bitcoin,
but the Bitcoin is sealed.
It's a proprietary example.
And I'll give you an example of that.
That would be like gray scale.
If I own a share of GBTC,
and so I own a security.
Actually you could own MSTR.
If you own a security or you own a product
that has Bitcoin embedded in it,
you get the benefits of Bitcoin,
but you don't have the
ability to withdraw the asset.
- You can the security
market at layer four.
Am I understanding this correctly?
- I don't know if I would say.
Not all securities are layer four,
but anything that's a proprietary product
based upon with Bitcoin embedded in it
where you can't withdraw the Bitcoin
is another application of Bitcoin.
So, if you think about
different ways you can use this,
you can either stay
completely on the layer one
and use the base chain
for your transactions
or you can limit yourself
to layer one in layer two Lightning.
And the purist would say, "We stay there.
Get your Bitcoin off the exchange."
But you could also go to the layer three.
When Cash App supported
Bitcoin, they made it very easy
to buy it and then they gave
you the ability of withdraw.
When PayPal or I think
Robinhood let you buy it,
they wouldn't let you withdraw it,
and it was a big community uproar.
And people want, they
want these layer threes
to make it possible to
withdraw the Bitcoin,
so you can take it to
your own private wallet
and get it off the exchange.
I think the answer to the question
of well is corruption possible?
Is corruption is possible
in all human institutions
and all governments everywhere.
The difference between digital property
and physical property is
when you own a building
in Los Angeles and the city
politics turn against you,
you can't move the building.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And when you own a share of a security
that's like a US traded security
and you wish to move
to some other country,
you can't take the
security with you either.
And when you own a bunch of gold
and you try to get through the airport,
they might not let you take it.
So Bitcoin is advantageous
versus all those
because you actually do have the option
to withdraw your asset from the exchange.
And if you had Bitcoin with Fidelity
and you had shares of stock with Fidelity
and if you had bonds and
sovereign debt with Fidelity,
and if you own some mutual funds
and some other random limited
partnerships with Fidelity,
none of those things can be
removed from the custodian,
but the Bitcoin, you can
take off the exchange,
you can remove from the custodian.
- It's still possible though.
- [Michael] There's a deterrent.
- Yes.
- There's a deterrent.
That's an anti-corruption element.
And the phrase is an armed society
is a polite society, right?
Because you have the
optionality to withdraw
all your assets from the crypto exchange,
you can enforce fairness.
And at the point where you
disagree with their policies,
you can within an hour move your assets
to another counterparty
or take personal custody of those assets,
and you don't have that option
with most other forms of property.
Maybe you don't have as much optionality
with any other form of property on earth.
And so what makes
digital property distinct
is the fact that it has the
most optionality for custody.
Now, coming back to this
digital energy issue.
The real key point is the
energy moves in milliseconds
for free on layer threes,
it moves in seconds
or less than seconds on layer twos.
It moves in minutes on the layer one.
And I don't think it makes any sense
to even think about trying to solve
all three problems on the layer one,
because it's impossible
to achieve the security
and the incorruptibility and immortality
if you try to build that much speed
and that functionality and performance.
In fact, if you come back
to the New York model,
you really wanted a block of granite,
a building, and a company.
That's what makes the economy, right?
If I said to you, "You're
gonna build a building,
but you can only have one company in it
for the life of the building,"
it would be very fragile.
Like very brittle.
What company a hundred years
ago is still relevant today?
You want all three layers
because they all oscillate
at different frequencies.
And there's a tendency to think, "Well,
it's gotta be this L1
or that L1," not really.
And sometimes people think,
"Well, I don't really want any L3,"
but companies, it's not an even or.
Companies are better than
crypto asset networks
at certain things.
If you want complexity, you
want to implement complexity
or you wanna implement compliance
or customer service, right?
Companies do these things well, right?
We know it.
You couldn't decentralize Apple
or Netflix or even YouTube.
The performance wouldn't be there
and the subtlety wouldn't be there.
And you can't really legally
decentralize certain forms
of banking and insurance because
they would become illegal
in the political jurisdiction they're in.
So unless you're a crypto anarchist
and you believe in no companies
and no nation states, right?
Which is just not very practical.
Not anytime soon.
Once you allow that nation
states will continue
and companies have a role,
then the layered architecture follows,
and the free market determines who wins.
For example, there are layer threes
that's let you acquire
Bitcoin and withdraw Bitcoin.
There are other applications
that let you acquire but not withdraw it.
And they don't get the same market share,
but they might give you
some other advantage.
There are certain layer threes
like Jack Dorsey's Cash App
where they just incorporated Lightning
and implementation of it.
- Into Cash App.
- So that makes it more,
that makes it advantageous
versus an application that
doesn't incorporate Lightning.
If you think about the big picture,
the big picture is 8 billion people
with mobile phones served
a hundred million companies
doing billions of transactions an hour.
And the companies are
settling with each other
on the base layer in blocks
of 80 million at a time.
And then the companies are trading
with the consumers, right,
in proprietary layers like layer three.
And then on occasion,
people are shuffling assets
across custodians with
Lightning layer two,
because you don't wanna
pay $5 to move $50.
You want to pay a 20th
of a penny to move $50.
And so all of these things
create efficiency in the economy.
And, Lex, if you wanna
consider how much efficiency.
If you gave me a billion
dollars in 20 years,
I couldn't find a way to
trade with another company
or a counterparty in Nigeria.
Like no amount of money.
Gimme $10 billion, I couldn't do it.
Because you get shut down
at the banking level.
You can't link up a bank in
Nigeria with the bank in the US.
You get shut down at
this credit card level
because they don't have the credit card,
so they won't clear.
You'll get shut down at
the compliance FCPA level,
because you wouldn't be
able to implement a system
that interfaced with
somebody else's system
if it's not in the right
political jurisdiction.
On the other hand, three
entrepreneurs in Nigeria
on the weekend could create a website
that would trade in this Lightning economy
using open protocols without
asking anybody's permission.
So you're talking about something
that's like a million times
cheaper, less friction
and faster to do it if you
wanna get money to move.
- What do you think that looks like?
So that now there's a
war going on in Ukraine,
there's other wars, Yemen,
going out throughout the world.
In this most difficult of
states than a nation can be in,
which is at war, civil war
or war with other nations,
what's the role of
Bitcoin in this context?
- I mean, Bitcoin's a universal
trust protocol, right?
A universal energy protocol, if you will.
English is one, okay.
What I see is a bunch of
fragmentation of applications.
For example, the Russian payment app
is not gonna work in Ukraine.
The Ukraine payment app is
not gonna work in Russia.
The US payment apps won't work either
of those places as far as I know.
And in Argentina, their payment app
may not work in certain parts of Africa.
So what you have is
different local economies
where people spin up their
own applications compliant
with their own local laws or
in war zones, not compliant,
but just spinning up, you know?
- So, how do you build
something that's not compliant?
What is the revolutionary
act here when you don't agree
with the government or what you want
to free yourself from the?
So, here's the thing.
When a nation is really at war,
especially if it's an
authoritarian regime,
it's going to try to control
the, like lock everything down.
- [Michael] Yeah.
- The spread of information.
How do you break through that?
Do you do the thing that you mentioned,
which is you have to build
another app essentially
that allows you the flow of money
outside the legal constraints
placed on you by the government.
So, basically break the law.
- Metaphorically speaking,
if you wanna break outta the
constraints of your culture,
you learn to speak English.
For example, it's not
illegal to speak English,
or even if it is, right, doesn't matter.
But English works everywhere in the world
if you can speak it, and
then you can tap into
a global commerce and
intelligence network.
So Bitcoin is a language, so
you learn to speak Bitcoin
or you learn to speak Lightning,
and then you tap into that network
in whatever manner you can.
- But the problem is,
it's still very difficult
to move Bitcoin around in Russia
and Ukraine now during war.
And there was a sense to me
that the cryptocurrency in general
could be the savior for helping people.
There's millions of refugees,
they're moving all around.
It's very difficult to move money around
in that space to help people.
- I think we're very early.
Like we're very embryonic here.
If you look at the-
- Who's we, sorry.
We as a human civilization
or we operating in the
cryptocurrency space?
- I think the entire crypto
economy is very embryonic
and the human races
adoption of it is embryonic.
We're like one, 2% down
that adoption curve.
If you take Lightning, for example,
the first real commercial applications
of Lightning are just
in the last 12 months.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So, we're like year one.
We might be approaching year two
of commercial Lightning adoption.
And if you look at Lightning adoption,
Lightning's not built into Coinbase,
it's not built into Binance,
it's not built into FTX.
Cash App just implemented
the first implementation,
but not all the features
are built into it.
There's a few dozen, a
dozen Lightning wallets
circulating out there.
So, I think that we're
probably gonna be 36 months
of software development at the point
that every Android phone and every iPhone
has a Bitcoin wallet or a
crypto wallet in it of sorts.
That's a big deal.
If Apple embraced Lightning,
that's a big deal.
- So the adoption is the thing,
like in a war zone adoption,
the people who struggle
the most in war are people
who weren't doing that great
before the war started.
They don't have the
technological sophistication.
- [Michael] Sure.
- The hackers and all those
kinds of people will find a way.
It's just regular people
who are just struggling
to make day by day living.
And so if the adoption
permeates the entire culture,
then you can start to move money
around in the digital space.
If you can psychoanalyze
Jack Dorsey for a second.
So he's one of the early adopters,
or he's one of the people
pushing the early adoption,
this layer three, so inside Cash App.
What do you make of the man
of this decision as a business owner,
as somebody playing in the space?
Why did he do it and what
does that mean for others
at this scale that
might be doing the same?
So incorporating Lightning Networking,
incorporating Bitcoin into their products.
- I think he's been
pretty clear about this.
He feels that Bitcoin is an instrument
of economic empowerment
for billions of people
that are unbanked and have no
property rights in the world.
If you want to give an incorruptible bank
to 8 billion people on the planet,
that's the same as asking the question,
how do you give a full education
through PhD to 8 billion
people on the planet?
And the answer is a digital version
of the 20th century thing,
running on a mobile phone.
And Bitcoin is a bank in cyberspace.
It's run by incorruptible software
and it's for everybody on earth.
So I think when Jack looks at it,
he's very sensitive to the
plight of everybody in Africa.
If you look at Africans, right,
like you're gonna give them banks,
you're not gonna put a bank
branch on every corner.
That's an obscene waste of energy.
You're not gonna run copper
wires across the continent.
That's an obscene waste of energy.
You're not gonna give them gold.
And so, how are you going to provide
people with a decent life?
The metaphor I think is relevant here.
The biological metaphor,
Lex, is a type one diabetic.
If you're a type one
diabetic, you can't form fat.
And if you can't form fat,
then you can't store excess energy.
So that means that, I mean,
fat is the ultimate organic battery,
and if you've got 30 pounds of it,
you can go 60 days without eating.
But if you can't generate
insulin, you can't form fat cells.
And if you can't form fat
cells and store energy,
then you can eat yourself to death.
I mean, you will eat and you will die.
You'll starve to death.
So the lack of property rights
is like being a type one diabetic.
And so if you look at most
people everywhere in the world,
they don't have property rights,
they don't have effective bank,
and their currency is broken.
Like what are the two
things that in theory
would serve as the equivalent
of an organic battery
or an economic battery to civilization?
It would be, I have a
currency which holds its value
and I can store it in a bank.
So, a risk-free currency derivative.
I pay you your money, you
take your life savings,
you put it in a bank, you
save up for your retirement,
you'll have happily ever after.
That's the American dream, right?
That's the idyllic situation.
The real situation is there are no banks.
You can't get a bank account.
So I give you your pay in currency
and then I double the supply
and I give it to my cousin,
or I give it to whatever cause I want,
or I use it to buy weapons.
And then you find a loaf of
bread cost triple next month
is what it costs, and your
life savings is worthless.
And so in that environment,
everybody's ripped back
to stone age barter.
And the problem with that,
even stone age barter
is you're gonna carry your
life savings on your back.
And what happens when the
guy with a machine gun
points it at your head and
just takes your life savings?
So, I think from Jack's point of view,
he thinks that life is,
this is maybe too strong,
but these are my words,
life is hopeless for a lot of people.
And Bitcoin is hope, right?
Because it gives everyone
an engineered monetary asset
that's a bearer instrument,
and it gives them a bank
on their mobile phone
and they don't have to
trust their government
or another counterparty
with their life force.
So there's a secondary thing
I think he's in interested in,
which is the first thing
is the human rights issue.
And the second thing would be the friction
to trade cross borders is so great, right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- You like AI, so I'll give
you a beautiful notion.
Maybe one day there'll be
an artificially intelligent
creature in cyberspace that
is self-sufficient and rich.
- Like that, it would've
sovereignty, you mean.
- Can a robot own money or property?
How about, can a Tesla car?
Can I actually put enough money in a car
for it to drive itself and
maintain itself forever?
Or can I create an artificially
intelligent creature
in cyberspace that is endowed such
that it would live a thousand years
and continue to do its job, right?
We have a word for that in
the real world is institution.
Harvard, Cambridge, Stanford, right?
There are institutions with endowments
that go on in perpetuity.
But what if I wanted to
perpetuate a software program?
And with something like digital property,
with Bitcoin and
Lightning, you could do it.
And on the other hand, with banks
and credit cards, you couldn't, right?
You couldn't ever, so
you can create things
that are beautiful and lasting.
And what's the difference in speed?
Well, it's, so I can either trade
with everybody in the world
at the speed of light,
friction free in 24 hours
writing a Python script,
or I can spend a hundred
billion dollars to trade
with a few million people in the world
after it takes them six
months of application.
The impedance is like a 10 million
to one difference, right?
And the metaphors are literally
like launching something
in orbit versus almost orbit
or vacuum sealing something.
Does it last forever and
does it orbit forever,
or does it go up and come
down and burn up, right?
And I think Jack is interested
in putting freedom in orbit, right?
- (chuckles) Putting freedom.
- Putting freedom in orbit.
And he said it many times, he said,
"The internet needs a native currency,"
right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And no political construct or security
can be a native currency.
You need a property
and you need a property
that can be moved a
million times a second.
Can you oscillate it at 10
kilohertz or a hundred kilohertz?
And the answer is only
if it's a pure digital
construct, permissionless and open.
And so I think that he's
enthusiastic as the technologist
and he is enthusiastic
as the humanitarian.
And what he's doing is to
support both those areas.
He's supporting the Bitcoin
and the Lightning protocol
by building them into his products,
but he is also building the applications
which you need at the Cash App level
in order to commercialize
and deliver the functionality
and the compliance necessary.
And they're related.
- And I should also say he's
just a fascinating person.
For a random reason that
I couldn't even explain
if I tried, I met him a few days ago
and gave him a great big hug
in the middle of nowhere.
There was no explanation.
He just appeared.
That's a fascinating human,
his relationship with art,
with the world, with human suffering,
with technology is fascinating.
I don't know what his path looks like,
but it's interesting that
people like that exist.
And in part I'm saddened that he no longer
is involved with Twitter
directly as a CEO,
because I was hoping
something inside Twitter
would also integrate some of these ideas
of what you're calling digital energy
to see how social networks,
something I'm really interested in
and passionate about could be transformed.
Let me ask you just for
educational purposes. (chuckles)
Can you please explain to me what Web3
and the beef between Jack and
Marc Andreesen is exactly?
Did you see what happened?
Sorry to have you analyze
Twitter like it's Shakespeare,
but can you please explain to me
why there was any drama over this topic?
- First of all, Web3 is a term that's used
to refer to the part of the
economy that's token finance.
So if I'm launching an
application and my ideas to
is to create a token
along with the application
and issue the token to the community
so as to finance the application
and build support for it.
I think that that's the most
common interpretation of Web3.
There are other interpretation too,
so I'm just gonna refer to that one.
And I think the beef in a
nutshell, not articulated,
but I'll articulate it, is whether or not
you should focus all your
energy creating applications
on top of an ethical digital
property like Bitcoin
or whether you should attempt
to create a competitor to it,
which generally would be deemed
as a security by the Bitcoin community.
So, I'm gonna put on my Bitcoin hat here,
right?
- Yeah.
- All the tokens that are being,
if it's driven by a venture capitalist,
well, it's a security.
If there's a CEO and a
CTO, it's a security.
All these projects, they're companies.
Foundations are companies, right?
If you call them a
project or a foundation,
it doesn't make it not a security.
They're all, in essence,
collections of individuals
that are issuing equity
in the form of a token.
And if there's a pre mine,
an IPO, an ICO, a foundation
or any kind of protocol where
there's a group of engineers
that have influence over it,
then to a securities lawyer
or to most Bitcoiners
and definitely to anybody
that's steeped in securities
law, you look at and say,
"Well, that passes the Howie test."
It looks like a security,
it should be sold
to the public pursuant to
disclosures and regulations
and you're just ducking
the IPO process, right?
And so, now we get back
to the ethical issue.
Well, the ethical issue
is if you're trading it
as a commodity and
representing it as a commodity,
while truthfully it's a security,
then it's a violation of ethics rules
and it's probably illegal.
- Well, you keep leaning on this.
Let me push back on that part.
- [Michael] Yeah.
- Maybe you can educate me.
But you keep leaning on
this line of securities law
as if it, with all due respect to lawyers,
as if that line somehow defines
what is and isn't ethical.
I think there's a lot of
correlation as you've discussed,
but I'd like to leave the line aside.
If the law calls something a security,
it doesn't mean in my eyes
that it's is unethical.
I mean, there could be some
technicalities and lawyers
and people play games with this
kind of stuff all the time.
But I take your bigger
point that if there's a CEO,
there's a project lead
that's fundamentally,
well, that to you is
fundamentally different
than the structure of Bitcoin.
- It's not that creating
securities is unethical.
I created a security.
I took a company public, right?
That's not the unethical part.
It's completely ethical
to create securities.
Block is a security, all
companies are securities.
The unethical part is to
represent it as property
when it's a security and to
promote it or trade it as such.
- This whole promotion,
that's also a technical thing.
'cause like what counts
as not as promotion
is a legal thing and you get in trouble
for all these things, but that
the game that lawyers play.
There's an ethical thing here,
which is like what's
right to promote or not.
To me, propaganda is unethical,
but it's usually not illegal. (chuckles)
- You roll the clock back 20 years, right?
All the boiler room pump and dump schemes
were all about someone
pitching a penny stock.
- [Lex] Sure.
- Selling swamp land in Florida.
And if you roll the clock
back forward 20 years,
and I create my own company
and I represented it as the same thing
and I don't make the disclosures, right?
You're just one step removed
from the boiler room scheme.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And that's what's distasteful about it.
There are ways to sell
securities to the public,
but there are expectations.
Maybe we could forget about
whether the security laws
are ethical or not, right?
I will leave that alone.
We'll just start with the
Biblical definition of ethics.
- [Lex] Yes.
- Don't lie, cheat or steal.
So if I'm going to sell something to you,
I need to fully disclose what
I'm selling to you, right?
And that's a matter of
great debate right now.
And so I think that
that's part of the debate.
But the other part of the debate
is whether or not we
need more than one token.
Like we need at least one, right?
- [Lex] Yes.
- We need at least one digital property.
- [Lex] One is better than zero.
- Because zero means there
is no digital economy.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And by the way, the
conventional view of maximalist
is they think there's only
one and everything else isn't.
That's not the point I'm gonna make.
I would say we know there is
at least one digital property,
and that is Bitcoin.
If you can create a truly decentralized
non-custodial bearer instrument
that is not under the control
of any organization that
is fairly distributed,
then you might create another or multiple.
And there may be others out there.
But I think that the
frustration of a lot of people
in the Bitcoin community
and I share this with Jack,
is we could create a hundred
trillion dollars of value
in the real world simply
by building applications
on top of Bitcoin as a foundation.
And so continually trying
to reinvent the wheel
and create competitive things
is a massive waste of time.
And it's diversion of human creativity.
It's like we have an ethical good thing.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And now we're going to try to create
a third or a fourth one.
Why?
- Well, let's talk about it.
So first of all, I'm with you,
but let me ask you this
interesting question
because we talked about
properties and securities.
Let's talk about conflict of interest.
So you said you could advertise public,
you have a popular Twitter account.
It's hilarious and insightful.
You do promote Bitcoin in a sense.
I don't know if you would say that.
But do you think there's
a conflict of interest
in anyone who owns
Bitcoin promoting Bitcoin?
Is it the same as you
promoting the farming?
- I would say no.
There's an interest.
I think that you can promote
a property or an idea
to the extent that you don't control it.
I think that the point at which you start
to have a conflict of interest
is when you're promoting
a proprietary product
or proprietary security.
A security in general
is a proprietary asset.
So for example, if you look at my Twitter,
you'll find that I make lots
of statements about Bitcoin.
You won't ever see me making a statement
that say MicroStrategy
stock will go up forever.
Right, I'm not promoting a security, MSTR,
because at the end of the
day, MSTR is a security,
it is proprietary.
I have proprietary interest in it.
I have a disproportionate
amount of control
and influence on the direction whereas-
- The control is the problem.
The control is the problem
because you have interest in both.
You can very, if Bitcoin is a successful,
as we're talking about,
you are very possibly
can become the richest human on earth
given how much you own in Bitcoin, right?
The wealthiest, not the richest.
I don't know what those words mean.
- I would benefit economically.
- [Lex] Economic, you
would benefit economically.
- That's true.
- So, the reason that's
not conflict of interest
is because the word property,
that Bitcoin is an idea
and it's Bitcoin is open.
- [Michael] It's because I don't own it.
- You don't.
- I don't control it.
In essence, the ethical line here
is could I print myself
10 million more Bitcoin
or not, right?
I could.
- Or can anyone, right?
It's not just you, it's can anyone.
Because can you promote somebody else's?
Yes, I guess you can.
Like can you promote Apple (chuckles)
when you have no stake.
- It's like you could
have a Twitter account
where you promote oil
or you promote camping
or you promote family values
or promote a carnivore diet
or promote the Iron Man, right?
- But you're not gonna get
wealthier if you promote camping.
'cause you can't own a stake in.
I mean, you own a lot of Bitcoin.
What is that?
Don't you own the stake
in the idea of Bitcoin?
- Yeah, I would grant you that.
- But the lack of control is
the fundamental ethical line
that you just, you don't have.
All you are is you're a fan of the idea.
You believe in the idea
and the power of the idea.
You can't take that idea away from others.
- Let's come back to, let me give you
some maybe easier examples.
If you were the head of
the Marine Corps, right?
And someone came to you and
said, I created Marine coin.
And the twist on Marine coin is I want you
to tell every Marine that
they'll get an extra Marine coin
when they get their next stripe.
And then I'm gonna give you,
and I'm gonna let you buy Marine coin now,
and then after you buy Marine coin,
I want you to like
promote it to them, right?
At some point, if you start to have
a disproportional influence on it,
or if you're in a conversation with people
with disproportionate influence
becomes conflict of interest
and it would make you profoundly
uncomfortable, I think.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- If the head of the Marine Corps
started promoting anything
that looked like a security.
Now if the head of the Marine Corps
started promoting canoeing,
you might think he's kind of wacky.
Like maybe like that's kind of
a waste of time at a distraction.
But to the extent that
canoeing is not a security,
not a problem unless you...
Ultimately the issue of decentralization
is really a critical one.
- So not having a head.
So is it something, can
Bitcoin be replicated?
So all the things that you're saying
that make it a property,
can that be replicated,
have any other-
- I think it's possible to
create other crypto properties.
- Does the having a head like of a project
a thing that limits its
ability to be a property
if you try to replicate a project?
Or is that the fundamental flaw?
- Look, I think the real fundamental issue
is you just never want it to change.
Like if you really want
something decentralized,
you want a genetic
template that substantially
is not gonna change for a thousand years.
So I think Satoshi said it at one point.
He said the nature of the software
is such that by version 0.1,
it's genetic code was set.
If there was any development team
that's continually changing
it on a routine basis,
it becomes harder and harder
to maintain is decentralization
because now there's the issue
of who's influencing the changes.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So what you really want
is a very, very simple idea, right?
The simplest idea, I'm
just gonna keep track
of who owns 21 million parts of energy.
And when someone proposes
big functional upgrades,
you don't really want that development
to go on the base layer.
You want that development
to go on the layer threes
because now Cash App has a
proprietary set of functionality
and it's a security.
And if you're gonna promote
the use of this thing,
you're not gonna promote
the layer three security
because that's an edge to a given entity
and you're trusting the counterparty.
You're gonna promote the layer
one or most the layer two.
- Okay, so one of the
fascinating things about Bitcoin,
and sorry to romanticize certain notions,
but Satoshi Nakamoto, that
the founder is anonymous.
Maybe you can speak to
whether that's useful,
but also I just like
the psychology of that
to imagine that there's a
human being that was able
to create something special and walk away.
So first, are you Satoshi Nakamoto?
- I'm certain I'm not. (chuckles)
(Lex chuckles)
No, actually, I think the
providence is really important
and if I were to look at
the highlighted points,
I think having a founder
that was anonymous
or synonymous is important.
I think the founder
disappearing is also important.
I think that the fact
that the Satoshi coins
never moved is also important.
I think the lack of an
initial coin offering
is also important.
I think the lack of a
corporate sponsor is important.
I think the fact that
it traded for 15 months
with no commercial value
was also important.
I think that the
simplicity of the protocol
is very important.
I think that the outcome
of the block size wars
is very important.
And all of those things
add up to common property.
They're all indicia, indicators
of a digital property
as opposed to security.
If there was a Satoshi sitting around,
sitting on top of $50
billion worth of Bitcoin,
I don't think it would
cripple Bitcoin as property,
but I think it would undermine
its digital property.
And if I wanted to undermine
a crypto asset network,
I would do the opposite
of all those things.
I would launch one myself.
I would sell 25% or 50%
to the general public.
I would keep some of the initial,
I would pre mine some
stuff or early mine it,
and I would keep an influence on it.
Those are all the opposite
of what you would do
in order to create common property.
And so I see the entire story as Satoshi
giving a gift of digital property
to the human race and disappearing.
- Do you think it was one person?
Do you have ideas of who it could be?
- I don't care to speculate. (laughs)
- [Lex] Okay, but do you
think it was one person?
- I think it was one
person, maybe in conjunction
with a bunch of others.
I mean, it might have
been a group of people
that were working together, but
certainly there's a Satoshi.
- I mean, it's just so fascinating to me
that one person could be
so brave and thoughtful.
Or do you think a lot of his accent,
like the block size wars,
the decision to make a
block a certain size.
All the things you mentioned led up
to the characteristics
that make Bitcoin property.
Do you think that's an accident,
or was it deeply thought through?
This is almost like a
history of science question.
- I think people tried it.
They tried 40 of them, right?
I mean, I think there's a history
of attempting to create
something like this.
And it was tried many, many times
and they failed for different reasons.
And I think that it's like Prometheus
tried to start a fire 47 times
and maybe the 48th time it sparked.
And that's how I see this is
the first one that sparked
and it sets a roadmap for us.
And I think if you're
looking for any one word
that characterize, it's fair, right?
The whole point of the network
is it's a fair launch,
a fair distribution.
Like yeah, I have
Bitcoin, but I bought it.
In fact, at this point
we've paid $4 billion
of real cash to buy it.
If I was sitting on the same
position and I had it for free,
then there's always this
question of did I pay,
or I bought it for a nickel,
a coin, or a penny of coin.
The question is, was it fair?
And that's a very hard
question to answer, right?
Did you acquire the Bitcoin
that you own fairly?
And if you rolled the clock back,
you could have bought it
for a nickel or a dime,
but that was when it was a million times
more likely to fail, right?
When the risk was greater,
the cost was lower,
and then over time the risk became lower
and the cost became greater.
And the real critical thing
was to allow the marketplace
absent any powerful,
interested actor, right?
It's almost like if Satoshi
held a million coins
and then stayed engaged for 10 more years,
tweaking things in the background,
there'd still be that question.
But what we've got is
really a beautiful thing.
We've got a chain reaction in cyberspace
or an ideology spreading
virally in the world
that has seasoned in a
fair, ethical fashion.
Sometimes it's a very
violent, brutal fashion
with all the volatility, right?
And there's been a lot of
sound and fury along the way.
- How do you psychoanalyze,
how do you deal from a financial,
from a human perspective
with the volatility?
You mentioned you could
have gotten it for a nickel,
and the risk was great.
Where's the risk today?
What's your sense?
- We're 13 years into
this entire activity.
I think the risk has never been lower.
If you look at all the risks, right?
The risks in the early years are,
is the engineering protocol proper?
Like one megabyte block size,
10 minute clock frequency
cryptography is first,
will it be hacked or will
it crash 730,000 blocks
and it hasn't crashed?
Will it be hacked?
Hasn't been hacked.
But it's a lengthy thing, right?
You wait 13 years to
see if it'll be hacked.
But on the other hand,
with a billion dollars,
it's not as interesting a target
as it is with a hundred billion.
And when it gets to be worth a trillion,
then it's a bigger target.
So, the risk has been
bleeding off over time
as the network monetized.
I think the second question
is, will it be banned?
You couldn't know.
It literally could have been
banned at many times early on.
In fact, in 2013 I tweeted on the subject,
I thought it would be banned.
I made a very infamous tweet.
- Infamous tweet, yeah.
- I thought it was gonna be banned.
In 2014, the IRS designated it as property
and gave it property tax treatment, okay?
So they could have
given it a tax treatment
where you had to pay tax
on the unrealized
capital gains every year,
and it probably would've
crushed it to death, right?
So it could have been in any number
of places banned by a government,
but in fact it was
legitimized as property.
And then the question is,
would it be hacked or would it be copied?
Will it be something better than that?
And it was copied 15,000 times.
And the story of all those
and they either diverged
to be something totally
different and not comparable,
or someone trying to copy
a non sovereign bearer
instrument store of value
found that their networks crashed
to be 1% of what Bitcoin is.
So now we're sitting at a point
where all those risks are out of the way.
I would say that year one of
institutional adoption is,
it started August, 2020, that's
when MicroStrategy bought
$250 million worth of Bitcoin.
And we put that out on the wire.
We were the first publicly traded company
to actually buy Bitcoin.
I don't think you could have
found a $5 million purchase
from a public company before we did that.
So that was kinda like a gun going off.
And then in the next 12
months, Tesla bought Bitcoin,
Square bought Bitcoin, and
I'd say now we're in year two
of institutional adoption, and about 24,
should be 24 publicly
traded Bitcoin miners
by the end of this quarter.
So you're looking at 36
publicly traded companies,
and you've got 50, at least
in the range of $50 billion
of Bitcoin on the balance sheet
of publicly traded companies
and hundreds of billions of dollars
of market cap of Bitcoin
exposed companies.
So, I would say the asset,
decade one was
entrepreneurial experimental,
decade two is a rotation from
entrepreneurs to institutions
and is becoming institutionalized.
So maybe decade one, you
go from zero to a trillion,
and a decade two, you go from 1 trillion
to a hundred trillion.
- What about governments,
government adoption?
You said institutional adoption.
Are governments important in this?
Maybe making it some
governments incorporating it
into as a currency into their
banks, all that kind of stuff.
Is that important?
And if it is, when will it happen?
- It's not essential for the
success of the asset class,
but I think it's inevitable
in various degrees over time.
But the most likely thing to happen next
is large acquisitions by
institutional investors
of Bitcoin as a digital gold
where they're just swapping
out gold for digital gold
and thinking of it like that.
And the government entities
most likely to be involved
with that would be sovereign wealth funds.
If you look at all the
sovereign wealth funds
that are holding big tech stock, equities,
the Swiss, the Norwegians,
the Middle Easterners,
if you can hold big tech
then holding digital gold
would be not far removed from that.
That's a non-controversial adoption.
I think there are
opportunities for governments
that are much more profound, right?
If a government started to adopt Bitcoin
as a treasury reserve asset,
that's much bigger than
just an asset investment
that's 100X bigger.
And you could imagine
that's like a trillion dollar opportunity.
Like any government
that wanted to adopt it
as a treasury reserve asset
would probably generate
trillions of dollars,
a trillion or more of value.
And then the thing that
people think about is,
well, will oil ever be priced in Bitcoin
or any other export commodity?
I think there's like $1.8 trillion
or more of export
commodities in the world.
And right now they're
all priced in dollars.
I think that this is a colorful thing,
but it not really that relevant.
Like you could sell all
that stuff in dollars.
The relevant decision that
any institution makes,
whether they're a non-profit university,
a corporation or a government,
is what's your treasury reserve asset?
And if your treasury
reserve asset is the peso,
and if the peso is losing 20%
or 30% of its value a year,
then your balance sheet is
collapsing within five years.
And if the treasury
reserve asset is dollars
in currency derivatives and US treasuries,
then you're getting your seven.
Right now it's probably 15%
or more monetary inflation.
We're running double the historic average.
You could argue triple.
Somewhere between double and triple
depending upon what your metric is.
So, do I think it'll happen?
I think that they're conservative,
but they have to be shocked.
And I think there is a shock.
The late Russian sanctions are a big shock
that when the West sees $300
billion worth of Russian gold
and currency derivatives,
I think it, you know,
you got the famous quote by Putin
that we have to rethink
our treasury strategies
and that pushes everybody
toward a commodity strategy.
What commodities do I wanna hold?
I think that's got a
lot of people thinking.
I think it's got the Chinese thinking.
Everybody wants to be the
reserve currency, right?
So if I buy $50 billion
worth of dollars every year,
then I buy 500 billion over a decade
and I probably pay $250
billion of inflation costs
on the backs of my citizens in a decade.
- So inflation could be one
of the sources of shock.
And you wonder if there
is a switch to Bitcoin,
whether it would be a bang or a whimper.
Like what is the nature of
the shock or the transition?
- I think that the year
2022 is pretty catalytic
for digital assets in general
and for Bitcoin in particular.
The Canadian trucker crisis,
I think educated hundreds
of millions of people
and made them start questioning
their property rights and their banks.
I think the Ukraine was a second shock,
but I think that the Russian
sanctions was a third shock.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- I think all three of the,
and I think hyperinflation
in the rest of the world
is a fourth shock and
then persistent inflation
in the US is a fifth shock.
So, I think it's a perfect storm.
And if you put all these events together,
what do they signify?
They signify the rational conclusion
for any person thinking about this is,
I'm not sure if I can trust my property,
I don't know if I have property rights,
I don't know if I can trust the bank.
And if I'm politically
at odds with the leader
of my own country, I'm
gonna lose my property.
And if I'm politically
at odds with the owner
of another country, I'm
still gonna lose my property.
And when push comes to shove,
the banks will freeze my
assets and seize them.
And I think that is playing out
in front of everybody in the world
such that your logical response would be,
I'm going to convert my weak
currency to a strong currency.
Like I'll convert my peso
and lira to the dollar.
I'm going to convert my weak
property to strong property.
I'm gonna sell my
building downtown Moscow,
and I'd rather own a
building in New York City.
I'd rather own in a powerful nation
than be stuck with a building in Nigeria
or a building in Argentina or whatever.
So, I'm gonna sell my weak properties,
buy strong properties, I'm
gonna convert my physical assets
to digital assets.
I'd rather own a digital building
than own a physical building.
Because if I had a billion
dollar building in Moscow,
who can I rent that to?
But if I have a billion
dollar digital building,
I can rent it to anybody
in any city in the world,
anybody with money and
the maintenance cost
is almost nothing.
And I can hold it for
a hundred years, okay?
So it's an indestructible building.
And then finally, I wanna
move from having my assets
in a bank with a counterparty
to self custody assets, right?
And this is not, it's not just Ukraine,
but this is like the
story in Turkey, Lebanon,
Syria, Afghanistan, Iraq, South America,
you don't really wanna be sitting
with $10 million in a bank in Istanbul.
The bank's gonna freeze your
money, convert it to lira,
devalue the lira, and then feed it
back to you over 17 years, right?
- So self custody assets
would be layer one Bitcoin?
- Self custody assets, it's like if I got
my own hardware wallet
and I've either got your
highest form of self custody
would be Bitcoin on
your own hardware wallet
or Bitcoin on your own self custody.
And the other thing people think about
is how do I get crypto dollars
like Tether, like some stable coin?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Like I'd rather, if you had a choice,
would you rather have your money in a bank
in a war zone in dollars,
or have your money in a stable coin
on your mobile phone in dollars, right?
I mean, you would take the latter risk
rather than the former risk.
- In a war zone, definitely yeah.
- [Michael] And you
can see that happening,
like we've gone from 5 billion
in stable coins to 200 billion.
- Yeah.
- [Michael] In the last 24 months.
- So, I do think there's massive demand
for crypto dollars in the
form of a US dollar asset.
And everybody in the world
would say, "Yeah, I want that."
Well, unless you're
just an extreme patriot,
but most people in the world
would say, "I want that."
And then a lesser group
of people would say,
"I think I want to be
able to carry my property
in the palm of my hand, so
I have self custody of it."
- So Bitcoin price has gone
through quite a rollercoaster.
What do you think is the
high point is gonna hit?
- I think it'll go forever, right?
I mean, I think the Bitcoin is going to,
it's going to climb in
a serpentine fashion.
It's going to advance and come back
and it's gonna keep climbing.
I think that the volatility attracts
all the capital into the marketplace.
And so the volatility makes
it the most interesting thing
in the financial universe.
It also generates massive yield
and massive returns for traders,
and that attracts capital.
Like we're talking about the difference
between 5% return and 500% return.
So the fast money is
attracted by the volatility.
The volatility's been
decreasing year by year by year.
I think that it's stabilizing.
I don't think we'll see as much volatility
in the future as we have in the past.
I think that if we look at Bitcoin
and model it as digital gold, you know,
the market cap goes to
between 10 and 20 trillion.
Remember gold is defective
property, gold is dead money.
You have a billion dollars of gold
that sits in a vault for a decade.
It's very hard to mortgage the gold.
It's also very hard to rent the gold.
You can't loan the gold.
No one's going to create
a business with your gold.
So gold doesn't generate much of a yield.
So for that reason, most
people wouldn't store
a billion dollars for a decade in gold.
They would buy a billion dollars
of commercial real estate, property.
And the reason why is
because I can rent it
and generate a yield on it
that's in excess of the maintenance cost.
So if you consider digital property,
that's a hundred to $200
trillion addressable market.
So I would think it goes from 10 trillion
to a hundred trillion as people
start to think of it as digital property.
- What does that mean in
terms of price per coin?
- At 500,000, right?
That's a $10 trillion asset-
- [Lex] Essentially.
- At 5 million, that's a
hundred trillion dollars asset.
- So you think it crosses a
million, it can go even higher.
- Yeah, I think it keeps going up forever.
I mean, there's no reason
we can't go to 10 million a coin, right?
Because digital property
isn't the highest form, right?
Gold was that low frequency money.
Property is mid frequency money.
But when I start to program it faster,
it starts to look like digital energy
and then it doesn't just replace property,
then you're starting to replace bonds.
It's a hundred trillion in bonds.
There's 50 to hundred trillion
in other currency derivatives.
And then and these are all
conventional use cases, right?
I think that there's 350 trillion
to $500 trillion worth of currency,
currency derivatives in the world.
And when I say that, I mean things
that are valued based
upon fiat cash flows.
Any commercial real estate,
any bond, any sovereign debt,
any currency itself, any
derivatives to those things,
they're all derivatives
and they're all defective.
And they're all defective
because of this persistent
seven to 14% lapse
which we call inflation
or monetary expansion.
Can we switch?
So I'm just gonna talk
about the energy side of it.
- Sure.
- [Michael] Like the innovative piece.
- Yeah.
- Let's just start with this
idea that I've got a hotel
worth a billion dollars
with a thousand rooms.
When it becomes a dematerialized hotel.
- I love that word so much, by the way,
dematerialized hotel.
- Wait, we're across from
the fountain blow here.
Imagine the fountain
blow is dematerialized.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- The problem with the physical hotel
is it gotta hire real people
moving subject to the speed of sound
and physics laws and Newton's laws.
And I can rent it to
people in Miami Beach.
But if it was a digital
hotel, I could rent the room
to people in Paris, London,
and New York every night,
and I can run it with robots.
And as soon as I do that, I
can rent it by the room hour
and I can rent it by the room minute.
And so I start to chop my hotel
up into a hundred thousand
room hours that I sell
to the highest bidder
anywhere in the world.
And you can see, all
of a sudden the yield,
the rent and the income of the property
is dramatically increased.
I can also see the maintenance
cost of the property falls.
I get on Moore's law and
I'm operating in cyberspace.
So I got rid of Newton's laws,
I got rid of all the friction
and all those problems.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- I tapped into the
benefits of cyberspace.
I created a global property.
I started monetizing at
different frequencies.
And of course now I can mortgage it
to anybody in the world, right?
I mean, you're not gonna
be able to get a mortgage
on a Turkish building from
someone in South Africa.
You have to find someone that's local
to the culture you're in.
So when you start to
move from analog property
to digital property, it's
not just a little bit better,
it's a lot better.
And what I just described, Lex,
is like the DeFi vision, right?
It's the beauty of DeFi flash loans,
money moving at high velocity.
At some point if the
hotel is dematerialized,
then what's the difference
between renting a hotel room
and loaning a block of stock, right?
I'm just finding the highest
best use of the thing.
- It feels like the magic
really emerges though,
when you build a lot a market of layer two
and layer three
technologies on top of that.
So like, maybe you can
correct me if I'm wrong,
but for all these hotels and
all these kinds of ideas,
it's always touching humans at some point
and the consumers or humans,
business holders and so on,
so you have to create interface,
you have to create services
that make all of that super
efficient, super fun to use,
pleasant, effective, all
those kinds of things.
And so you have to build a
whole economy on top of that.
- Yeah, and I happen to
think that won't be done
by the crypto industry at all.
I think that'll be done by
centralized applications.
I think it'll be the
Citadels of the world,
the high speed traders of
the world, the New Yorkers,
I think it'll be Binance, FTX and Coinbase
as a layer three exchange
that will give you the yield
and will give you the
loan and the best terms
because ultimately you have to
jump these compliance hoops.
It comes, like BlockFi can give you yield,
but they have to do it in compliant way
with the United States jurisdiction.
So ultimately those applications
to use that digital property
and either generate a loan on,
give you a loan on it,
or give you yield on it,
are gonna come from companies.
But the difference, the
fundamental difference
is it could be companies
anywhere in the world.
So if a company in Singapore comes up
with a better offering, right?
Then the capital is gonna
start to flow to Singapore.
I can't send 10 steady
blocks of LA to Singapore
to rent during a festival.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But I can send 10 blocks
of Bitcoin to Singapore.
So you've got a truly global
market that's functioning
and this asset and is
their second order asset.
For example, maybe you're
an American citizen
and you own 10 Bitcoin
and someone in Singapore
will generate 27% yield in the Bitcoin,
but legally you can't
send the money to them
or the Bitcoin to them, it doesn't matter,
because the fact that that exists
means that someone in Hong Kong
will borrow the 10 Bitcoin
from somebody in New York,
and then they will put on
the trade in Singapore,
and that will create a demand for Bitcoin,
which will drive up the price of Bitcoin,
which will result in an
effective tax-free yield
for the person in the US
that's not even in the jurisdiction.
So there's nothing that's
going on in Singapore
to drive up the price of your land in LA.
But there is something going
on everywhere in the world
to drive up the price of
property and cyberspace
if there's only one digital Manhattan.
And so there's a dynamic there,
which is profound because it's global.
But now let's go to the next extreme.
I'm still giving you a
fairly conventional idea,
which is let's just loan the
money fast on a global network
and let's just rent the hotel
room fast in cyberspace.
But now let's move to maybe
a more innovative idea.
The first generation of internet
brought a lot of productivity,
but there's also just
a lot of flaws in it.
For example, Twitter is full of garbage.
Instagram DMs are full of garbage.
Your Twitter DMs are full of garbage.
YouTube is full of scams.
Every 15 minutes there's a
Michael Saylor Bitcoin giveaway
spun up on YouTube.
- [Lex] Yep.
- My Office 365 inbox,
it's full of garbage,
millions of spam messages.
I'm running four different email filters.
My company spends million dollars a year
to fight denial of service attacks
and all sorts of other security things.
There are denial of
service attacks everywhere
against everybody in
cyberspace all the time.
It's extreme.
And we're all beset with hostility, right?
You've been a victim of it on Twitter.
You go on Twitter and people post stuff
they would never say to your face.
And then if you look, you find out
that the account was
created like three days ago
and it's not even a real person.
So, we're beset with phishing attacks
and scams and spam bots
and garbage and why?
And the answer is because
the first generation
of internet was digital
information and there's no energy.
There's no conservation
of energy in cyberspace.
The thing that makes the universe work
is conservation of energy.
Like if I went to a hotel room,
I'd have to post a credit card,
and then if I smashed the place up,
there'd be economic consequences,
maybe there'd be criminal consequences,
there might be reputational consequences.
A lamp might fall on me.
But in the worst case thing,
I can only smash up one hotel room.
Now imagine I could actually
write a Python script
to send myself to every
hotel room in the world,
every minute, not post a credit card
and smash them all up anonymously.
The thing that makes the
universe work is friction,
speed of sound, speed of light.
And the fact that it's
ultimately, it's conservative.
You're either energy or your matter,
but once you've used
the energy, it's gone.
And you can't do infinite everything.
That's missing in cyberspace right now.
And if you look at all
of the moral hazards
and all of the product
defects that we have
in all of these products,
most of them, 99% of them
could be cured if we
introduced conservation
of energy into cyberspace.
And that's what you can do
with high speed digital
property, high speed Bitcoin.
And by high speed, I mean,
not 20 transactions a day.
I mean, 20,000 transactions a day.
So, how do you do that?
Well, I let everybody on
Twitter post a thousand
or 10,000 satoshis via Lightning wallet,
a Lightning badge, gimme an orange check.
If you put up 20 bucks once in your life,
you could give 300 million
people an orange check.
Right now you don't
have a blue check, Lex.
You're a famous person.
I don't know why you
don't have a blue check.
Have you ever applied for a blue check?
- No.
- There are 360,000 people
on Twitter with a blue check.
There are 300 million people on Twitter.
So the conventional way to verify accounts
is elitist, archaic.
- Yeah, how does it work?
How do you get blue check?
- You gotta apply and wait six months
and you have to post like three articles
in the public mainstream media.
- Sure.
- That illustrates you're
a person of interest.
- [Lex] Interesting.
- Generally, they would grant them
to CEOs of public companies,
or the whole idea is
to verify that you are
who you say you are.
- [Lex] Yeah, who you are.
Right.
- But the question is, why
isn't everybody verified?
And there's a couple of threads on that.
One, is some people don't wanna be doxed,
they wanna be anonymous.
- [Lex] Sure.
- But they're even anonymous
people that should be verified.
Because otherwise you're
subjecting their entire following
to phishing attacks and
scams and hostility.
But the other-
- What's the orange verification?
So this idea, can you actually elaborate
a little bit more if you put up 20 bucks?
- Yeah, I think everybody
on Twitter ought be able
to get an orange check if they
could come up with like $10.
- And what is the power
of that orange check?
What does that verify exactly?
- You basically post a security deposit
for your safe patches through cyberspace.
So the way it would work is
if you've got $10 once in your life,
you can basically show
that you're credit worthy.
And that's your pledge to me
that you're gonna act responsibly.
So you put the 10 of the $20
into the Lightning wallet,
you get an orange check.
Then Twitter just gives you
a setting where I can say,
the only people that can
DM me are orange checks.
The only people that can post on my tweets
are orange checks.
So instead of locking out the public
and just letting your followers comment,
you lock out all the unverified.
And that means people
that don't wanna post
$10 security deposit can't comment.
Once you've done those two things,
then you're in a position
to monetize malice.
Right, monetize motion or
malice for that matter.
But let's just say for
the sake of argument,
you post something and 9,700 bots spin up,
and pitch their whatever scam.
Right now you sit and
you go report, report,
report, report, report, report.
And if you spend an hour,
you get through half of them,
you waste an hour of your life
and they just spin up another 97 kazillion
because they've got a Python
script spinning it up,
so it's hopeless.
But on the other hand, if you report them
and they really are a bot,
Twitter's got a method
to actually delete the account.
They know that they're bots.
The problem is not they don't know
how to delete the account.
The problem is there are no consequences
when they delete the account.
So if there are consequences
Twitter could give,
they could just seize
the $10 or seize the $20,
'cause it's a bot, it's
a malicious criminal act
or whatever as a violation
of the platform rules.
You end up seizing $10,000,
give half the money
to the reporter and half the
money to the Twitter platform.
- That's a really powerful idea,
but that's tying it,
that's adding friction
akin to the kind of friction
you have in the physical world.
You're tying, you have consequences.
You have real consequences.
- [Michael] There's putting
conservation of energy.
- Conservation of energy.
- There's no friction,
there's no nothing on this earth, right?
I mean, you can't walk across the room
without friction, right?
So friction is not bad, right?
Unnecessary friction is bad.
So in this particular case,
you're introducing conservation of energy
and in essence you're
introducing the concept
of consequence or truth into cyberspace.
And that means if you do wanna
spin up 10 million fakes,
fake Lex Fridmans, right?
- [Lex] Its gonna cost.
- It's gonna cost you a
hundred million dollars
to spin up 10 million fake Lexes.
- But the thing is, you could
do that with the dollar,
but your case, you're
saying that it's more tied
to physical reality when
you do that with Bitcoin?
- Yeah, well, let's follow
up on that idea a bit more.
If you did do it with the
dollar, then the question is,
how does 6 billion people
deposit the dollars, right?
Because what you're doing is, yeah,
could you do it with a credit card?
Like how do you send dollars?
Well, you have to dox yourself.
Like, it's not easy.
So you're talking about inputting
a credit card transaction,
doxing yourself, and now
you've just eliminated
the 2 billion people that
don't have credit cards
or don't have banks.
You've also got a problem with everybody
that wants to remain anonymous.
But you've also got this other problem,
which is credit cards are
expensive transactions,
low frequency, slow settlement.
So do you really want to pay 2.5%
every time you actually
show a $20 deposit?
And maybe you could do a kludgy version
of this for a subset of people.
It's 10% as good if you did it
with conventional payment rails.
But what you can't do is the next idea,
which is I want the orange badge
to be used to give me safe passage
through cyberspace tripping
across every platform.
How do I solve the
denial of service attacks
against a website?
I publish a website, you hit
it with a million requests.
Okay, now how do I deal with that?
Well, I can lock you out
and I can make it a zero trust website,
and then you have to be coming at me
through a trusted firewall
or with a trusted credential.
But that's a pretty draconian thing.
Or I could put it behind a Lightning wall.
A Lightning wall would
be I just challenge you,
Lex, you wanna browse my website?
You have to show me your a
hundred thousand satoshis.
Do you have a hundred thousand satoshis?
Click.
Okay, now you click away a hundred times
or a thousand times.
And after a thousand times, I'm like,
"Well, now, Lex, you're getting offensive
to take a satoshi from you,
or 10 satoshis a micro transaction."
You wanna hit me a million times?
I'm taking all your satoshis
and locking you out.
What you wanna do is you want
to go through 200 websites
a day and what you want,
every time you cross a
domain, you need to be able to
in a split second, prove
that you've got some asset.
And now when you cross
back, when you exit domain,
you wanna fetch your asset back.
So how do I, in a friction free fashion,
browse through dozens
or hundreds of websites,
post a security deposit for safe passage,
and then get it back.
You couldn't afford to pay
a credit card fee each time.
When you think about
two point a half percent
as a transaction fee, it
means you trade the money
40 times and it's gone.
- [Lex] (chuckles) Yeah.
- It's gone.
- Yeah, so you can't do
this kind of hopping around
through the internet with
this kind of verification
that grounds you to a physical reality.
It's a really, really interesting idea.
Why hasn't that been done?
- I think you need two things.
You need an idea like a
digital asset like Bitcoin
that's a bearer instrument
for final settlement.
And then you need a high
speed transaction network
like Lightning where the transaction cost
might be a 20th of a penny or less.
And if you roll the clock back 24 months,
I don't think you had
the Lightning Network
in a stable point.
It's really just the past 12 months.
It's an idea you could
think about this year.
And I think you need
to be aware of Bitcoin
as something other than like
a scary speculative asset.
So I really think we're
just the beginning,
- The embryonic stage.
I have to ask Michael Saylor,
you said before there's
no second best to Bitcoin.
What would be the second best?
Traditionally there's
Ethereum with smart contracts,
Cardano with proof of stake,
Polkadot with interoperability
between blockchains, Dogecoin
has the incredible power
of the meme, privacy with Monero.
I just can keep going.
There's of course after
the block size wars,
the different offshoots of Bitcoin.
- I think if you decompose
or segment the crypto market,
you've got crypto property,
Bitcoin is the king of that, you know,
and other Bitcoin forks that wanted
to be a bearer instrument store of value
would be a property, a
Bitcoin Cash or a Litecoin,
something like that.
Then you've got cryptocurrencies.
I don't think Bitcoin's a currency
because a currency, I define
in nation states sense.
A currency is a digital
asset that you can transfer
in a transaction without
incurring a taxable obligation.
So that means it has to be a stable dollar
or a stable euro or a
stable yen, a stable coin.
So I think you've got
cryptocurrencies, Tether,
Circle, most famous, I think
you've got crypto platforms,
and Ethereum is the most
famous of the crypto platforms,
the platform upon which, you know,
with smart contract
functionality, et cetera.
And then I think you've
got just crypto securities.
It's just like my favorite
whatever, meme coin.
And I love it, 'cause I love
it and it's attached to my game
or my company or my
persona or my whatever.
I think if you pushed me and said,
"Well, what's the second best?"
I would say the world wants two things.
It wants crypto property
as a savings account,
and it wants cryptocurrency
as a checking account.
And that means that the most popular thing
really is going to be a
stable coin dollar, right?
There's a maybe a fight right now.
It might be Tether, right?
But a stable dollar because I feel like
the market opportunity, it's not clear
that there'll be one that will win.
The class of stable dollars is probably
a one to $10 trillion market easily.
I think that in the crypto platform space,
Ethereum will compete with Solana
and Binance Smart Chain and the like.
And are there certain
characteristics of any of them
that kind of stand out to you?
Don't you think the competition
is based on a set of features?
Also, so the set of features
that a cryptocurrency provides,
but also the community that it provides.
Don't you think the community matters
and sort of the adoption,
the dynamic of the adoption
both across the developers
and the investors.
- And if I'm looking at them,
I mean the first question
is what's the regulatory risk,
how likely is it to be deemed
a property versus security?
And the second is what's
the competitive risk?
And the third is what's the
speed and the performance.
And all those things lead to the question
of what's the security risk?
How likely is it to crash and burn,
and how stable or unstable is it?
And then there's the marketing risk.
I mean, there are different teams
behind each of these things
and communities behind them.
I think that the big cloud
looming over the crypto industry
is regulatory treatment
of cryptocurrencies
and regulatory treatment
of crypto securities
and crypto platforms.
And I think that won't be determined
until the end of the first
Biden administration.
For example, there are
people that would like
only US FDIC insured banks
to issue cryptocurrencies.
They want JP Morgan to issue
a crypto dollar backed one-to-one.
But then in the US
right now we have Circle
and we have other companies
that are licensed entities
that are backed by cash
and cash equivalents,
but they're not FDIC insured banks.
There's also a debate in Congress about
whether state chartered
banks should be able
to issue these things.
And then we have Tether and others
that are outside of the US jurisdiction,
they're probably not backed
by cash and cash equivalents.
They're backed by stuff.
And we don't know what stuff.
And then finally you have UST and D,
which are algorithmic stable coins, right?
That are even more innovative,
further outside the compliance framework.
So if you ask who's gonna win?
The question is really, I don't
know, will the market decide
or will the regulators decide.
If the regulator get outta the
way and the market fought up?
Well, then it's an interesting discussion.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And then I think that all bets are off
if the regulators get more
heavy handed with this.
And I think you could
have the same discussion
with crypto properties
like the DeFi exchanges
and the crypto exchanges.
The SEC would like to
regulate the crypto exchanges.
They like to regulate the DeFi exchanges.
That means they may regulate
the crypto platforms
and at what rate and in what fashion.
And so I think that I
could give you an opinion
if it was limited to competition
under the current regulatory regime.
But I think that the
regulations are so fast moving
and it's so uncertain that
it's, you can't make a decision
without considering the potential
actions of the regulators.
- I hope the regulators
get out of the way.
Can you steelman the
case that Dogecoin is,
I guess the second best cryptocurrency
or if you don't consider
Bitcoin a cryptocurrency,
but instead of crypto property.
- I would classify it as crypto property
because the US dollar is a currency.
So unless your crypto asset
is pegged algorithmically
or stably to the value of
the dollar is not a currency,
it's a property or it's an asset.
- So then can you steelman the case
that Dogecoin is the
best cryptocurrency then,
because Bitcoin is not even in that list.
- The debate is gonna be whether
it's property or security,
and there's a debate whether
it's decentralized enough.
So let's assume it was decentralized.
- Yep.
- Well, it's increasing at not quite five,
what 5% a year inflation rate.
But it's not 5% exponentially,
it's like a plus 5 million, 5%,
something capped in is less.
I forget the exact number,
but it's an inflationary property.
It's got a lower inflation
rate than the US dollar,
and it's got a much lower inflation rate
than many other fiat currencies.
So, I think you could say that.
- But don't you see the power
of meme, the power of ideas,
the power of fun or whatever mechanism
is used to captivate a community?
- I do, but there are meme stocks.
It doesn't absolve you of your ethical
and securities liabilities
if you're promoting it.
So like I don't have a problem
with like people buying a stock.
It's just the way I
divide the world is right,
there's investment, there's saving
and there's speculation
and there's trading.
So Bitcoin is an asset for saving.
If you wanna save money
for a hundred years,
you don't really want to
take on execution risk
or the like, so you're just buying
something to hold forever.
For you to actually endorse
something as a property.
Like if you said to me, "Mike,
what should I buy for the
next a hundred years?"
I say, "Well, some amount of real estate,
some amount of scarce collectibles,
some amount of Bitcoin," right?
You can run your company, right?
But running your company as an investment,
so the savings are properties.
If you said, "What should I invest in?"
I'd say, "Well, here's a
list of good companies,
private companies, you could
start your own company."
That's an investment, right?
If you said, "What should I trade?"
Well, I'm trading as
like a proprietary thing.
Like I don't have any
special insight into that.
If you're a good trader, you know you are.
If you said to me, "What
should you speculate in?"
We talk about meme stocks,
right, and meme coins,
and it's kind of sits up there.
It sits right in the same space
with what horse should you bet on
and what sports team should you gamble on?
And should you bet on
black six times in a row
and double down each time?
I mean, it's fun, but
at the end of the day
it's a speculation, right?
You can't build a civilization-
- On speculation.
- On it.
It's not an institutional asset.
And in fact, where I'd leave it, right,
is Bitcoin is clearly digital,
which makes it an institutional
grade investible asset
for a public company, a public figure,
a public investor or
anybody that's risk adverse.
I think that the other,
the top 100 other cryptos
are like venture capital investments.
And if you're a VC
and if you're a qualified
technical investor
and you have a pool of capital
and you can take that kind of risk,
then you can parse through
that and form opinions.
It's just orders of magnitude more risky
because of competition,
because of ambition
and because of regulation.
And if you take the meme coins,
it's like when some rapper
comes out with a meme coin,
it's like maybe it'll peak
when I hear about it, right?
It's like, I mean, Shib
was created as the coin
such that it had so many
zeros after the decimal point
that when you looked
at it on the exchanges,
it always showed 0000.
And it wasn't until like six
months after it got popular
that they started expanding the display,
so you could see whether
the price had changed.
- That's speculation.
Maybe you can correct me,
but you've been critical of Elon Musk
in the past in the crypto space.
Where do you stand on
Elon's effect on Bitcoin
and cryptocurrency in general these days?
- I believe that Bitcoin
is a massive breakthrough
for the human race that
will cure half the problems
in the world and generate
hundreds of trillions of dollars
of economic value to the civilization.
And I believe that it's in an early stage
where many people don't understand it
and they're afraid of it.
And there's FUD and there's
uncertainty, there's doubt
and there's fear and there's
a very noisy crypto world
and there's 15,000 other cryptos
that are seeking relevance.
And I think most of the
FUD is actually fueled
by the other crypto entrepreneurs.
So the environmental FUD and
the other types of uncertainty
that surround Bitcoin,
generally they're not coming
from legitimate environmentalists.
They don't come from legitimate critics.
They actually are guerilla
marketing campaigns
that are being financed and fueled
by other crypto entrepreneurs
because they have an interest in doing so.
So if I look at the
constructive path forward.
First, I think it'd be very constructive
for corporations to embrace Bitcoin
and build applications on top of it.
You don't need to fix it.
There's nothing wrong with it, right?
Like when you put it on a
layer two and a layer three,
it moves a billion times a
second at the speed of light.
So every beautiful, cool DeFi application,
every crypto application,
everything you could imagine
you might wanna do, you can
do with a legitimate company
and a legitimate website
or mobile application
sitting on top of Bitcoin
or Lightning if you want to.
So I think that to the
extent that people do that,
that's gonna be better for the world.
If you consider what holds people back,
I think it's just misperceptions
about what Bitcoin is.
So I'm a big fan of just educating people.
If you're not going to commercialize it,
then just educate people on what it is.
So for example, Bitcoin's
the most efficient
use of energy in the world by far, right?
Most people don't, they don't
necessarily perceive that
or realize that.
But if you were to take any
metric energy intensity,
you put like $2 billion
worth of electricity
in the network every year
and it's worth $850 billion.
There is no industry in
the real world, right,
that is that energy efficient.
Not only that energy efficient,
it's also the most sustainable industry.
We do surveys, 58% of Bitcoin
mining energy is sustainable.
So there's a very good story.
In fact every other industry,
planes, trains, automobiles,
construction, food,
medicine, everything else,
it's less clean, less efficient.
- So the basic debate was-
- I would like to, I wouldn't
say there is a debate,
I would just say that to the extent
that the Bitcoin community
had any issue with Elon,
it was just this environmental uncertainty
that he fueled in a couple
of his tweets, right?
Which I think just is very distracting.
- Well, that was one of them.
But I think it's like
the Bitcoin maximalist,
but generally the crypto community,
what you call the crypto entrepreneurs are
it's also they're using it
for, I mean, for investment,
for speculation, and
therefore get very passionate
about people's kind of celebrities,
including you, like famous people
saying positive stuff about
any one particular crypto,
a thing you can buy in Coinbase.
And so they might be
unhappy with Elon Musk
that he's promoting Bitcoin and then not,
and then promoting Dogecoin, then not.
And this kind of there's so much emotion
tied up in the
communication on this topic.
I think that's where a lot of the-
- Look, I don't have a
criticism of Elon Musk.
He's free to do whatever he wishes to do.
It's his life.
In fact, Elon Musk is the second largest
supporter of Bitcoin in the world.
So I think that the Bitcoin community
tends to eat its own quite a bit.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Like it tends to be very self-critical.
And instead of saying, well,
Elon is more supportive
of Bitcoin than the other
10,000 people in the world,
with serious amounts
of money, they're like,
they focus upon, you know?
- Yeah, this is strange.
Eating your own is just-
- So, I mean, I think he's
free to do what he wants to do.
And I think he's done a
lot of good for Bitcoin
in putting it on the balance
sheet of Tesla and holding it.
And I think that sent a
very powerful message.
- Do you have advice for young people?
So, you've had a heck of a life.
You've done quite a lot
of things before MIT,
but starting with MIT.
Is there advice you have for young people
in high school and college,
how to have a career they can be proud of,
how to have a life they can be proud of?
- I was asked by somebody for quick advice
for his young children, he had twins,
when they enter adulthood.
He said, "Give me your
advice for them in a letter.
I'm gonna give it to them when
they turn 21 or something."
I was at a party and then he handed me
this sheet of paper and I thought,
"Oh, he wants me to
write it down right now."
So I sat down, I started
writing and I figured,
"Well, what would you want
to tell someone at age 21?"
- You wrote it down?
- [Michael] So I wrote it down.
- Awesome.
Then I tweeted it and
it's sitting on Twitter.
But I tell you what I said.
I said my advice if
you're entering adulthood.
Focus your energy, guard your time,
train your mind, train your
body, think for yourself,
curate your friends,
curate your environment,
keep your promises, stay cheerful
and constructive, and upgrade the world.
Like that was the 10.
- Upgrade the world.
That's an interesting choice of words.
Upgrade the world, upgrade the world.
- [Michael] It's like an engineering-
- Focus your energy.
Yeah, it is a very engineering themed.
Keep your promises too.
That's an interesting one.
- I think most people suffer
because they don't focus.
Like you gotta figure out,
I think the big risk in this world
is there's too much of everything.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Like you can sit and watch chess videos
a hundred hours a week and
you'll never get through
all the chess videos, right?
There's too much of every possible thing,
too much of every good thing.
So figuring out what you wanna do
and then everything will
suck up your time, right?
There's a hundred streaming
channels to binge watch on.
So you gotta guard your time
and then train your body,
train your mind, and
control who's around you,
control what surrounds you.
So ultimately in a world
where there's too much
of everything, then your success-
- It's like those laser eyes.
It's like those laser
eyes, you have to focus
on just a few of those things.
- Yeah, I mean, I got a thousand opinions
we could talk about and I
could pursue a thousand things,
but I don't expect to be successful.
And I'm not sure that my
opinion in any of the 999
is any more valid than the
leader of thought in that area,
so how about if I just
focus upon one thing
and then deliver the best
I can in the one thing.
That's the laser eye message.
The rest get you distracted.
- How do you achieve that?
Do you find yourself given
where you are in life
having to say no a lot or
just fo focus comes natural
when you just ignore
everything around you?
So how do you achieve that focus?
- I think it helps if people
know what you're focused on.
(Lex chuckles)
- So everything about you just
radiates that, people know.
People know this is-
- Right, if they know
what you're focused on,
then you won't get so many
other things coming your way.
If you dally or if you flirt
with 27 different things,
then you're gonna get approached by people
in each of the 27 communities, right?
- You mentioned at beginning a PhD
and given your roots at MIT,
do you think there's all kinds of journeys
you can take to educate yourself?
Do you think a PhD or
school is still worth it?
Or is there other paths through life that-
- Is it worth it if you had to pay for it?
Is it worth it if you
to spend the time on it?
- The time and the money is a big cost.
Time probably the bigger one, right?
- It seems clear to me that the world
wants more specialists.
It wants you to be an expert
in and to focus on in one area,
and it's punishing generalist,
jack of all trades,
especially people that are generalists
in the physical realm,
'cause if you're a specialist
in the digital realm, you might very well,
you're the person with
700,000 followers on Twitter
and you show them how to tie knots
or you're the banjo player
with 1.8 million followers,
and when everybody types
banjo, it's you, right?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so the world wants
people that do something well,
and then it wants to stamp
out 18 million copies of them.
And so that argues in favor of focus.
Now, I mean, the definition
of a PhD is someone
with enough of an education
that they're capable of
or have made, I guess to get a PhD,
technically you have to
have done a dissertation
where you made a seminal contribution
to the body of human knowledge, right?
And if you haven't done that,
technically you have a master's degree,
but you're not a doctor.
So if you're interested in any
of the academic disciplines
that a PhD would be granted for,
then I can see that being
a reasonable pursuit.
But there are many people
that are specialists.
You know the Agadmator?
- Yeah, yeah.
- The Agadmator on YouTube.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- He's the world's
greatest chess commentator.
- [Lex] Yeah. (chuckles)
- And I've watched his career
and he is got progressively better.
And he is really good.
- He's gonna love hearing this. (chuckles)
- Yeah, if the Agadmator overhears this,
I'm a big fan of the Agadmator,
unfortunately, I have to
cut myself off, right,
because otherwise you'll watch
the entire Paul Morphy
saga for your weekend.
But the point really is
YouTube is full of experts
who are specialists in something,
and they rise to the
top of their profession.
And Twitter is too, and the internet is.
So I would advocate that you figure out
what you're passionate about
and what you're good at,
and you do focus on it,
especially if the thing
that you're doing can be automated.
The problem is back to that
500,000 algebra teacher type comment.
The problem is if it is
possible to be automated,
then over time someone's
probably gonna automate it
and that squeezes the state
space of everybody else.
It's like after the
lockdowns, it used to be there
are like all these local
bands that played in bars,
and everybody went to the
bar to see the local band.
And then during the lockdown
you would have like these six super groups
and they would all get
500,000 or a million followers
and all these smaller local bands
just got no attention at all.
- Well, the interesting thing is,
one of those 500,000 algebra teachers
is likely to be part of the automation,
so it's like it's an
opportunity for you to think,
where's my field, my
discipline evolving into.
I talked to a bunch of librarians,
just happen to be friends with librarians
and libraries will probably be evolving.
And it's up to you as
a librarian to be one
of the few that remain in the rubble.
- If you're gonna give
commentary on Shakespeare plays,
I want you to basically do it
for every Shakespeare play.
Like, I want you to be
the Shakespeare dude.
Just like Lex, you're like-
- I don't know what kind of. (chuckles)
- You are the deep
thinking podcaster, right?
Or you're the podcaster that goes
after the deep intellectual conversations.
And once I get comfortable
with you and I like you,
then I start binge watching Lex.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But if you changed your format
through 16 different formats,
so that you could compete
with 16 different other
personalities on YouTube,
you'd probably wouldn't
beat any of 'em, right?
You would probably just
kind of sink into the,
you're the number two or number three guy.
You're not the number
one guy in the format.
And I think the algorithm, right?
The Twitter algorithm and
the YouTube algorithms,
they really reward the person
that's focused on message, consistent.
The world wants somebody they can trust
that's consistent and reliable
and they kind of want to know
what they're getting into
because and this is
taken for granted maybe,
but there's 10 million people
vying for every hour of your time,
and so the fact that anybody
gives you any time at all
is a huge privilege, right?
- [Lex] Is amazing.
- And you should be thanking them.
And you should respect their time.
- It's interesting,
like everything you said
is very interesting.
But of course, from my perspective
and probably from your perspective,
my actual life has nothing to do with,
it's just being focused on stuff.
And in my case, it's like focused
on doing the thing I really
enjoy doing and being myself
and not caring about anything else.
Like I don't care about
views or likes or attention.
And that just maintaining that focus
is the way from an individual perspective,
you live that life.
But yeah, it does seem
that there's the world
and technology is rewarding
the specialization
and creating bigger and bigger platforms
for the different specializations.
Yeah, and then that
lifts all boats actually,
'cause the specializations
get better and better
and better at teaching
people to do specific things
and they educate themselves and
it just, everybody gets more
and more knowledgeable and
more and more empowered.
- The reward for authenticity
more than offsets
the specificity with which
you pursue your mission.
- [Lex] That's true, yeah.
- Another way to say it is like,
nobody wants to read advertising.
Like if you were to spend
a hundred million dollars
advertising your thing,
I probably wouldn't wanna watch it.
- Yeah, that's so fascinating.
Yeah, so fascinating.
- [Michael] We see the death of that.
- Yeah.
- And so the commercial shows
are losing their audiences
and the authentic specialists
or the authentic artists
are gaining their audience.
- And that's a beautiful thing.
Speaking of deep thinking,
you're just a human,
your life ends, you've
accumulated so much wisdom,
so much money, but the ride ends.
Do you think about that?
Do you ponder your death, your mortality?
Are you afraid of it?
- When I go all my assets
will flow into a foundation,
and the foundation's mission
is to make education free
for everybody forever.
And if I'm able to
contribute to the creation
of a more perfect monetary system,
then maybe that foundation
will go on forever, right?
- (chuckles) The idea, the
foundation of the idea,
so not just the, it's
each of the foundations.
- It's not clear we're on the
S-curve of a mortal life yet.
Like that's a biological question.
And you asked that on some of
your other interviews a lot.
I think that we are on the
threshold of immortal life
for ideas or immortal life
for certain institutions
or computer programs.
So if we can fix the money,
then you can create a
technically perfected endowment.
And then the question really
is what are your ideas?
What do you want to leave behind?
And so if it's a park, then
you endow the park, right?
If it's free education, you endow that.
If it's some other ethical idea, right?
- Does it make you sad
that there's something
that you've endowed
some very powerful idea
of digital energy that you
help put into the world,
and then your mind, your conscious mind
will no longer be there to experience it.
It's just gone forever.
- I'd rather think that the
thing that Satoshi taught us
is you should do your part
during some phase of the journey,
and then you should get out of the way.
- [Lex] (chuckles) Yeah.
- I think Steve Jobs
said something similar
to that effect in a very,
very famous speech one day,
which is, "Death is a natural part of life
and it makes way for the next generation."
And I think the goal is you
upgrade the world, right?
You leave it a better place,
but you get out of the way.
And I think when that breaks
down, bad things happen.
I think nature cleanses itself.
There's a cycle of life.
- And speaking one of great people
who did also get outta the
way is George Washington.
So hopefully when you get outta the way
and nobody's bleeding you to
death in hope of helping you.
To do a bit of a callback.
What do you think is the
meaning of this whole thing?
What's the meaning of life?
Why are we here?
We talked about the rise
of human civilization.
It seems like we're engineers at heart.
We build cool stuff, better
and better use of energy,
channeling energy to be productive.
Why?
What's it all for?
- (chuckles) You're
getting metaphysical on me.
- Very, there's a beautiful
boat to the left of us.
Like why do we do that?
This boat that sailed the ocean,
then we build models of it
to celebrate great
engineering of the past.
- To engineer is divine.
You can make lots of
arguments as why we're here.
We're either here to entertain ourself
or we're here to create
something that's beautiful
or something that's functional.
I think if you're an engineer,
you entertain yourself
by creating something that's
both beautiful and functional.
So I think all three of those things,
it's entertaining, but it's ethical.
You gotta admire the first
person that built a bridge,
crossing a chasm or the first
person to work out the problem
of how to get running water to a village
or the first person to figure out
how to dam up a river
or mastered agriculture
or the guy that figured out
how to grow fruit on trees
or created orchards, and maybe one day
he had like 10 fruit trees.
He is pretty proud of himself.
- So, that's functional.
There is also something to that,
just like you said, that's just beautiful.
It does get you closer to,
like you said, the divine something.
When you step back and
look at the entirety of it,
a collective of humans
using a beautiful invention
or creation or just something
about this instrument
is creating a beautiful piece of music.
That seems just right.
That's what we're here for.
Whatever the divine is, it
seems like we're here for that.
And I of course love talking to you
because from the engineering perspective,
the functional is ultimately
the mechanism towards the beauty.
- Isn't there something beautiful about
making the world a better
place for people that you love?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Your friends, your family, or yourself.
- [Lex] Yeah, yeah.
- And when you think about the
entire arc of human existence
and you roll the clock back 500,000 years
and you think about every struggle
of everyone that came before us
and everything they had to overcome
in order to put you here
right now, you know,
you kind of, you gotta admire that, right?
You gotta respect that.
- That's a heck of a gift they gave us.
It's also a heck of a responsibility.
Don't screw it up. (chuckles)
- If I dropped you 500,000 years ago
and I said, figure out steel refining,
or figure out silicon
chips, fab production
or whatever it is or fire?
- Why?
- And so now we're here and I
guess the way you repay them
is you fix everything in front
of your face you can, right?
And that means to someone like Elon,
it means get us off the planet, right?
To someone like me, it's like,
I think fix the energy and the system.
- And that gives me hope.
Michael, this was an
incredible conversation.
You're an incredible human.
It's a huge honor you
would sit down with me.
Thank you so much for talking today.
- Yeah, thanks for having me, Lex.
- Thanks for listening
to this conversation
with Michael Saylor.
To support this podcast,
please check out our
sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you
with a few words from Francis Bacon.
"Money is a great servant,
but a bad master."
Thank you for listening and
hope to see you next time.