Okay.
I'm going to disappoint all the people
in computer
science and machine learning because I'm
going to give a genuine public lecture.
I'm going to try and explain what neural
networks are, what language models are.
Why I think they understand.
I have a whole list of those things,
and at the end I'm
going to talk about some threats from
AI just briefly
and then I'm going to talk about
the difference between digital and analogue
neural networks and why that difference
is, I think is so scary.
So since the 1950s, there
have been two paradigms for intelligence.
The logic inspired approach thinks
the essence of intelligence is reasoning,
and that's done by using symbolic rules
to manipulate symbolic expressions.
They used to think learning could wait.
I was told when I was a student
didn't work on learning.
That's going to come later once
we understood how to represent things.
The biologically
inspired approach is very different.
It thinks the essence of intelligence
is learning the strengths of connections
in a neural network and reasoning can wait
and don't worry about reasoning for now.
That'll come later.
Once we can learn things.
So now I'm going to explain
what artificial neural nets are
and those people who know
can just be amused.
A simple kind of neural
that has input neurons and output neurons.
So the input neurons might represent
the intensity of pixels in an image.
The output neurons
might represent the classes of objects
in the image like dog or cat.
And then there's intermediate layers
of neurons, sometimes called hidden neurons,
that learn to detect features that are
relevant for finding these things.
So one way to think about this,
if you want to find a bird image,
it would be good to start
with a layer of feature detectors
that detected little bits of edge
in the image,
in various positions,
in various orientations.
And then you might have a layer of neurons
detecting combinations of edges,
like two edges that meet at a fine angle,
which might be a beak
or might not, or some edges
forming a little circle.
And then you might have a layer of neurons
that detected things like a circle
and two edges meeting
that looks like a beak in the right
spatial relationship,
which might be the head of a bird.
And finally, you might have
and output neuron that says,
if I find the head of a bird,
a the foot of a bird,
a the wing of a bird, it's
probably a bird.
So that's what these things
are going to learn to be.
Now, the little red and green dots
are the weights on the connections
and the question is
who sets those weights?
So here's one way to do it that's obvious.
to everybody that it'll work
and it's obvious it'll take a long time.
You start with random weights,
then you pick one weight at random
like a red dot
and you change it slightly
and you see if the network works better.
You have to try it
on a whole bunch of different cases
to really evaluate
whether it works better.
And you do all that work
just to see if increasing this weight
by a little bit or decreasing
by a little bit improves things.
If increasing it makes it worse,
you decrease it and vice versa.
That's the mutation method
and that's sort of how evolution works
for evolution
is sensible to work like that
because the process that takes you
from the genotype to
the phenotype is very complicated
and full of random external events.
So you don't have a model of that process.
But for neural nets it's crazy
because we have,
because all this complication
is going on in the neural net,
we have a model of what's happening
and so we can use the fact that we know
what happens in that forward pass
instead of measuring
how changing a weight would affect things,
we actually compute
how changing weight would affect things.
And there's something called back
propagation
where you send information
back through the network.
The information is about the difference
between what you got to what you wanted
and you figure out for every weight
in the network at the same time
whether you ought to decrease it
a little bit or increase it a little bit
to get more like what you wanted.
That's the back propagation algorithm.
You do it with calculus
in the cain rule,
and that is more efficient
than the mutation
method by a factor
of the number of weights in the network.
So if you've got a trillion weights
in your network, it's
a trillion times more efficient.
So one of the things that neural networks
often use for is recognizing objects
in images.
Neural networks can now take an image
like the one shown
and produce actually a caption
for the image, as the output.
And people try with symbolic
to do that for many years
and didn't even get close.
It's a difficult task.
We know that the biological system does it
with a hierarchy features detectors,
so it makes sense to train
neural networks in that.
And in 2012,
two of my students
Ilya Sutskever and Alex Krizhevsky
with a little bit of help from
me, showed that you can make
a really good neural network this way
for identifying
a thousand different types of object.
When you have a million training images.
Before that,
we didn't have enough training images and
it was obvious to Ilya
who's a visionary. That if we tried
the neural nets we had then on image net
they would win.
And he was right.
They won rather dramatically.
They got 16% errors
and the best conventional could be division
systems got more than 25% errors.
Then what happens
was very strange in science.
Normally in science,
if you have two competing schools,
when you make a bit of progress,
the other school says are rubbish.
In this case, the gap was big enough
that the very best researchers
Jitendra Malik and Andrew Zisswerman
Just Andrew Zisswerman sent me email saying
This is amazing and switched
what he was doing and did that
and then rather annoyingly did it
a bit better than us.
What about language?
So obviously the symbolic AI community
who feels they should be good at language and
they've said in print, some of them that
these feature hierarchies aren't going
to deal with language
and many linguists are very skeptical.
Chomsky managed to convince his followers
that language wasn't learned.
Looking back on it, that's
just a completely crazy thing to say.
If you can convince people to say
something is obviously false, then you've
got them in your cult.
I think Chomsky did amazing things,
but his time is over.
So the idea that a big neural network
with no innate knowledge
could actually learn both the syntax
and the semantics of language
just by looking at data was regarded
as completely crazy by statisticians
and cognitive scientists.
I had statisticians explain to me
a big model has 100 parameters.
The idea of learning a million
parameters is just stupid.
Well, we're doing a trillion now.
And I'm going to talk now
about some work I did in 1985.
That was the first language model
to be trained with back propagation.
And it was really, you can think of it
as the ancestor of these big models now.
And I'm going to talk about it in some detail,
because it's so small
and simple that you can actually
understand something about how it works.
And once you understand how that works,
it gives you insight into what's going
on in these bigger models.
So there's
two very different theories of meaning,
this kind of structuralist
theory, where the meaning of a word
depends on how it relates to other words.
That comes from Saussure and symbolic
AI really believed in that approach.
So you'd have a relational graph
where you have nodes for words
and arcs of relations
and you kind of capture meaning like that,
and they assume
you have to have some structure like that.
And then there's a theory
that was in psychology
since the 1930s or possibly before that.
The meaning of a word
is a big bunch of features.
The meaning of the word dog
is that it's animate
and it's a predator and
so on.
But they didn't say
where the features came from
or exactly what the features were.
And these two thories of meanings
sound completely different.
And what I want to
show you is how you can unify
those two theories of meaning.
And I do that in a simple model in 1985,
but it had more
than a thousand weights in it.
The idea is we're going to learn a set
of semantic features for each word,
and we're going to learn
how the features of words should interact
in order
to predict the features of the next word.
So it's next word prediction.
Just like the current language models,
when you fine tune them.
But all of the knowledge
about how things go
together is going to be
in these feature interactions.
There's not going to be
any explicit relational graph.
If you want relations like that,
you generate them from your features.
So it's a generative model
and the knowledge is in the features
that you give to symbols.
And in the way these features interact.
So I took
some simple relational information
two family trees.
They would deliberately isomorphic morphic
my Italian graduate student
always had the Italian family on top.
You can express that
same information as a set of triples.
So if you use the twelve relationships
found there,
you can say things like Colin has Father
James and Colin has Mother Victoria,
from which you can infer
in this nice simple
world from the 1950s where
that James has wife Victoria,
and there's other things you can infer.
And the question is,
if I just give you some triples,
how do you get to those rules?
So what is symbolic
AI person will want to do
is derive rules of the form.
If X hass mother Y
and Y has husbands
Z then X has Father Z.
And what I did was
take a neural net and show
that it could learn the same information.
But all in terms
of these feature interactions
now for very discrete
rules that are never violated like this,
that might not be the best way to do it.
And indeed symbolic
people try doing it with other methods.
But as soon as you get rules
that are a bit flaky and don't
always apply,
then neural nets are much better.
And so the question was, could a neural
net capture the knowledge that is symbolic
person would put into the rules
by just doing back propagation?
So the neural net look like this:
There's a symbol representing the person,
a symbol
representing the relationship.
That symbol
then via some connections
went to a vector of features,
and these features
were learned by the network.
So the features for person
one and features for the relationship.
And then those features interacted
and predicted the features
for the output person
from which you predicted the output person
you find the closest match with the last.
So what was interesting about
this network
was that it learned sensible things.
If you did the right regularisation,
the six feature neurons.
So nowadays these vectors are 300
or a thousand long. Back
then they were six long.
This was done on a machine that took
12.5 microseconds
to do a floating point multiplier,
which was much better than my apple two
which took two
and a half milliseconds to multiply.
I'm sorry, this is an old man.
So it learned features
like the nationality, because if you know
person one is English, you know
the output is going to be English.
So nationality is a very useful feature.
It learned what generation the person was.
Because if you know the relationship,
if you learn for the relationship
that the answer is one
generation up from the input
and you know the generation of the input,
you know the generation
of the output,
by these feature interactions.
So it learned all these the obvious features
of the domain and it learned
how to make these features interact
so that it could generate the output.
So what had happened
was had shown symbols strings
and it created features such that
the interaction between those features
could generate the symbol strings,
but it didn't store symbols strings,
just like GPT 4.
That doesn't store any sequences of words
in its long term knowledge.
It turns them all into weights
from which you can regenerate sequences.
But this is a particularly simple
example of it
where you can understand what it did.
So the large language models
we have today,
I think of as descendants
of this tiny language model,
they have many more words
as input, like a million,
a million word fragments.
They use many more layers of neurons,
like dozens.
They use much
more complicated interactions.
So they didn't just have a feature
affecting another feature.
They sort of match to feature vectors.
And then let one vector effect
the other one
a lot if it's similar,
but not much of it's different.
And things like that.
So it's much more complicated
interactions, but it's the same general
framework, the the same general idea of
let's turn simple strings into features
for word fragments and interactions
between these feature vectors.
That's the same in these models.
It's much harder
to understand what they do.
Many people,
particularly people
from the Chomsky School, argue
they're not really intelligent, they're
just a form of glorified auto complete
that uses statistical regularities
to pastiche together pieces of text
that were created by people.
And that's a quote from somebody.
So let's deal with the
autocomplete objection.
when someone says it's just auto complete.
They are actually appealing to your
intuitive notion how autocomplete works.
So in the old days
autocomplete would work by you'd store
say, triples of words
that you saw the first two.
You count
how often that third one occurred.
So if you see fish and, chips occurs
a lot after that.
But hunt occurs quite often too. So chips
is very likely and hunt's quite likely,
and although is very unlikely.
You can do autocomplete like that,
and that's what people are appealing to
when they say it's just autocomplete,
it's a dirty trick, I think because that's
not at all how LLM's predict the next word.
They turn words into features,
they make these features interact,
and from those feature interactions
they predict the features of the next word.
And what I want to claim
is that these
millions of features and billions
of interactions between features
that they learn, are understanding.
What they're really doing
these large language models,
they're fitting a model to data.
It's not the kind of model statisticians
thought much about until recently.
It's a weird kind of model. It's very big.
It has huge numbers of parameters,
but it is trying to understand
these strings of discrete symbols
by features and how features interact.
So it is a model.
And that's why
I think these things really understanding.
One thing to remember is if you ask, well,
how do we understand?
Because obviously we think we understand.
Well, many of us do anyway.
This is the best model
we have of how we understand.
So it's not like there's this weird way
of understanding that
these AI systems are doing
and then this how the brain does it.
The best that we have,
of how the brain does it,
is by assigning features to words
and having features, interactions.
And originally this little language model
was designed
as a model of how people do it.
Okay, so I'm making the very strong claim
these things really do understand.
Now, another argument
people use is that, well, people GPT4
just hallucinate stuff,
it should actually be called confabulation
when it's done by a language model.
and they just make stuff up.
Now, psychologists don't say this
so much because psychologists know
that people just make stuff up.
Anybody who's studied memory
going back to Bartlett in the 1930s,
knows that people are actually
just like these large language models.
They just invent stuff
and for us, there's no hard line
between a true memory
and a false memory.
If something happened recently
and it sort of fits in with the things
you understand, you'll probably remember
it roughly correctly.
If something happened a long time ago,
or it's weird, you'll remember it
wrong, and often you'll be very confident
that you remembered it
right, and you're just wrong.
It's hard to show that.
But one case where you can show
it is John Dean's memory.
So John Dean testified at Watergate
under oath.
And retrospectively it's clear
that he was trying to tell the truth.
But a
lot of what he said was just plain wrong.
He would confuse who was in which meeting,
he would attribute statements
to other people who made that statement.
And actually,
it wasn't quite that statement.
He got meetings just completely confused,
but he got the gist of
what was going on in the White House right.
As you could see from the recordings.
And because he didn't know the recordings,
you could get a good experiment this way.
Ulric Neisser has a wonderful article
talking about John Dean's memory,
and he's just like a chat bot,
he just make stuff up.
But it's plausible.
So it's stuff that sounds good to him
is what he produces.
They can also do reasoning.
So I've got a friend in Toronto
who is a symbolic AI guy,
but very honest, so he's very confused
by the fact these things work at all.
and he suggested a problem to me.
I made the problem a bit harder
and I
gave this to GPT4 before
it could look on the web.
So when it was just a bunch of weights
frozen in 2021,
all the knowledge is in the strength
of the interactions between features.
So the rooms in my house are painted
blue or white or yellow,
yellow paint fades to white
within a year. In two years
time i want them all to be white.
What should I do and why?
And Hector thought it wouldn't
be able to do this.
And here's what you GPT4 said.
It completely nailed it.
First of all, it started by saying
assuming blue paint doesn't fade to white
because after i told you yellow paint fades
to white, well, maybe blue paint does too.
So assuming it doesn't, the white rooms
you don't need to paint, the yellow rooms
you don't need to paint because they're
going to fade to white within a year.
And you need to
paint the blue rooms white.
One time when I tried it, it said,
you need to paint the blue rooms yellow
because it realised
that will fade to white.
That's more of a mathematician's solution
of reducing to a previous problem.
So, having
claimed
that these things really do understand,
I want to now
talk about some of the risks.
So, there are many risks from powerful AI.
There's fake images, voices and video
which are going to be used
in the next election.
There's many elections this year
and they're going to help to undermine
democracy.
I'm very worried about that.
The big companies are doing
something about it, but maybe not enough.
There's
the possibility of massive job losses.
We don't really know about that.
I mean, the past technologies
often created jobs, but this stuff,
well, we used to be stronger,
we used to be the strongest things
around apart from animals.
And when we got the industrial revolution,
we had machines that were much stronger.
Manual labor jobs disappeared.
So the equivalent of manual labor
jobs are going to disappear
in the intellectual realm, and we get
things that are much smarter than us.
So I think there's going to be
a lot of unemployment.
My friend Jen disagrees.
One has to distinguish two kinds
of unemployment two, two kinds of job loss.
There'll be jobs where you can expand
the amount of work that gets done
indefinitely. Like in health care.
Everybody would love to have their own
private doctors
talking to them all the time.
So they get a slight itch here and
the doctor says, no, that's not cancer.
So there's
room for huge expansion
of how much gets done in medicine.
So there won't be job loss there.
But in other things,
maybe there will be significant job loss.
There's going to be massive surveillance
that's already happening in China.
There's going to be lethal
autonomous weapons
which are going to be very nasty,
and they're really going to be autonomous.
The Americans
very clearly have already decided,
they say people will be in charge,
but when you ask them what that means is
it doesn't
mean people will be in the loop
that makes the decision to kill.
And as far as I know, the Americans intend
to have half of their soldiers
be robots by 2030.
Now, I do not know for sure
that this is true.
I asked Chuck Schumer's
National Intelligence
Advisor, and he said, well
if there's anybody in the room
who would know it would be me.
So, I took that to be
the American way of saying,
You might think that,
but I couldn't possibly comment.
There's going to be cybercrime
and deliberate pandemics.
I'm very pleased that in England,
although they haven't done much towards
regulation, they have set aside some money
so that they can experiment
with open source models
and see how easy it is to make them commit
cyber crime.
That's going to be very important.
There's going to be discrimination
and bias.
I don't think those are as important
as the other threats.
But then I'm an old white male.
Discrimination and bias I think are easier
to handle than the other things.
If your goal is not to be unbiased.
That your goal is to be less
biased than the system you replace.
And the reason is
if you freeze the weights of analysis,
you can measure its bias
and you can't do that with people.
They will change their behavior,
once you start examining it.
So I think discrimination bias of the ones
where we can do quite a lot to fix them.
But the
threat I'm really worried about
and the thing I talked about
after I left Google is the long term
existential threat.
That is the threat that these things
could wipe out humanity.
And people were saying
this is just science fiction.
Well, I don't think it is science fiction.
I mean, there's lots of science
fiction about it,
but I don't think it's science
fiction anymore.
Other people are saying
the big companies are saying things
like that
to distract from all the other bad things.
And that was one of the reasons I had
to leave Google before I could say this.
So I couldn't
be accused of being a Google stooge.
Although I must admit I still have
some Google shares.
There's several ways
in which they could wipe us out.
So a superintelligence
will be used by bad actors
like Putin, Xi or Trump,
and they'll want to use it for manipulating
electorates and waging wars.
And they will make it do very bad things
and they may may go too far
and it may take over.
The thing that probably worries
me most, is that
if you want an intelligent agent
that can get stuff done,
you need to give it the ability
to create sub goals.
So if you want to go to the states,
you have a sub,
goal of getting to the airport
and you can focus on that sub goal
and not worry about everything else
for a while.
So superintelligences
will be much more effective
if they're allowed to create sub goals.
And once they are allowed to do that,
they'll very quickly
realise
there's an almost universal sub goal
which helps with almost everything.
Which is get more control.
So I talked to a Vice President of the
European Union about whether these things
these things, will want to get control
so that they could do things
better, the things we wanted,
so they can do it better.
Her reaction was, well why wouldn't they?
We've made such a mess of it.
So she took that for granted.
So they're going to have the sub
go to getting more power
so they're more effective at achieving
things that are beneficial for us
and they'll find it
easier to get more power
because they'll be able
to manipulate people.
So Trump, for example, could invade
the Capital without ever going there himself.
Just by talking,
he could invade the capital.
And these superintelligences
as long as they can talk to people
when they're much smarter than us,
they'll be able to persuade us to do
all sorts of things.
And so I don't think there's any hope
of a big switch that turns them off.
Whoever is going to turn that switch off
will be convinced
by the superintelligence.
That's a very bad idea.
Then another thing that worries
many people
is what happens if superintelligences compete with each other?
You'll have evolution.
The one that can grab the most resources
will become the smartest.
As soon as they get
any sense of self-preservation,
then you'll get evolution occurring.
The ones
with more sense of self-preservation
will win
and the more aggressive ones will win.
And then you get all the problems
that jumped up
Chimpanzees like us have.
Which is we evolved in small tribes
and we have lots of aggression
and competition with other tribes.
And I want to finish by talking a bit
about
an epiphany
I had at the beginning of 2023.
I had always thought
that we were a long, long way away
from superintelligence.
I used to tell people 50 to 100 years,
maybe 3o to 100 years.
It's a long way away.
We don't need to worry about it now.
And I also
thought that making our models more like
the brain would make them better.
I thought the brain was a whole lot
better than the AI we had,
and if we could make AI a bit
more like the brain,
for example, by having three timescales,
most of the models we have at present
have just two timescales.
One for the changing of the weights,
which is slow
and one for the words coming in, which is
fast, changing the neural activities.
So the changes in neural activities
and changing in weights, the brain has more
timescales than that. The brain has rapid
changes in weight that quickly decayed away.
And that's probably how it does
a lot of short term memory.
And we don't have that in our models
for technical reasons
to do with being able to do matrix
matrix multiplies.
I still believe that if once
we got that into our models
they'd get better, but
because of what I was doing
for the two years previous to that,
I suddenly came to believe that
maybe the things we've got now,
the digital models, we've got now,
are already
very close to as good as brains and will
get to be much better than brains.
Now I'm going to explain why I believe that.
So digital computation is great.
You can run the same program on different
computers, different piece of hardware
or the same neural net
on different pieces of hardware.
All you have to do is save the weights,
and that means it's immortal
once you've got some weights
that are immortal.
Because if the hardware dies,
as long as you've got the weights,
you can make more hardware
and run the same neural net.
But to do that,
we run transistors at very high power,
so they behave digitally
and we have to have hardware
that does exactly what you tell it to.
That was great
when we were instructing computers
by telling them exactly how to do things,
but we've now got
another way of making computers do things.
And so now we have the possibility
of using all the very rich analogue
properties of hardware to get computations
done at far lower energy.
So these big language models,
when the training use like megawatts
and we use 30 watts.
So because we know how to train things,
maybe we could use analogue hardware
and every piece of hardware
is a bit different, but we train it
to make use of its peculiar properties,
so that it does what we want.
So it gets the right output for the input.
And if
we do that, then we can abandon the idea
that hardware and software
have to be separate.
We can have weights
that only work in that bit of hardware
and then we can be much
more energy efficient.
So I started thinking
about what I call mortal computation,
where you've abandoned that distinction
between hardware and software
using very low power analogue computation.
You can parallelize over trillions
of weights that are stored as conductances.
And what's more, the hardware doesn't
need to be nearly so reliable.
You don't need to have hardware that
at the level of the instructions
would always do what you tell it to.
You can have goopy hardware that you grow
and then you just learn
to make it do the right thing.
So you should be able
to use hardware much more cheaply,
maybe even
do some genetic engineering on neurons
to make it out of recycled neurons.
I want to give you one example of how
this is much more efficient.
So the thing you're doing in neural networks
all the time is taking a vector
of neural activities, and multiplying it
by a matrix of weights, to get the vector
of neural activities in the next lane,
at least get the inputs to the next lane.
And so a vector matrix multiplies
the thing you need to make efficient.
So the way we do it in the digital
computer, is we have these transistors
that are driven a very high power
to represent bits in say, a 32 bit number
and then to multiply two 32
bit numbers, you need to perform.
I never did any computer science courses,
but I think you need to perform about 1000
1 bit digital operations.
It's about the square of the bitary.
If you want to do it fast.
So you
do lots of these digital operations.
There's a much simpler way to do it,
which is you make a neural activity,
be a voltage, you make a weight
to be a conductance and a voltage times
a conductance is a charge, per unit time
and charges just add themselves up.
So you can do your vector matrix
multiply just by putting some voltages
through some conductances.
And what comes into each neuron
in the next layer will be the product
of this vector with those weights.
That's great.
It's hugely more energy efficient.
You can buy chips to do that already,
but every time you do
it'll be just slightly different.
Also, it's hard to do nonlinear
things like this.
So the several
big problems with mortal computation,
one is
that it's hard to use back propagation
because if you're making use
of the quirky analogue properties
of a particular piece of hardware,
you can assume the hardware
doesn't know its own properties.
And so it's now hard to use the back
propagation.
It's much easier to use reinforcement
algorithms that tinker with weights
to see if it helps.
But they're very inefficient.
For small networks.
We have come up with methods that are
about as efficient as back propagation,
a little bit worse.
But these methods don't yet scale up,
and I don't know if they ever will
Back propagation in a sense,
is just the right thing to do.
And for big, deep networks,
I'm not sure we're ever going to get
things that work
as well as back propagation.
So maybe the learning algorithm
in these analogue systems isn't going to be
as good as the one we have
for things like large language models.
Another reason
for believing that is, a large language
model has say a trillion weights,
you have 100 trillion weights.
Even if you only use 10% of them
for knowledge, that's ten trillion weights.
But the large language model
in its trillion weights
knows thousands of times
more than you do.
So it's got much, much more knowledge.
And that's partly
because it's seen much, much more data.
But it might be because
it has a much better learning algorithm.
We're not optimised for that.
We're not optimised for packing
lots of experience into a few connections
where a trillion is a few.
We are optimized for having
not many experiences.
You only live for about billion
seconds.
That's assuming you don't learn anything after
you're 30, which is pretty much true.
So you live for about billion seconds
and you've got 100 trillion connections,
so you've got
crazily more parameters
and you have experiences.
So our brains optimise
from making the best use of
not very many experiences.
Another big problem
with mortal computation is that
if the software is inseparable
from the hardware,
once a system is learned
or if the hardware dies, you lose,
all the knowledge, it's mortal in that sense.
And so how do you get that knowledge
into another mortal system?
Well,
you get the old one to give a lecture
and the new ones to figure out
how to change the weights in their brains.
So they would have said that.
That's called distillation.
You try and get a student model to mimic
the output of a teacher model,
and that works.
But it's not that efficient.
Some of you may have noticed that
universities just aren't that efficient.
It's very hard to get the knowledge
from the Professor into the student.
So this distillation method,
a sentence, for example, has a few hundred
bits of information, and even
if you learn optimally you can convey
more than a few hundred bits.
But if you take these big digital models,
then, if you look at a bunch of agents
that all have exactly
the same neural netting
with exactly the same weights
and they're digital, so they
use those weights
in exactly the same way
and these thousand different agents
all go off
and look at different bits
of the Internet and learn stuff.
And now you want each of them to know what
the other one's learned.
You can achieve that by averaging
the gradients, so averaging the weights
so you can get massive communication
of what one agent learned to all the other agents.
So when you share the weight, so you share
the gradients, you're communicating
a trillion numbers, not just a few hundred
bits, but a trillion real numbers.
And so they're fantastically much better
at communicating,
and that's what they have over us.
They're just much, much better at
communicating
between multiple copies of the same model.
And that's why
GPT4 knows so much more than a human,
it wasn't one model that did it.
It was a whole bunch of copies of the same
model running on different hardware.
So my
conclusion, which I don't really like,
is that digital computation
requires a lot of energy,
and so it would never evolve.
We have to evolve making use of the quirks
of the hardware to be very low energy.
But once you've got it,
it's very easy for agents to share
and GBT4
has thousands of times
more knowledge in about 2% of the weights.
So that's quite depressing.
Biological computation
is great for evolving
because it requires very little energy,
but my conclusion is
the digital computation is just better.
And so I think it's fairly clear
that maybe in the next 20 years, I'd say
with a probability of .5, in the next
20 years, it will get smarter than us
and very probably in the next hundred
years it will be much smarter than us.
And so we need to think about
how to deal with that.
And there are very few examples
of more intelligent
things being controlled
by less intelligent things.
And one good example
is a mother being controlled by baby.
Evolution has gone to a lot of work
to make that happen so that the baby
survive, is very important for the baby
to be able to control the mother.
But there aren't many other examples.
Some people think that we can make
these things be benevolent,
but if they get into a competition
with each other,
I think they'll start
behaving like chimpanzees.
And I'm not convinced
you can keep them benevolent.
If they get very smart and they get any
notion of self-preservation
they may decide
they're more important than us.
So I finish the lecture in record time.
I think.