[Music]
Mark we just tried Orion together yeah
we're fresh off of it it feels like true
AR glasses are finally getting closer
Orion is a product that you all have
been working on for five plus years yeah
almost 10 almost 10 yeah so take me back
to the beginning when you started the
project when it started in research like
what were you thinking about what was
the goal for it well I I think a lot of
it goes all the way back to
our relationship with mobile platforms
and all that right so it's um you know
we have lived through one major platform
transition already because we started on
web right not not on mobile and mobile
phones and smartphones kind of got
started around the same time as Facebook
and and kind of early social media was
getting started so didn't really get to
play any role in that platform
transition but going through it right we
weren't born on mobile we kind of
had this awareness that okay web was a
thing mobile is a thing it is different
um there are strengths and weaknesses of
it there's this Continuum of computing
where now you have a a mobile device
that you can take with you all the time
and that's amazing MH but it's small
kind of pulls you away from other
interactions those things are not great
but there was sort of this recognition
that just like there's the transition
from computers to mobile um mobile is
not going to be the end of the line so
as soon as we started
becoming like a more I I guess I'd say
Stable Company like once we found our
footing on mobile and and we weren't
like clearly going to go out of business
or something like that I was like okay
let's start um
planting our our some seeds for what we
think could be the future right it's
like mobile is already kind of getting
defined um you know by 2012 2014 is it
was generally too late to to Really
shape that platform in a meaningful way
I we we had some experiments I didn't
succeed or go anywhere so pretty quickly
I was like okay we should focus on the
future because just like there's the
shift from from from desktop to Mobile
new things are going to be possible in
the future so what is that um I think
the kind of simplest version of it is
basically what you started seeing with
Orion right it's it's like the vision is
a normal pair of
glasses that can do two really
fundamental things one is
put Holograms in the world to deliver
this realistic sense of presence like
you there with another person or in
another place or maybe you're physically
with a person but just like we did you
can pull up a virtual pong game or you
know whatever um you can work on things
together you can sit at a coffee shop
pull up your whole uh workstation of
different monitors you know you can be
on a flight or in the backseat of a car
and pull up a full screen movie theater
and and like okay all these things like
great Computing full sense of presence
like you're there with people no matter
where they are thing
two is it's the ideal device for AI and
the reason for that is because glasses
are sort of uniquely positioned for you
to be able to let them see what you see
and hear what you hear and give you very
subtle feedback back to you where they
can speak in your ear or um or they can
have silent input that that kind of
shows up on the on the glasses that that
other people can't see and doesn't take
you away from the world around you and I
think that that is all going to be
really profound now when we got started
with this I had thought that kind of the
Hologram part of this was going to be
possible before AI um so it's sort of an
interesting Twist of faith that the AI
part is actually possible before um
before the Holograms are really able to
be mass-produced at a at kind of an
affordable price but um but that was
sort of the vision I think that it's
pretty easy to wrap your head around and
there's already you know billion to two
billion people who wear glasses on a
daily basis just like you know everyone
who didn't have smartphones were kind of
the first people to upgrade two
smartphones I think everyone who has
glasses is pretty quickly going to
upgrade to smart glasses over the next
decade and then I think it's going to
start being really valuable and you know
a lot of other people who aren't wearing
glasses today are going to end up
wearing them too um that's kind of the
simple
version and then I think as we've
developed this out there are all these
sort of more Nu directions that have
emerged too so we've started you know
while while that was kind of the full
version of what we wanted to build there
are all these things that we said okay
well well maybe it's it's really hard to
build normal looking glasses that can do
Holograms um at an affordable price
point so what parts of that can we take
on and that's where we did the
partnership with slor luoda so it's like
okay before you have a display you can
get normal looking glasses that can have
a camera they can have a microphone
great audio can capture content can um
um and you can stream video at this
point but the most important feature at
this point is the ability to access meta
Ai and just kind of have kind of a full
AI there multimodal because it has has
camera um and I mean that product is
starting at $300 and you know initially
I kind of thought hey this is sort of on
the technology path to building full
holographic glasses at this point I
actually just think both are going to
exist longterm right I think that there
are going to be people who want the full
holographic glasses and I think that
there are going to be people who prefer
kind of the superior form factor or
lower price of a device where they are
primarily optimizing for getting AI um I
also think there's going to be a range
of things in between right so there's
the full kind of field of view that we
that you just saw right 70° really wide
field of view for glasses um but I think
that there are other products in between
that too there's like a heads up display
version which um you know for that you
probably just need you know 20
30° you can't do
kind of the full kind of world Holograms
where you're interacting with things
like you're not going to play ping pong
in in 30 Dee field of view um but you
can communicate with AI um you can text
your friends you can get directions um
you can see the content that you're
capturing um so I there's a lot there
that's going to be compelling and at
each step along this Continuum from
display list to small display to kind of
full holographic you're packing more
technology in so each step up is going
to be a little more expensive um is
going to have a little more constraints
on the form factor even though I think
we'll get them all to be attractive
you'll be able to do the the kind of
simpler ones and much smaller form
factors permanently um and then of
course there's the mixed reality
headsets which kind of took a different
direction which is going towards the
same vision
but on that we said okay well we're not
going to try to fit into a glasses form
factor for that one we're going to say
okay we're going to really go for all
the compute that we want and we're going
to say okay this is going to be more of
like a heads goggles form factor and my
guess is that that's going to be a thing
long term too because there are a bunch
of uses where people want the full
immersion um and you know if you're
sitting at your desk and working for a
long period of time you might want the
more computing power than you're going
to be able to get but but I I I think
that there's no doubt that kind of what
you saw with Orion is the I think kind
of quintessential vision of what people
what at least kind of I thought and and
continue to think is going to be the
next multi billion person major
Computing platform and then kind of all
these other things are going to get
built out around it it's my
understanding that you originally hoped
Orion would be a consumer product when
you first set out to build it yeah yeah
Orion was meant to be our first consumer
product and we weren't sure if we were
going to be able to pull it off I mean
in general it's probably turned out
significantly better than our kind of
50/50 estimates of what it would be but
we didn't get there on everything that
we wanted to I think we we still wanted
to be a little smaller um a little
brighter like a little bit higher
resolution um and a lot more affordable
before we kind of put it out there as a
product and and look we have line of
sight to all those things so I think um
so so I I think we'll we'll probably
have the thing that was going to be the
V2 end up being the consumer product and
we're going to use Orion with developers
to basically cultivate the software
experience that way by the time we're
ready to ship something it's going to be
much more dialed in but to be clear
you're not selling Orion at all I guess
what I'm wondering is when you made the
call I think it was around 2022 to say
oryan is going to just be internal kind
of dev kit um how did you feel about
making that call was there any part of
you that was like man I really wish this
could have just been the consumer
product we had built I me I always want
to ship stuff quickly and and all that
um
but I think it was the right thing I
mean I think on this product I think
that there is
a there's a pretty clear set of
constraints that I think you want to hit
MH um especially around the form Factor
right I mean it it is very helpful for
us that sort of chunkier glasses are
kind of ascendant in the fashion world
because that allows us to build glasses
that are going to be fashionable but
also Tech forward but
um even so I'd say you know these are
unmistakably glasses they're reasonably
comfortable they're you know under 100
gram I them for two hours and I couldn't
really tell yeah but but I mean I think
we aspire to building things that like
look really good right and and I think
this is like good glasses but I I I
wanted it to be a little a little
smaller so it can fit within like really
fashionable right when people see the
ray bands there's no compromise on
fashion it's like like part of why I
think people like them is yeah you get
all this functionality but even when
you're not using it they're great
glasses and I I think for the future
version of Orion that's the Target too
we want to make it so that um you know
most of the time you're going through
your day you're not Computing right and
or it's or something is happening in the
background or something but um so it
just needs to be good in order for you
to kind of want to keep it on your face
and I I feel like we're almost there I
think we made we've made more progress
than anyone else in the world that I'm
aware of um but it didn't quite hit my
bar um and similarly on price um these
are going to be more expensive than the
ray bands right I mean there's just a
lot more Tech that's going in them but
you know we do want to have it be within
a consumer price point and um this was
this was outside that race so I wanted
to wait until we could get to that range
in order to to have something that we sh
are you imagining that the first
commercial version whenever it is in the
next couple few years will it be a
developer focused product that you're
selling publicly you want it to be a
consumer ready and that's why I'm asking
about the strategy because Apple snap
others have decided to do developer
Focus plays and get the hardware kind of
going with developers early but you're
kind of are you saying you're skipping
that and you just want cons we are using
this as a developer kit just primarily
inter and maybe with a handful of
Partners but I mean I think at this
point meta is by far the kind of Premier
developer of augmented reality and
virtual and mixed reality software and
Hardware in the world so you can think
about it as a developer kit but we just
have a lot of that talent inous and then
we also have well-developed Partnerships
with a lot of folks externally who we
can go to and work with them as well so
it's um I don't think we need to go
announce a dev kit that like that kind
of arbitrary developers can go buy to
get access to the talent that we need to
go build out the platform I think we're
kind of in a place where we can work
with partners and and do that but that's
absolutely what we're going to do over
the next few years we're going to hone
the experience and figure out what we
need to do to to to Really nail it when
it's ready to ship a lot has been
written about how much you're spending
on reality labs and if you I don't you
probably can't have an exact number but
if you were to guesstimate the cost of
just building Orion over the last 10
years are we talking five plus billion
more than that um yeah probably probably
yeah yeah but I mean
overall um for reality labs for a while
a lot of people thought of all of that
budget is going towards virtual and
mixed reality and I actually think we've
said publicly that our glasses programs
are are a bigger budget than our virtual
and mixed reality programs um but that
goes across all of them right so that's
the kind of full AR that's um the
displaylist glasses like all the work
we're going to do on on um on rayan and
we just announced the expanded
partnership with luoda luoda great
company we've had a great experience
working with them they designed so many
great glasses and I think you know
working with them to to do even more um
is is is going to be really exciting so
there there's a lot more to do there on
on all of these things how does this
partnership work uh and this renew that
you just did with them how is it
structured what is this deal like you
know I think it was more of just a kind
of commitment from companies that we're
feeling pretty good about how this is
going and we're going to build a lot
more glasses together and part of the
way it works is um you know rather than
having sort of doing one generation and
then designing the Next Generation I
think by having a longer term
partnership it allows the teams to not
just have to worry about one thing at a
time then like
okay is this one going to be good
and then how do we build on that for the
next one now we can start like a
multi-year road map of many different
devices knowing that we're going to be
working together for a long time so I'm
optimistic about that that's sort of how
we work internally right we don't just I
mean sometimes when you're early on you
you definitely want to learn from each
device launch but
um when there are things that you're
committed to I don't think you want the
team to feel like okay if we don't get
the short-term Milestone then like we're
going to cancel the whole thing right um
so are you buying mistake in elsur
lexotica um yeah I think we've talked
about investing in them it's it's not
going to be a a kind of major thing I'd
say it's more of a of a symbolic um
thing I me we we we want to have this to
be a long-term partnership and um as as
part of that um I thought that this
would be kind of a nice gesture and I
fundamentally believe in them a lot I
mean I think that they're going to go
from being a the premier glasses company
in the world to I think one of the major
technology companies in the world I me
my vision for for them and how I think
about it is that if you think about like
how Samsung in in Korea kind of um made
it so that Samsung that Korea became one
of the main hubs of building phones in
the world I mean I think that this is
probably kind of one of the best shots
for Europe and Italy in particular to
become a major hub for manufacturing and
building and designing the next major
category of of smart glasses and sorry
of computing platforms overall so um
and and I think that they're they're
kind of all in on that now and and it's
been this interesting question um
because you know they have they have
such a good business and such deep
competence in in the areas and I I've
gotten more of an appreciation of how
strong of a technology they company they
are in their own way right designing
lenses designing the materials that you
need to make um fashionable glasses that
can be light enough but um but also kind
of like feel good um they have they
bring a huge amount that I think is um
people in kind of our world the tech
World probably don't necessarily see but
but I think that they're really well set
up for the future so I I I believe in
the partnership I'm really excited about
the work that we're doing together and
fundamentally I think that that's just
going to be a massively successful
company in the future um is is it set up
to where they control the designs or and
you provide the tech stack or do you
collaborate on the design like I I think
we collaborate on on everything it's
it's actually I mean part of working
together is
um you kind of build a joint culture
over time and there were a lot of really
sharp people over there who I think it
took maybe a couple versions for us
really to gain an appreciation for how
we each of us approach things because um
you know they really think about things
from this like fashion manufacturing
lens selling optical devices perspective
um and we obviously come at it from uh
kind of consumer electronics AI umof
software perspective but I think over
time we just kind of appreciate each
other's perspectives on things a lot
more and I mean I I'm like constantly
talking to them about things to get
their ideas on different things I mean
but you know when Partnerships are
working well when you reach out to them
to get their opinion on things that are
not actually currently in the scope of
what you're working on together and and
because I I do that frequently with um
with Rocco who runs their wearables and
Franchesco who's their their uh their
CEO it's um and our team does that too
with with like a large part of the
working group over there it's um it's
it's a good crew they're they they kind
of they share good values they're
they're really sharp and like I said I I
believe in them a lot and I think it's
going to be a very successful
partnership and Company yeah how many
Rayband metas have you sold so far I
don't know if we've given a number on
that but I know it's asking yeah it's um
it's going very well uh you know one of
the things I think is interesting is we
we underestimated demand so part of you
know one thing that is very different in
the world of consumer electronics than
software is um there are fewer kind of
Supply constraints in software there are
some I mean like some of the stuff that
we're rolling out like voice on meta AI
um we need to meter it as we're rolling
it out because we need to make sure we
have enough inference capacity to to
handle it but fundamentally we'll
resolve that um in weeks right but for
manufacturing it's like you make these
concrete decisions like okay are we
setting up four manufacturing lines or
six
and you know each one it was a big
upfront capex investment and you're
basically deciding upfront the velocity
at which you're going to be able to
generate Supply before you know what the
demand is so on this one we
thought that Rayband meta was probably
going to
sell three or five times more than the
first version did and we just
dramatically underestimated what the so
now we're in this position where it's
actually been somewhat hard for us to
gauge what the real demand is because
they're sold out you can't get them so
if you can't get them like then then how
do you know where where the actual curve
is but but that's um we're basically
getting to the point where that's
resolved now we we kind of adjusted we
made the decision to build more more
manufacturing lines they took some time
to do it they're online now we're kind
of you know it's it's not just about
being able to make them you need to get
them into all the stores and get the
distribution right we feel like that's
in a pretty good place now so I'd say
over the rest of this year we're going
to start getting a real sense of the
demand but while that's going on the
glasses keep getting better because of
overthe a AI updates so the hardware
doesn't necessarily change even though
um we keep shipping new frames and new
type of you know they're adding more
Transitions lenses because people want
to wear them indoors um and that's an
interesting thing because I mean
people sunglasses are a little more
discretionary so I think a lot more
people early on were thinking hey yeah
I'll try I'll experiment with this with
sunglasses I'm not going to make these
my primary glasses
um now we're seeing a lot more people
say hey this actually really useful I
want to be able to wear them inside I
want them to be my primary glasses so
whether that's kind of working with them
through the optical Channel or the
transitions that's an important part but
the the AI part of this um is also it
just keeps getting better I we talked
about it at um at connect I mean
basically the ability to now you over
the next few months when we roll This
Out real-time translations you're
traveling abroad someone's speaking
Spanish to you you just get it
translated into English in your ear just
roll out to more and more languages over
time I think we're starting with a few
we'll kind of hit more over time um I
tried that well actually I didn't try
real time but I tried looking at a menu
in French and it translated into English
and then I was like at the end I was
like what is Euro and dollar actually
and it did that too and then I'm also
starting to see the Continuum of this to
Orion in the sense of the utility
aspects you could say look at this and
remind me about it at 8:00 p.m. tonight
and then it sinks with
so I guess it's not replacing the phone
but it's augmenting what I would do with
my phone like how are these glasses
going to be more deeply tied to Med AI
over time um seems like they're getting
closer and closer all the time but yeah
well well I think Medi is becoming a
more and more prominent feature of the
glasses right there's more stuff that
you can do so you just mentioned
reminders as another example it's like
now that is just going to work and now
your glasses can remind you of things
and so okay you can look at a phone
number and say call this phone number
and then it calls on the phone you know
just will just add more capabilities
over time and some of better are model
updates right so like okay now it has
llama 3.2 but um but some of it is is
kind of software development around it
like reminders you don't get for free
just because we updated the model that's
kind we have this big software
development effort and um and and we're
kind of adding features continuously and
developing the ecosystem right so you
get more apps so know Spotify and all
these different things kind of kind of
can work more natively so the glasses
just more and more useful um which I
think is also going to increase demand
over time and how does it interact with
phones I
mean like you said I don't think people
are getting rid of phones anytime soon
um the way I kind of think about this is
that when phones became the primary
Computing platform we didn't get rid of
computers we just kind of shifted right
so I I I don't know if you have this
experience but at some point in the
early 2010s I noticed that I'd be
sitting at my desk in front of my
computer and I'd just pull out my phone
to do things yeah and I think what's
going to happen it's not like we're
going to throw away our phones but I
think
slowly
um we're just going to start doing more
things with our glasses and leaving our
phones in our pockets more and it's not
like we're done with our computers and I
don't think we're going to be done with
our phones for a while but there's a
pretty clear path where um where you're
just going to use your glasses for more
and more things and over time I the
glasses are also going to be able to be
powered by wrist-based wearables or
other wearables so you're going to wake
up one day 10 years AG from now and
you're not even going to need to bring
your phone with you now you're still
going to have a phone but I I think like
more of the time people are going to
leave it in their pocket or leave it in
their bag or eventually even some of the
time leave it in their at home and um I
think there will just be this sort of
gradual shift to glasses becoming the
main way that we do Computing it's
interesting that we're talking about
this right now because I feel like
phones are becoming kind of boring and
stale you know like I I just was like
looking at the new iPhone and it's
basically the same as the year before
people are doing foldables but like it
feels like people have kind of run out
of ideas on phones and that they're kind
of at their natural end State and I
wonder you know when you see something
like the rayb bands and how people have
really gravitated to them in a way
that's surprised you guys and I think
surprised all of us but it's also just
like people want to interact with
technology in different ways now and I
think
AI like you said at the beginning like
the way that AI is intersected with this
is just kind of like a aha thing for
people that honestly for me I didn't
expect it to click as quickly as it did
but like when I got WID listed for the
AI I was like walking around my backyard
and like using it and I was like oh like
I it's obvious now where this is going
so it feels like we're like I was saying
at the beginning it feels like things
are finally you can see where it's going
whereas Before It's been a lot of like
R&D and talking about it but like these
the ray bands are kind of a signifier of
that and I'm wondering if you agree with
that I agree I mean I still think it's
early um I think you really want to be
able
to not just ask the AI
questions but ask it to do things yeah
and know that it's going to reliably go
do it and we're starting with simple
things right so voice control of your
glasses although you can do that on
phones too things like ERS although you
can generally do that on on phones too
but I think as the model capabilities
grow over the next couple of generations
and you get more of you know what people
call these agentic um capabilities I
think it's it's going to start to get
pretty exciting for what it's worth I I
I also think that all the AI work is
going to make phones a lot more exciting
um it's the most exciting thing I think
that has happened to our family of apps
road map in a long time is all of the
all the AI things that we're building so
um you know if I were trying to design
what you know the next few versions of
iPhone or Google's phone should be I
mean I I think that there's a long and
interesting road map of things that they
can go do with AI that um as an app
developer we can't so um so I think that
that's like a pretty exciting and and
interesting thing for them to go do
which I I assume that they will on the
AI uh social media piece one of the
Wilder things that your team told me you
guys are going to start doing is showing
people AI generated imagery personalized
to them in feed I think it's starting as
an experiment but like if you're a
photographer you would see Meta AI
generating content that's maybe
personalized for you alongside content
from the people you follow yeah and
that's this idea that I've been thinking
about of AI and kind of invading social
media so to speak um maybe you don't
like the word invading but you know what
I mean and what does that what does that
do to how we how we relate to each other
as humans like how much AI stuff and AI
Genera stuff is going to be filling
feeds in the near future uh in your
view well here's how I Comm at this so
in the history of running the company
where we've been building these apps for
20 years every call it 3 to five years
there's some new major format that comes
along
that is typically additive to the
experience right so you know initially
people kind of updated their profiles
then they were able to post statuses
that were texts then then links
um you got photos early on um then you
added videos um then with
mobile basically you know snap invented
stories the first version of that and
that became a a pretty kind of widely
used format
um the whole version of short form
videos I think is is sort of a still
ascendant format but you basically
um at each step along the way
you want
to right it's like you keep on making
the system richer by having more
different types of content that people
can um can share and and different ways
to express themselves and when you look
out for the next 10 years of okay if
this trend seems to happen where every 3
five years whatever the pace is that
there are new
formats I think given the pace of change
in the tech industry I think you'd bet
that that continues or accelerates and I
think you'd bet that probably most of
the new formats are going to be kind of
AI connected in some way given that
that's the kind of driving theme for the
industry at this point so given that
kind of set of assumptions
um we're sort of trying to understand
what are the things that are most useful
to people within that um there's one
vein of this which is helping people and
creators make better content using AI
right so that's um that I think is going
to be pretty clear right just make it
like super easy for like aspiring
creators or Advanced creators to make
much better stuff than they would be
able to otherwise
um that can take the format of like all
right like my daughter is writing a book
and she wants it Illustrated and like we
sit down together and work with meta Ai
and imagine to help her come up with
images to illustrate it um it's like
okay that's like a thing that's like she
didn't have the capability to do that
before she's not a graphic designer but
now she kind of has that that that that
ability I think that that's going to be
pretty cool
um then I think that there's a version
where you have just this great
diversity of AI agents that are as part
of the system and this I think is a big
difference between our vision of AI and
most of the other companies is yeah
we're building meta AI as as kind of the
main assistant that you can build that's
sort of equivalent to you know the
singular assistant that maybe like a
Google or an open AI or different folks
are building
but it's not really the main thing that
we're doing um you know our main vision
is that we think that there are going to
be a lot of these right it's every
business all the hundreds of millions of
small businesses um you know just like
they have a website and an email address
and a social media account today I think
that they're all going to have an AI
that helps them interact with their
customers in the future that does some
combination of sales and customer
support and all that um I think all the
creators are basically going to want
some version of this that basically
helps them interact with their Community
when they're just limited by they don't
have enough hours in the day to interact
with all the messages that are coming in
and um they want to make sure that they
can show some love to to people in their
in their Community um and those I think
are just the two most obvious ones that
even if we just did those that's many
hundreds of millions but then there's
going to be all this more creative stuff
that's ugc that people create for that
are kind of Wilder use cases that they
want and our view is okay these are all
going to like live across these social
networks and Beyond
and
um I I don't think that they should just
be constrained to waiting until someone
messages them right I think that they're
going to have their own profiles they're
going to be creating content people will
be able to follow them if they want um
you'll be able to comment on their stuff
um they may be able to comment on your
stuff if you're connected with them I
there will obviously be different
different logic and rules but that
that's one way that there's going to be
just a lot more kind of AI participants
in the kind of broader social construct
that we have and then I think you get to
the test that you mentioned which is
maybe the most abstract which is just
having kind of the central meta AI
system directly generate content for you
based on what we think is going to be
interesting to you and putting that in
your feed and on that you know I think
that there's this been there's been this
trend over time where the feeds started
off as primarily and exclusively
content from people you you followed
friends um I guess it was friends early
on then it kind of broadened out to okay
you followed a set of friends and
creators and then it got to a point
where the algorithm was good enough
where we're actually showing you a lot
of stuff that you're not following
directly because um in some ways that's
a better way to show you more
interesting stuff than only constraining
it to things that you've chosen to
follow
and I think the next logical jump on
that is like okay we're showing you
content from your friends and creators
that you're following and creators that
you're not following that are generating
interesting things and you just add on
to that a layer of okay and we're also
going to show you content from um that's
generated by by an AI system that might
be something that you're interested in
now how big do any of these segments get
I think it's really hard to know until
you build them out over time but it
feels like it is a category in the world
that's going to exist and um how big it
gets is kind of dependent on the
execution and how good it is why do you
think it needs to exist as a new
category I'm still wrestling with why
people want this I get the companionship
stuff that character Ai and some
startups have already shown there's like
a market for um and you've talked about
how Med is already being used for role
playing and but the big idea is that AI
has been used to inter intermediate in
feed how humans reach each other and now
all of a sudden AIS are going to be in
feeds with us well I think the main
difference and that feels big yeah but
in a lot of ways the big change already
happened which is people getting content
that they weren't following and the
definition of feeds in social
interaction has changed very
fundamentally in the last 10 years now
in Social
systems most of the direct interaction
is happening in more private forums in
messaging our groups and this is one of
the reasons I think why we were late
with reals initially to competing with
Tik to is cu we we hadn't made this
mental shift where we kind of felt like
no feed is where you interact with
people actually increasingly feat is
becoming a place where you discover
content that you then take to your
private forums and interact with people
there so a lot of the the the way that I
interact with people it's like yeah I'll
still have the thing where a friend will
post something and I'll I'll comment on
it and engage directly in feed um again
you know this is additive you're adding
more over time
um but the main way that you engage with
reals isn't necessarily that you know
you go into the reals comments and
comment and talk to people you don't
know it's like you see something funny
and you send it to friends in a group
chat right and I I think that that
Paradigm will absolutely continue with
AI and all kinds of interesting content
so it is facilitating connections with
people um but I think already we're in
this mode where our connections through
social media are shifting to more
private places and the role of Feed in
the ecosystem is more as a you know I
call it a discovery engine content to
kind of um you know of ice breakers or
interesting kind of topic starters for
the conversations that you're having um
across this like broader spectrum of
places where you're interacting do you
worry about people interacting with AIS
like this making
people less likely to talk to other
people like it reducing the engagement
that we have with humans the sociology
that I've seen on this is that most
people have way fewer friends physically
than they would like to have I think
people cherish the kind of human
connection that they have and the more
we can do to make that feel more real
and give you more reasons to connect
whether it's through something funny
that shows up so you can message someone
or a pair of glasses that lets like you
your sister show up as a hologram in
your living room when you you know she
lives across the country and you
wouldn't be able to see her otherwise
like that's always kind of our main
bread and butter and the thing that
we're
doing but you know in addition to
that I mean if the you know the average
person I think you know maybe they'd
like to have 10 friends and I mean
there's the stat that it's like it's
sort of sad but I think the the average
American feels like they have fewer than
three like real kind of close friends so
does this take away from that my guess
is no I I think that what's going to
happen is it's going to help um give
people more of the support that they
need and give people more kind of
reasons and ability to connect with
either a broader range of people or more
deeply with the people who they care
about how are you feeling about how
threads is doing these days I mean
threads on fire it's great I mean it's I
mean these things it's like there's only
so quickly that something can get to a
billion people so it's G to you know
we'll kind of keep on pushing on it over
I've heard it's still using Instagram a
lot for growth like I'm guess I'm
wondering when do you see it getting to
like a I mean of Standalone growth
driver on its own I mean I think that
these things all connect to each other
so I I don't I mean I think threads
helps Instagram I think Instagram helps
threads I don't I don't know that we
have some strategic goal which is like
like make it so that threads is
completely disconnected from Instagram
or Facebook I actually think we're going
the other direction it started off just
connected to Instagram and now we also
connected it so that the content can
show up now taking a step back I me we
just talked about how for most people
they're interacting in more private
forums if you're a Creator what you want
to do is have your content show up
everywhere right because you're trying
to build the biggest community that you
can in these different places so it's
this huge value um for for people if
they can generate a real or a video or
some text based content and now you can
post it in Threads Instagram Facebook um
and more places over time so um so I
think the direction there is generally
kind of more flow not less and kind of
more interoperability and that's that's
why um I've been I've been kind of
pushing on that as as a theme over time
I'm not even sure what x is anymore but
I think what it used to be and what
Twitter used to be was a place where you
went when news was happening I know you
and the company seem to be distancing
yourself from recommending news but with
threads it feels like
that's what people want and people
thought threads might be but it seems
like you all are intentionally saying we
don't want threads to actually be that
yeah I mean it's interesting there's
there are different ways to to look at
this um I always looked at Twitter not
as primarily about realtime news but as
a kind of short form primarily text
discussion oriented app to me the
fundamental defining aspect of that
format is that you don't when you make a
post the comments aren't subordinate to
the Post
the comments are kind of at a pure level
and that is a very different
architecture than every other type of of
um of social network that's out there
and
um it's a subtle difference but Within
These systems these subtle differences
lead to very different emerging
behaviors so because of that people can
take they can Fork discussions and it
makes it a very good discussion oriented
platform now news is one thing that
people like discussing um but it's not
the only thing and I always looked at
Twitter and I was like
hey this is such a wasted opportunity
like this is clearly a billion person
app um you know maybe in the modern day
when you have multiple like many
billions of people using social apps it
should be multiple billions of people
and for whatever reason I mean there was
there are a lot of things that have been
complicated about Twitter and the
corporate structure and all that but
they just weren't quite getting there
and
eventually you know I kind of thought
hey I think we can do this I think we
can get this like build out the
discussion platform in in a way that can
get to a billion people and be more of a
ubiquitous social platform that I think
achieves the um the fullness of what
what what what it like its full
potential but our version of this is we
wanted to be a Kinder place right we
don't want to start with kind of the
like direct kind of head-to-head combat
of news um and especially politics and
um you feel like that constrains the
growth of the product at all I mean I
think I think we'll see we'll run the
experiment um or that that needs to
exist in the world cuz I feel like with
x's seeming implosion it's not really
existing anymore maybe I'm biased to
someone in the media but I do think I do
think people want when something big
happens in the world they want an app
that they can go to and see everyone
that they follow talking about it
immediately yeah
well there's not we're not the only
company I there's there were like a ton
of different competitors and different
companies doing things and you know I
mean I think that there's a talented
team over at Twitter and and um so so I
I I I wouldn't write them off um and you
know then obviously there's all these
other folks and there's a lot of
startups that are doing stuff so I don't
feel like
we have to go with that first I I think
that like maybe we get there over time
or maybe we decide that it's enough of a
zero sum trade or maybe even a negative
sum trade where like that that use case
should exists somewhere but maybe that
use case prevents a lot more usage um
and and kind of a lot more value in
other places because it makes it a
somewhat less friendly place and
um I I don't think we know the answer to
that yet but I I do think the last 10
years eight years of um of our
experience has been that the political
discourse is
um it's It's Tricky right it's on the
one hand it's obviously a very important
thing in society and on the other hand I
don't think it leaves people feeling
good so I'm torn between these two
values on the one hand I I think like
people should be able to have this kind
of open discourse and that's good on the
other hand I don't want to design a
product that makes people angry right
it's like I mean is like there's an
informational lens for looking at this
and there's kind of a you're designing a
product and like what's the feel of the
product right it's like I think anyone
who's designing a product cares a lot
about how the thing feels and but you
Rec you recognize the importance of that
discussion happening in the world I
think it's useful and look we don't
block it you know we we just make it so
that um you know for the content where
you're following people if you want to
talk to your friends about it if you
want to talk to them about it in
messaging there can be groups about it
um if you follow people it can show up
in your feed but we don't go out of our
way to recommend that content when
you're not following it and I think that
that has been a healthy balance for us
and for getting our products to
generally feel the way that we want
um and you know culture changes over
time maybe the stuff will be like a
little bit less polarized and anger
inducing at some point and maybe it'll
be possible to have more of that while
also at the same time having a product
where we're proud of how it feels but
until then I think we we just we want to
we want to design a product that um yeah
people can get the things that they want
but um but you know fundamentally we we
um I care a lot about how people feel
coming away from the products do you see
this decision to to downrank political
content for people that who aren't being
followed um in feed as a political
decision I guess because I don't know
you're also at the same time you know
not really saying much about the
election this year you're not donating
you've said you kind of want to stay out
of it now and I see the way the
company's acting and it reflects your
personal kind of way you're operating
right now and I'm wondering like how
much more of it is also about what you
and the company have gone through and
the political environment and not
necessarily just what users are telling
you sure um like is there a through line
there I I mean I'm sure it's all
connected I think in this case it wasn't
a trade-off between those two things
because this actually was what our
community was telling us and people were
saying generally we don't want so much
politics it it like this isn't you know
like we don't feel good like like I we
want like we we want content to that we
want more stuff from our friends and
family we want more stuff from our
interests
um so that that was kind of the primary
driver but I think it's definitely the
case that our corporate experience on
this um shaped this and there's a big
difference between something being
political and being partisan and the
main thing that I care about is making
sure that we can be seen as a
nonpartisan and you know as much as
something can in the world in 2024 be
sort of like a trusted institution by as
many people as possible and um I just
think that the partisan politics is so
tough in the world right now that um
I've made the decision that I I kind of
feel like for me and for the company um
best thing to do is to try to be as
nonpartisan as possible in in in all of
this and and kind of be be kind of as as
neutral and and distance ourselves as
much as possible and it's not just the
substance I also think the perception
matters so I think um so that's why you
maybe you know it doesn't matter on our
platforms whether I endorse a candidate
or not but like I don't even I don't
want to go anywhere near
um and yeah I mean you could say that's
a political strategy um but I think it's
um I think for where we are in the world
today it's very hard almost every
institution has become partisan in some
way and we are just trying to resist
that and maybe I'm too naive and maybe
that's impossible but that's we're going
to try to do that on the acquired
podcast recently you said that the
political miscalculation was a 20-year
mistake and a brand from a brand
perspective and was going to take
another 10 or so for you to fully work
through that cycle yeah what makes you
think it's such a lasting thing because
you look at like how you personally have
kind of evolved over the last couple
years and I think perception of the
company has evolved and I'm wondering
like what you meant by saying it's going
to take another 10 years I'm just
talking about where our brand is and our
reputation are compared to where I think
they would have been I mean there's no
doubt that even now here and okay yeah
sure maybe things have improved somewhat
over the last few years you can feel the
trend but it's still significantly worse
than it was in 2016 um you know it's I
mean the internet industry overall um
and I think our company in particular um
just were seeing way more positively and
now look there were real issues right so
so I I I I think that it's always very
difficult to talk about this stuff in a
nuanced way because
um I think to some Dee before 2016
everyone was sort of too Rosy about the
internet overall and didn't talk enough
about the issues and then the pendulum
sort of swung and people only talked
about the issues and didn't talk about
the stuff that was positive and it was
all both there the whole time um but so
when I talk about this I don't mean to
you know come across as simplistic or um
you know you guys didn't do anything
wrong or anything like or that there
weren't issues with the Internet or
things like that I mean obviously every
year you know whether it's politics or
other things there always things that
you look back at and you're like hey
yeah like if I were playing this
perfectly I would have done these things
differently and
um but I do think it's the case that I
didn't really know how to react to
something as big of of of sort of a
shift in the world as what happened and
it took me a while to find my footing
and and I I I do think that It's Tricky
when you're caught up in these kind of
big debates and you're not kind of
experienced or sophisticated and
engaging with that I think um you can
make some big missteps and I I do think
that some of the things that um that
that that we were accused of over time
it just you know I think it's just been
pretty clear at this point you know now
that all the investigations have been
done that like they they weren't true um
and you're talking about like Cambridge
analytica I think C analytica is a good
example of something that it's like
people thought that like all this data
had been taken and that um it had been
used in this campaign and out wasn't and
like and yeah so it's like all the stuff
okay the data wasn't even you know
accessible to the to the developer and
and we'd fix the issue like five years
ago so um but in the moment it was like
really hard for us to to kind of have a
rational discussion about that and I
think part of the challenge is that um
you know for the general population I
think a lot of people they read the
initial headlines and they don't
necessarily read the um you know and and
and frankly you know a lot of the media
I don't think was like as loud to write
about when all the invest concluded that
said that there weren't um that like a
lot of the initial allegations were just
completely wrong so I I think that's
like a that's a real thing so okay so
you take these hits and I didn't really
know how to how to kind of push back on
that and maybe some of it you can't but
I I like to think that I think we could
have played this some of this stuff
differently um and I do think it was
certainly the case that when you take
responsibility for things that are not
your fault you become sort of a weak
Target for people who are looking to
blame other things and find a target for
them and it's sort of like um this is a
different part of of of it's it's
somewhat related to this but when you
think about like like litigation
strategy for the company one of the
reason why I hate settling lawsuits is
that it it basically sends a signal to
people that hey this is a company that
settles lawsuits so maybe like we can
sue them and they'll settle lawsuits so
um so you wouldn't write a blank check
to the government like Google did for
its antitrust case no I think like I
think the right kind of way to approach
this is when you believe in something
you fight really hard for it and I think
this is a repeat game this isn't like
this it's not like there's a single
issue and we're going to be around for a
long time and I think it's it's really
important that people know that we're a
company that has conviction and that we
we believe in what we're doing and we're
going to back that up and defend
ourselves and I think that that kind of
sets the right tone um now now I think
over the next 10 years I think we're
sort of digging ourselves back to
neutral on this and but I I like to
think that if we hadn't had a lot of
these issues we would have made progress
over the last 10 years too so I sort of
give it this time frame maybe 20 years
is too long maybe it's 15 but it's hard
to know with politics it feels like
mental health and youth mental health
may be the next wave of this that that I
think is the next big fight and and on
that you know I think a lot of the data
on this I I think is just not where the
narrative is the The Narrative yeah I
think the narrative is a lot of people
sort of take it as um as if it's like an
assumed thing that there's some link and
like I think the majority of the of the
high quality research that's out there
suggests that there's no causal
connection like a at kind of a broad
scale between between these things so um
now look I mean I think that that's
different from saying like in any given
issue like was is someone bullied should
we try to stop bullying yeah of course
um
but yeah overall um I I I think that
this is this is one
where there there are a bunch of these
cases I think that there will be a lot
of litigation around them uh and it's
one where we're trying to make sure that
the academic research that that shows
something that that I think is you it um
you know to me it sort of foots more
with what I've seen of how the platforms
operate but it's counter to what a lot
of people think and I think that that's
going to be a reckoning that we'll have
to have is is basically when as the the
kind of the majority of the highquality
academic research um kind of gets shown
is like Okay can people accept this and
I think that's going to be a really
important um set of debates over the
next year at the same time you guys have
acknowledged there's affordances in the
product like the teen roll out with
Instagram recently that you can make to
make the product a better experience for
young people yeah and I think this is an
interesting part of the balance is
um you can play a role in trying to make
something better even if the thing
wasn't caused by you in the first place
like there's no doubt that being being a
parent is really hard and there's a big
question of in this internet age where
we have phones
um what are the right tools that parents
need in order to be able to raise their
kids and like I think that we can play a
role in giving people controls over U
parental controls over the apps I think
that parental controls are also really
important because parents have different
ways that they want to raise their kids
or just like schooling and education
people have like very significantly
different local preferences for how they
want to raise their kids I don't think
that most people want some internet
company setting all the rules for this
either so obviously you know when there
are laws passed we'll we'll kind of
follow the the the government's
Direction and and and the laws on that
but I actually think the right approach
for us is to primarily kind of align
with parents to give them the tools that
they want to be able to raise their kids
in the way that they want and some
people are going to think that more
technology use is good that's sort of
how my parents you know Raised Me
growing Up um I think it worked pretty
well um some people are going to be kind
of more more um you know want to limit
it more and we want to give them the
tools to be able to do that but but I
don't think that this is you know
primarily or only a social media thing
um even even the parts of this that are
technology age verification I think
phones like the phone platforms have a
huge part of this this I mean it's um
yeah there's this big question of how do
you do age verification and I mean I can
tell you what the easiest way is which
is like all right like every time you go
do a payment on your phone I mean there
already is child um you know basically
like child age verification so I don't
really understand well I guess I
understand but I think it's it's it's
not very um you know excusable from my
perspective why apple and and and um I
guess to some extent Google don't want
to just extend the age verification that
they already have on their phones to be
a parental control for parents to to
basically be able to say what um you
what apps can my kids use right it's
hard for me to not see the logic in it
either I don't I don't really I think
they don't want to take
responsibility but maybe that's on
Congress then to pass who has to take
responsibility yeah yeah so and and and
we're going to do our part and we're
going to we're going to build the tools
that we can for for parents and for and
for teens um but it the end of the day
um I I and look I'm not saying it's all
the phone's fault either although I I
would say that like the ability to get
push notifications and get kind of
distracted is from my perspective seems
like a much greater contributor to
mental health issues than um than than
kind of a lot of the specific apps but
but there are things that that I think
everyone should should kind of try to
improve and work on um
but yeah I mean I that that's sort of
that's sort of my view on all that on
the regul piece as it relates to AI
you've been very vocal about what's
happening in the EU and uh you recently
signed an open letter and I believe it
was saying basically that you guys just
don't have Clarity on consent for
training how it's supposed to work um
and I'm wondering what you think needs
to happen there for things to move
forward because like Med AI is not
available in Europe new llama models are
not um is that something you see getting
resolved uh at all
I guess and what would it take yeah I
don't know it's it's a little hard for
me to parse the the European politics um
I have a hard time enough with American
politics I mean it's and and I'm I'm
American but
um so in theory my understanding of the
way this is supposed to work is they
they kind of passed this gdpr
regulation and you're supposed to have
this this idea of sort of a One-Stop
shop like home regulator who can
basically on behalf of the whole EU
interpret and enforce the rules and we
have our European headquarters and we
work with that regulator and you know I
think they're like okay they're pretty
tough on us and pretty firm but at least
when you're working with one regulator
you can kind of understand how are they
thinking about things and it's and you
can make progress and the thing that I
think has been
tricky is there there have been from
from my perspective a little bit of a
backslide where now you get all these
other um dpas across the continent sort
of also intervening and and trying to do
things and it just seems like more of an
kind of internal EU political thing
which is like okay do they want to have
this One-Stop shop and have Clarity for
companies so companies can act can kind
of like can execute or or do they just
want it to be this kind of very
complicated regulatory system and um I
look I think that's for them to out um
but but I know there's no doubt that
when you have like dozens of different
Regulators that can ask you kind of the
same questions about different things it
makes it a much more difficult
environment to build things do you do I
don't think that that's just us I think
that that's all the company but do you
understand the concern people have about
training data and creators even and this
idea that their data is being used for
these models they're not getting
compensated and the models are creating
a lot of value and I know you're giving
away llama but you're still you've got M
Ai and
I understand the frustration that people
have about that I think it's a naturally
bad feeling to be like oh my my data is
now being used in a new way that I have
no control or compensation over do you
do you sympathize with that yeah I mean
I think that there in any new medium and
Technology there's like the concepts
around fair use and like where are the
boundaries between what you have control
over right when you put something out in
the world to what degree do you still
get to control it and and kind of own it
and license it
um and I I think that all these things
are basically going to get need to get
you know relitigated and rediscussed in
the um in the in the AI era so I'm I get
it I I I think that these are these are
important questions I think this is not
like a completely novel thing to AI in
in the grand scheme of things I think it
was you a lot of them there were
questions about it with with the
internet overall too and with different
Technologies over time
um and but I think getting to clarity
that is going to be important so that
way the things that Society wants people
to build they can go build what is
Clarity look like to you there I mean I
think it starts with having some
framework of like okay what's the
process going to be if we're working
through that but but you don't see a
scenario where creators get like
directly compensated for the use of
their content I think that there's a lot
of different possibilities for how stuff
goes in the future now I do think that
there's this issue which is a lot of
like while psychologically I understand
what you're saying yeah I think
individual creators or Publishers tend
to
overestimate the value of their specific
content right so it's like okay maybe
like in in in like in the grand scheme
of this right so um so we have this set
of challenges with with um you know news
Publishers around the world which is
like okay they they're like a lot of
folks are constantly kind of asking to
be paid for the content and on the other
hand we have of our community which is
asking us to show less news because it
makes them feel bad right and I mean we
talked about that so it's like there's
this issue which is okay it's like
actually we're showing some amount of
the news that we're showing because we
think it's socially important against
what our community wants like if we were
actually just following our our our what
our what our community wants we'd show
even less than we're showing um and you
see that in the data that people just
don't like to engage with this stuff and
we've had these issues where sometimes
we like Publishers say okay if you're
not going to pay us then pull our cont
down and it's just like yeah Share Fine
pull pull your content down I mean that
sucks I'd rather people be able to share
it but but if but I think some to some
degree some of these questions have to
get tested by their negotiations and
they have to get tested by people
walking and and like and then at the end
once people walk you figure out where
the value really is right if if it if it
really is the case that that news was a
big thing the community wanted then I
mean look we're we're a big company we
could you know we we could probably you
know we pay for Content when it's
valuable to people we're just not going
to pay for Content when it's not
valuable to people um so I think that
you'll probably see a similar Dynamic
with AI which is my guess is that there
are going to be certain Partnerships
that get made when content is really
important and valuable um and i' guess
that there's probably a lot of people
who are kind of have a a concern about
like the feel of it like you're saying
but then when push comes to
shove if like if they demanded that we
take that we don't use their content
then we just wouldn't use their content
and it's not like you know that's going
to change the outcome of this stuff that
much I guess to bring this full circle
where we started uh as you're building
augmented reality glasses um and what
you've learned over just the societal
implications of the stuff you've built
over the last decade um how are you
thinking about this as it relates to
glasses at scale because you're
literally going to be augmented
augmenting reality which is a it's a
responsibility I think that's going to
be another platform too and you're going
to have a lot of these questions as well
I mean I think the interesting thing
about Holograms and augmented reality is
it's going to be this intermingling of
the physical and digital much more than
we've had in other platforms um where on
your phone it's like okay yeah we we
live a primarily physical world but then
you have the small window into this
digital world and I think we're going to
basically have this world in the future
that is
increasingly you know call it half
physical half digital or I don't know
60% physical 40% digital and it's like
and it's um going to be Blended together
and I think that there are going to be a
lot of interesting governance questions
around that right in terms of um like is
is kind of all of the digital stuff
that's overlaid physically going to fit
within sort of a
physical kind of
national regulation perspective or is it
sort of is it actually coming from a
different world or something you know
and and um I think these will all be
very interesting questions that we will
have a perspective I'm sure we're not
going to be right about every single
thing um I I think like the world will
kind of need to sort out where it wants
to be different countries will have
different values and take somewhat
different approaches on things and I
think that that's it's part of the
interesting process of this the the
tapestry of how it all gets built is
like is um you need to work through so
that it ends up being positive for you
know as many of the possible
stakeholders as possible more to come
yeah a lot to come yeah thanks Mark okay
cool good game good game you you haveen
anage that's all right I've played a few
more cool all right done